Stanford University
In the last quarter we studied classical mechanics
and Classical mechanics is fairly intuitive
The basic ideas are things that you can visualize
You can picture in your head the motion of the particles the motion of the objects
It gets a little hard when you start thinking of ten particles all at the same time
But, nevertheless, the whole thing is based on the concepts
drawn from pretty much everyday work
Of course it gets more abstract as you go along
The crazy French who are obsessed with elegance
kept making it more and more mathematically elegant
Lagrangians, Poisson Brackets, blah blah blah
turn out all to be tremendously important
The abstraction is not all that difficult to understand
And the basic concept is the concept of updating
Well before that, the concept of a space of state
What is a state of a system?
Even before that, the concept of a system
The closed, isolated system that doesn't interact with anything
and whose motion and whose evolution whose history you wish to predict
Classical mechanics is predictive it's deterministic
In the first concept as I said,
after the concept of a system is the concept of a state of a system
A system can have a collection of different state
We've talked about very simple examples,
The first state of the quarter last time
I just describe for you the most elementary simple system
consisting nothing more for example than the coin
Heads and tails, the only states of the systems are heads and tails
They form a mathematical set of states
Two of them for heads and tails, two points, one state, two states
And we can draw them as dots
This one stands for head, this one stands for tails
And, you know, it's easy to picture in your head
From there, we talked about equations of motion
Equations of motion or laws of evolution
for the very simple system of a couple of points
Heads, tails, we formulated some very very simple possible laws of motion
The simplest being if nothing happens
If you start with heads you stay with heads, heads, heads, heads
If you start with tails you stay with tails, tails, tails, tails
That was a very simple law of motion
More complicated motion begin with heads you get tails
If you begin with tails, you go to heads, and just oscillate back and forth
The basic ideas is the idea of updating
If you know everything there is to know about a system in any instant of time
Then classical mechanics, everything there is to know
essentially mean everything that is needed in order to predict the future
If you know everything there is to know
then classical mechanics consist of a set of equations
which tell you how to update the state given it's value at given time
and go from one time to the next
That basic idea, for example, well,
I don't think I need to describe the example again
We describe it at length the last time
And it's extremely intuitive in going from this very discrete example
to a world of continuous motion, indeed we have to abstract,
we have to replace the ideas of a small number of state
a finite number of configuration by an infinite number of configuration
For example the motion of a particle along a line
We have to label the state by points along the line as well as their velocities
So it does get more complicated but nevertheless
Classical physics consist of equation which tell you
how to update the states in any given time
And it's completely deterministic
And as I said, easy to visualize, at least by comparison easy to visualize
Because it makes use of the concept of the ordinary world
which out brain is hardwired to be able to understand
Now I always give a little sermon of this point and give it again
Probably you have heard it a dozen times
about the way one has to think of physics beyond classical physics
So we move past classical physics
I don't think it can be said enough, it's so rarely said
It's that once physics move past the realm of parameters
that has to do with ordinary experience
either objects which are so small,
they are far beyond what ordinary physics is all about
Or velocity which are so fast that far beyond ordinary velocities
When everyone move out of the range of parameters
that we were familiar with in ordinary experience
We inevitably run into things we cannot visualize
Nobody can visualize the motion of an electron
It's just you are not wired for it
Nobody can visualize four dimensional space or four dimensional space time
let along ten or eleven dimensions
It's not the way physicists have done
I often read some of the stuff that goes back and forth
between some people especially people in this class
about trying to explain to themselves to each other
or ask questions to each other about a certain abstract physical questions
And I know very much that a lot of the mistakes a lot of confusion
happens because of trying to visualize things
using old fashion or standard intuition you are hardwired for
You may think physicists good physicists
are especially good for visualizing things
They are not, I cannot visualize five, six dimension any better than you can
But I know how to use abstract mathematics to describe it
There is no substitutes, there is no substitutes for the process of abstracting
and using mathematics to describe the thing
which is beyond the ability to directly visualize
The example that I gave, I'm gonna do it again tonight,
I just want you to really focus on it and realize
you are not going to understand quantum mechanics by trying to visualize it
by some funny form of classical mechanics
What's more, you will always get it wrong
But just the idea of visualizing space of dimension of different three dimensions
In particular I always use the same, okay,
how many people here can visualize five dimensions?
And everybody would say, no
We can't, of course there will be a few freak() or clown in the class
who would say yeah I can do it I can do it
They couldn't , I know they couldn't
They can't visualize five dimensions
But they I began to realize although you have probably heard it before
that it's equally hard to directly visualize two dimensions
Okay I will say to the class how many people now can visualize two dimensions?
Almost everybody will raise their hands
And I would say, no you are wrong
Close your eyes and try to visualize two dimensions
They would say okay I see it I see two dimensional of curved space
What they are seeing is not two-dimensional curved space
What they are seeing is a two-dimensional surface embedded in three dimension
Even trying to see one dimensional space
One-dimensional space, abstract one dimensional space is just a line
You cannot see that line in your head
without seeing it as a line drawing in a plane
And the plane you can't see without seeing it as embedded in three dimensional
What's going on? I can do it,
I hate to tell you this but
you are a prisoner of your own neurological architecture
Your neural architecture is built for three dimension
Alright how you get around it?
You don't get around it by training yourself to see four or five dimension
You get around it by training yourself to think abstractly about it
If three dimensional space there is a point x y and z
In four dimensional space it's x y z and w
And you learn to manipulate the symbols
It's not to say that after a while
you don't start to gain a new kind of intuition for things
You do, but the intuition is not the process of physical visualization
as the same kind as you visualize a wave as the wave in the ocean
So I have warn you about that
And I will tell you quantum mechanics is as abstract as anything can be
Well perhaps things are getting a little bit more abstract now
But again, quantum mechanics is about things that
you evolutionarily developed neural structure
is not prepared to dealt with directly
How do you deal with it? Abstract mathematics
And relativity, this is also true with relativity
And it's worse in quantum mechanics   >> end o
Okay let's begin quantum mechanics
with a very very simplistic primitive question you can ask
What is the state, I think I can ask the most primitive question is
what is a system?
Now I don't think I can answer it,
it's sort of indefinable you thought of the idea of a system
and I don't think I would try to give it a definition
but in particular closed system
A closed system is a system at least temporarily
is not interacting with anything else
Isolated, it's not interacting with anything else
And so it can be describe by itself
as a lonesome entity with nothing else involved
In classical mechanics, or it's not even a question of classical mechanics
It's a question of classical logic
The whole logic of quantum mechanics
is different than the logic of classical mechanics
The logic of classical mechanics again begin
of course with a system I just describe
But the next step is the space of state
The collection of the possible states of the system
If the system is a discrete system like a point
Or a die, you know the six-faced die
It can have six states, of course a real die
a real genuine die in three-dimensional space of course
can be in all sort of orientation in infinitely many states
But what I mean by a die now was I mean in an abstract mathematical die
which whose state is consist of one of six numbers
The space of states is a set, one two three four five six
This is the space of states of a die
This is the space of states of a coin
Okay again the abstract coin which only has two states heads and tails
This will be heads this will be tails
The abstract space of a point particle moving along a line
What is that? Anybody know what that is?
What is the abstract space of a particle moving along a line?
Well, I will remind you the term of physics space
The space consist of the possible position of the particle
and the possible momentums, the possible velocities
And so for the particles moving on a line
The possible states of a system form a plane
And the plane has a position sometimes call q
and the momentum sometimes call p
And every point on that plane is a possible state of
a point particle moving along a line
What is a set? In this case it's the continuously infinite set	 of two dimension
In this case it's just two points, in this case it consist of six points
And now we can start building some logical concepts for classical physics
For example, concepts such as OR and AND what do they mean?
OR and AND are concept which apply to a collection of states
Let's consider a proposition, proposition such and such
The proposition could be, the die it's locate, has a value which is even
It's even value okay?
That's a subset of the state of space
In fact it consist of three of them if I'm not mistaken
Three are one, one three and five
And another proposition would be the die is odd
No did I say odd, odd or even whatever it is
Another overlapping set of configuration
Let's take another case, let's take two proposition,
one of which again is the die is odd
And another proposition is that the die is less than or equal to three
So let's see, it's one, three, five, it's two four six
And less than or equal to three is this set over here
So now there are overlapping sets
And we can ask concepts of AND and OR
For example the proposition that it is that
the die is both less than or equal to three
And odd is the intersection of these two subsets
One and three are odd are less than or equal to three
The concept of AND, AND in this subsets, the mathematical concept
is the intersection of two sets
It's the intersection of two sets, so it satisfied two things
That's the concept of AND
Given two proposition, each proposition is a collection of states
The concept of AND is intersection
What about the concept of OR?
OR becomes a concept of union
What does it say here, either it's less than or equal to three OR odd
It's the inclusive OR incidentally
Inclusive OR means it can be both
Alright that is not the intersection of two sets
It's the union of two sets, and union meaning everything in two sets
Everything here is either equal or less than three	OR it is odd, inclusively
both being allowed
So the inclusive OR translated into union
And the concept of AND is the intersection of sets
That's the logic of a classical reasoning to a logical stance
Here's a concept, two sets are completely none overlapping,
this one and that one
That simply means the AND statement of false
There is no state in there for which both statements are true
So the whole logic that it's connected with the space of state being a set
And it's the logic of set theory, we are not going through the logic of set theory
But it's important for me to tell you right now that
the logic of quantum mechanic is different
It's not based on the idea that the states of a system is set
The state of a system is something entirely different and only in certain limits
only in certain limits where system behaves classically
does whatever a space of states of quantum mechanics
Whatever it is,
does it approximately reduced to the concept of a mathematical set
In fact if I just tell you what it is, it's vector space
And we will talk about that
Alright but before we do,
before we start to talk about the abstract mathematics of abstract spaces
And spaces of states in quantum systems, let's talk about experiments
And describe the simplest possible system in quantum mechanics
It's the coin of quantum mechanics, a system with two states, heads and tails
We have to completely erase the blackboard to start over again
So we have some systems, whenever we measure that system
We measure something about the system, namely analog it's heads or tails
We either get heads or tails
Alright let's give that a mathematical notation
I'm not going to call it a coin, I'm going to call it a qubit
A qubit is a system which has two states, and qu stands for quantum
The analog for classical physics is call the c-bit, classical bit
And it's the simple idea of a coin, heads or tails
We gonna see that a qubit is a much more interesting well complicated for sure
But a much richer idea even though it has some sense as two states
Okay so the qubit, the qubit on it's measure -
I'm gonna talk about measuring in a moment - is either heads or tails
But let's describe it in another way
And give it a freedom the mathematical degree of freedom
And I'm gonna call that mathematical degree of freedom sigma
Sigma is the traditional name for the degree of freedom describe in a qubit
And sigma can either take on the value one, or it can take on the value of -1
It's one when qubit is heads and minus one when qubit is tails
And there is no more content in it - other than heads and tails
But it allow us start being able to write equations for something
You can also describe it some other way by a picture
I'm gonna describe sigma as one by an arrow pointing up
Sigma equals minus one by and arrow pointing down
No implication here, not anything geometric here, just notation
Notations, three different notations, heads and tails,
sigma equals one or sigma equals minus one
And arrow pointing up and arrow pointing down
Okay let's imagine an experiment, an experiment involve more than one system
It involve a second system, the second system is call the apparatus
In classical mechanics we never bother thinking too much about details
Unless we happen to be experimental physicists
and really going to the laboratories and doing experiments
We sort of don't worry very much about, at least in a deep sense
We think the system can be describe completely without worrying
how you detect it how you measure it or anything else
But in quantum mechanics,
one can not get away ignoring the concept of a apparatus
So let's introduce an apparatus, and I've tell you what an apparatus
We are going to make a mathematically abstract apparatus
I'm not gonna tell you how it works, black box
It's a black box I'm gonna call it A, A for apparatus
It's a box that has a little window, there is the window
It also, it really is a box, it's like a carten(),
a carten getting mail which says this side up, this side up
You want to stand up right?
Here is a little window, by window I mean screen
And numbers appears on that screen
And it has some sort of detector on the end of a wire
that senses the qubit
It senses the qubit is plus one or minus one
So you start with your qubit and you don't know what state it's in
The experiment is to determine what state it's in
So the qubit begins with an unknown state, unknown
We don't know it's plus one or minus one
We are gonna do an experiment , the experiment
As I said, I'm not gonna tell you how the detector work
It's not important for us, it's only important the detector do exists
We are gonna, we will talk later about the process of detection, but not for now
Let us central over here, central over the qubit
What does it do?
A number lights up in here, if it's plus one
Oh, first of all, before we do the detection, the apparatus is in the neutral state
The blank state, no number there at all
So let's just call that a blank configuration of the apparatus
We take the apparatus over, close enough to the qubit to react with it
And it's a good faithful apparatus it will register a number here
And the number would either be plus one or minus one
Plus one or minus one, depending on which way, whether it's heads or tails
That's the act of the measurement
Now you may or may not be there to look at the apparatus this is a secondary
The apparatus has detected and recorded what is going on over here
So that's something that, in classical mechanics of course we do the same thing
There is nothing in particular quantum mechanical about this
But we tend never to think about it,
then formulate the basic principle of quantum mechanics, oh, classic mechanics
Okay so that's the experiment that measures the state of
Or it measure whether sigma is plus one or minus one
But we can also think of it as another way
We can think of it not so much as a measurement but as a preparation
The preparation of the system
Here's the idea, supposing we in fact do measured sigma to be plus one
Supposing that is the outcome of the experiment
That we can erase the one that it wasn't, and start over
And then say let's back off
We set the apparatus, we set it means start it over in the blank state
And then we do the experiment again
Let's say we do it fast enough so that
there wasn't many times for anything to happen
What happens? What happen is that the detector records again
And if it's a good detector, and the system hasn't had time to change very much
It will simply record the same number again
It will confirm the previous experiment
This is important, the experiment can be confirmed, again
No difference between classical and quantum mechanics in this respect
We just emphasize it in quantum mechanics
Experiment can be confirmed
We can do it again and again, and again, and again
And we will continue to get the same answer that we got in the first place
So we can think a little bit more differently the first experiment
Instead of saying that it determines whether it is heads or tails
We can say it prepare it with a state which was in this case heads
After the first detection now known to be heads
it's been prepared in states heads
We can do the experiments over and over and over again
And always get the same answer
So the devices that measures
is also device that prepares the system in a given state
Of course the same thing would be true
had the device determines in the first round the signal was minus one
Then it would continue to detcet the same thing
Of course there can be bad detectors, not all detectors are well made
Not all detectors work the way you want them to be work
In which case it's just wasn't a good detector
It didn't do what you wanted it to do
>> would this heads and tails have to do with this point
>> what's the purpose of having a heads and tails
It's just two possibilities
You wanna know what actually has to do with a heads and a tails?
I just used that for familiarity
The marines() do heads and tails
Okay now we are gonna do something new
We are gonna do a new experiment
First we are gonna start with a preparation
The preparation determines the spin was, what was a spin, I call it a spin
I'm giving away, it is a spin
The qubit is in the state plus one alright?
So the qubit in the other notation is an arrow pointing up
We've prepared, we now know, we can do a few times to check
But once we check it we now know that this qubit is up
And if we continue to do it, we will continue to get the same answer
Now we are gonna do something funny
After we've determine or prepared the qubit
We are now gonna take the detector and turn it over
A... I don't know, this side up?
We turn the detector over and now we are going to probe the qubit again
And what have we learn in this case?
We discover, we discover that instead of getting plus one we get minus one
By turning the detector over we get the opposite answer
What is this telling us?
What is this telling us about the nature of this system?
What is it telling us? Of course then if we take our upside-down detector
and continue to do the experiment over and over
We will continue to get minus one
Of course what happen let say if we do it thirty five times
We turn the detector back up right?
Then we get plus one
What we were learning is whatever this system is
This particular qubit has a sense of directionality to it
Then when I drew it as up versus down
There really was a sense in which the orientation is being distinguished
By turning the detector upside down we interchange up and down
Well that's what I normally mean by up and down
Turn it over, we got it upside down
And it changes the sign of the qubit
That's the indication the qubit has some directionality in space
Spatial direction associate with it
And not every qubit has spatial directionality with it
But by doing this experiment we discover that whatever this qubit is
It really does have a sense of orientation
An upness and downness in space
So that's a piece of interesting information
We might begin to suspect that it's a vector
We might begin to suspect since it has a directionality in space
It's a vector, the one that is pointing up
is different to the one that is pointing down
We can make... well yes alright...
so that's the basic idea of a qubit which also have a sense of directionality
Like this pen then our detector when we measure it up then we measure it down
But now we are gonna do something else
Oh we might, here is what we might believe, here is what we might believe
Given that the detector has an orientation to it
and it does have an orientation to it
There is right side up and wrong side up
In fact in the detector we might even think
that something which itself is an orientation
Something built into the detector which has an orientation in it
And you know what we might think, we might think that
this detector is detecting the value of a component of a vector
along the direction of the detector itself
So when the detector is right side up
And it's detecting the things here
it's detecting the component of some vector in the plus direction
When you turn the detector over,
it's measuring the component of the same object
except with respect to an axis which has been flipped
So you might start to think this thing might be a vector, this qubit
So now we do something, let's say alright, do something else now
Let's turn the detector on it's side, let's turn the detector on it's side
We have initially determine that the qubit was up
We definitely make sure it's up, we've done it a thousand time
with the right side up detector and know for sure it's up
It's not down
And now we detect, take the side way detector
A this side up over right here
With a internal arrow pointing in this direction over here
And what should we expect ordinariliy
Ordinarily we say, well if this thing is going to measure now
not the vertical component of some vector
but the horizontal component of some vector
we know that the vector was pointing upward by the initial preparation
which you do get here, well what's the component along horizontal axis?
Zero, so the answer is we should get zero
If this were classical physics and this were classical little vector
That's exactly what we will get
So we are going to be experiment, probe it, and we get not zero
But either one or minus one again
Which one do we get? One or minus one? One or minus one?
So it seem to be symmetrically located relative to the axis of the detector
So we say oh I got one, let's do this experiment a whole bunch of time
Let's go back, get us some new qubits
Throw this qubit away, we've finished with it
Get us a new qubit, make sure it's pointing up
And do the same experiment again
Well, we might get plus one again, but again we might get minus one
We do it many many times,
exactly the same experiment with a qubit known to be pointing up
And we measure what you would've like to think
with the horizontal component of an object
And we always get plus one or minus one, randomly
Randomly but in such a way that if you do it a great many times
Then the average value is zero
There is many z... as many plus one as minus ones
If you do it a great many times
And you will find every single one of them is either plus one or minus one
But on the average it add up to zero
>> you said you threw the qubit away ()
well if you reoriented it, if you reoriented it and make sure it's up again
then it would not matter if it's a new qubit or not
>> if you look at the same qubit at the same place
Okay good question, alright good, good, good
So let's go back ,good question
We start with the qubit known to be up
We made a detection and we got plus one
The implication of that is the qubit is lying in the horizontal direction
Somehow, somehow we've detected a plus one
but a plus one relative to a new axis
Not the original axis but a new axis
Supposing we now take that same qubit don't modify it
But do the same experiment over and over and over again
We will always get the same plus one
Once that qubit has registered plus one and we don't disturb it
Do the experiment again and again we will continue to get plus one
Another words we will confirm we will confirm the experiment
>>difference between two actions you projected from
>>going from top side to the bottom side,
>>that's a hundred and eighty degrees
>>whereas the other is only ninety degree
When I turn the detector for ninety degrees
it no longer have the definiteness about the answer
The answer is random but only the first time
Once I do it, once I do it
and I determine whether the horizontal component is plus one or minus one
Then it's determined,
and if I do the same horizontal experiment over and over again
I will continue to get the same answer
Well, then I could come back and say okay,
now having done that and pretty sure
the horizontal components of it is in the plus direction
I can come back and turn the detector again
Guess what will happen?
I will find the random result after time plus after time minus
But again, once it's determined and I do it over and over and over again
It stays the same, ya?
>> this is probably not important but on your side way detector,
>>your arrows are tickle in the wrong way
How so?
>> the point from A
Oh oh oh, maybe there was an A here
This side up I think, okay yes you are right
It's interesting okay, so therefore,
having done this experiment and found out that I get a plus one
I do it over and over and over a few times
I get a plus one each time
Let's say I take the detector and turn it around 180 degrees
What do I get?
Minus one, or what happen if I turn it 90 degrees?
Random, random means a particular kind of randomness
equal probability for up and down
equal probability for plus one and minus one
And that means if I would do the same experiment,
the whole thing over and over
Perhaps with a whole bunch of different qubits
I have whole() lots of qubits over here, a lots of them
I don't even know what their directions are
They are in, whatever they are doing
And I take them one at a time
I subject them to the first experiment
If I get up I keep them
If I get down I throw them in the trash
At the end of the day, what I would have gotten myself
with a whole bunch of qubit known to be pointing up
Now I take one of them , and subject it to the side way experiments
I may get one, or I may get minus ones
I record what I got for all the way
Go to the next one do the same experiment
and make it plus one and minus one record what I get
Take this whole collection, large collection of them
And do the side way experiment for all of them
What would be the average result?
Zero, zero, I will have as many plus ones as minus ones
And so the average would be zero
Let's try that in this case here
The same that the average value, we need a symbol for the average value
But after the experiment here we will discover the average value of the x
Or the horizontal component of the qubit here is zero
Classically if we would have created a little vector in the up direction
And we measure the horizontal component we simply get zero
In the real world with quantum mechanics we always get plus or minus one
But in such a way that the average is zero
>> Is that true (even if that you don't throw away the qubit)
>> which measured plus one or minus one?
Yeah, actually it's still true, that is correct, the answer is yes
>> In your description either the detector () seems to have some type of memory
Some type of, yeah ,we were assuming that the law of the motion of the qubit
is that nothing happens to it so we remember when you detect it
And then you detect it again instantly after , and it hasn't changed
Right that's correct
Now later on, we are gonna consider possibilities
where during the intervening time between the measurement
some interesting things might happen
For the moment we supposing nothing interesting happen in between
It's analog of the classical coin
with law of physics there's just nothing happens
>> we don't talk about the collapsing of a wave function
that's of course up till now but
No, let's not talk about it, let's talk about the operational things that
we might do to discover in the clause of quantum mechanics
Then we will puts some words on them such as collapsible wave package
Okay, so things are funny in some average sense
The horizontal component of something zero within each individual instance
You only get plus one or minus one
Now let's go a little further
Let's, or instantly the same thing would be true
if instead of turning the detector this way we turn it this way
so the internal vector was pointing outward
It's to be true, same thing
Okay now let's do a little different experiment
Same set up to begin with
But instead of rotating the detector by 90 degrees
Let's rotate it by 45 degrees, in fact any angle, let's not do 45 degrees
Let's rotate it by an arbitrary angle so that the internal detector ()
is now characterize by an angle theta relative to the vertical
It's been rotated by an angle theta and do the same experiment now
We take the first qubit
subject it now to the detector oriented to the angle theta
What do we get , plus one or minus one?
do it again what do we get , plus one or minus one?
What do we get do it again , plus one or minus one?
Never do anything in between,
but in this case the average value of the experimental value,
or what comes out here is not equal to zero
It's equal to, what do you expect it to equal to?
Cosine of theta, cosine of the angle
Exactly like the x component of a vector would be
Or exactly like yes, exactly like the components of these vectors
along the detector axis
The component of these vector along the detector axis()
would be smaller by an amount cosine theta, classically,
quantum mechanically, we simply get plus one minus one
Plus one plus one minus one plus plus plus whatever
In such a way as to averages to the cosine of the angle
As the detector gets more and more up right
Cosine theta gets closer and closer to one
And that just mean it gets closer and closer to the value to ()
the answer if the detector is perfectly up right
Now and then you might get a minus sign, but mostly plus sign
And as soon as the detector get perfectly right side up
All plus ones
What about the detector is almost upside down?
Well then you get mostly minus one, a few in there are plus ones
And so it seems that the average values of sigma
are behaving as if sigma was a component of a vector
this is something you know, really different
>>() if you have prepared these as up, if you just took more qubits with there
if you what?
>> it stay up because you started with up
yes, yes
>> why do we need a collection of qubits?
Why do we need what?
>> a collection of qubits? Since nothing happening to the qubit right?()
If you take the same one and do it over and over and over again
with the same detector, you will just get the same answer over and over
You just confirm the previous measurement
So we take one qubit known to be up because you made it you know that it's up
And you subject it to the angularly ()rotated experiment
You either get plus one or minus one but if you do it a second time
You will just get the same answer you got the first time
You won't learn anything new
Incidentally if that weren't the case, there will be no way to confirm
That the answer you got the first time was in any sense the right answer
The only way you confirm an answer is right is by checking it
And one way to check it it's just
If I close my eyes and look at you see you up right
And then I close my eyes again and look at you again
I've confirm the first time you are up right
>> but it also gonna be the same stick?
This one here? Second one?
Ya , I'm saying if you only have one of them
Then you do the experiment you will either get plus one or minus one
And then if you do the same experiment again on the same one over and over
You just get plus one
But if you have a sequence of them
and you do the experiment with a sequence of them
All having them prepared in the same way
Then you will get a statistical distribution
>>So if you turn off the detector and turn it on again
>> will you still have the memory of the same
That's what I mean by switch it off again
Switch the detector off and turn if back on
>>So does the detector seem to store memory or
the detector has an orientation to it, and when I say you turn
>> and what you say you change or did not change
change the qubit? Say it again?
>> how does you know that you changed or did not change the qubit
No, they didn't change the detector
>> But when you switch the qubit and now it's reset
>> but if you ()qubit and it gives you the same reading?
There was only one qubit you did the same
>> isn't that the detector is not remembering things but the qubit has changed?
I would like to say the students and audience
Some of them are sitting upside-down and
some of them are sitting rightside-up
If I randomly open my eyes to the students
50% are standing rightside-up or not
I close my eyes and look at another student, 50% I don't know
But I if I open my eyes, and then close them, open them, close them
And look at the same student it's always the same way
How do my eyes know the student was gonna that
I wasn't looking at the different student?
Answer is just look at the same student okay?
So the whole thing is not that weird that
we can't keep track and remember which of these things we were looking at
>> so basically we can think of it as the act of observing
>> ()prepare that particular qubit
>> to let you observe that one you prepare it
>> so now you always get that answer
until you intervened by something else
>> if you change the qubit but let the measuring apparatus
>> in the same position, you still get plus ones?
>> you are not gonna change the orientation of the measurement device?
>> but you just measure a sequence of different qubits?
>> are they really gonna be plus ones or minus ones?
It depends, it depends on how they were prepared
Somebody might have given you a sequence of qubit
which happens to be up down up down up down up down
You might have gotten them from some place
You got them from a , you know , qubit store
If they didn't have a very good quality control
But if all of these qubits are prepared in the same way and identical way
And then you send them to here they will continue to be identical
Okay, what this is telling us,
is there something funny about the notion of the status of a system
is not as clear cut in another symbol as
a state of either a coin which is either heads or tails
Or a little vector which has components in different directions
But for example when you measure a component along the axis
perpendicular to the known direction of the vector, you get zero
Not so, so there is something intrinsically different
And the difference does trace to the big difference between the notion
of a state in quantum mechanics and the state of classical mechanics
>> but you have everything there up plus one?
>> and one by one you put it plus one or minus one?
>> and each one you bring up that was just minus one
>> then becomes the minus one of the original
if you do the experiment
>> If you bring one down, let's say it's minus one down here
>> then you turn the apparatus up again
>> and now you say it will be minus one from now on
No no, none of you turn the apparatus
>> I thought you said if you turn the apparatus up if it measure minus()
>> it would stay minus if you turn the apparatus ()
If you turn the apparatus, then you get a statistical distribution
Okay when you turn an apparatus
Once you have the qubits that comes out of this apparatus
Let's say it was plus one, let's say it comes out plus one
And now you take that qubit over here
Then you turn the apparatus back up again
Then you get a random plus or minus
>> then if will be random if you turn back up
>> so in that way then
every time you turn it, it will be random
you will end up in a random bunch of qubits
now it depends on the angle, if the angle is not too large, if the angle is small
then mostly you will get pluses
Right, mostly you will get pluses
>> two state system and that with a detector,
>> what would be the difference in large, when the signal can be variable
>> and the detector and two state system, see if I could get the same out
Say it again, say it again
>> you postulated two state system plus and minus one
>> but then you have a detector that always produces plus and minus one
>> if you postulated with variable to start with the detector
>> will still like to be what you
The detector will still be what?
>> It seems like you are really saying the detector is ()
>> and it doesn't seem to imply that
You are absolutely right that at some point we will come back to this
And say the detector is a system and it had states
And understand the combine system as
a quantum system composed of two quantum systems
But let's not do that yet, let's divide the worlds into detectors and systems
And then come back later and then say, look
A detector really is a system and we have to describe it quantum mechanically
Also as a system and to understand the entire thing as
the interplay between the two quantum systems,
but that would take a, that would take some steps before we get there
>> the axes of rotation doesn't matter?
You mean if we rotate this way or, right it doesn't matter
>> I mean if we do rotation on one axis and then on a different axis
Right, you are right and guessing the whole story is much more complex
But still, the story is more complex but not inconsistent with what I said
So don't try to guess too far ahead, don't try to guess to far ahead
Let's try the simple version of the first
And then we will eventually come to a much more rich understanding of it
>> so if it is correct to think the detector is something
>> could repetitiously continue value of plus one or minus ones
>> the system would only be, the key would only be
For now, yes, if you like, you could think of,
For now you can think of the detector as the thing
which can be oriented in many direction
And when we measure it, it behaves like a classic system
Eventually we will have to reconcile that
with idea of the detector themselves are quantum systems
And have to respect the same law as the system itself
Okay, now let's, I leave you to ponder now
And we are going to separate from this for a while and discuss mathematics
We are gonna describe the mathematics of a state space
Or the space of state of a quantum system
And as I said , it's not a set,
not a set in the same sense of set of configuration of a die
It's not a set of six configurations
It's more complicated
#Alright but we need some mathematics
We need some mathematics, we need some mathematics abstract mathematics
And the mathematics as I said it's not the mathematics of set theory
The mathematics of vector spaces
Now let's just discuss the word vector for a moment
You are familiar of course with the idea of a vector
A vector is an arrow pointing to certain direction in ordinary space
And it's one concept of a vector but
there is more abstract notion of a mathematical vector space
A mathematical vector space can accomplice
many many kinds of mathematical objects
Which are not necessarily pointers along an axis in space
I generally, only I get to this point I generally make a new name
An un(non?)conventional new name nobody else I known of users
For the notion of an ordinary vector in an ordinary space
Another words a thing pointing at ordinary space
I call it a pointer that distinguish it from
the abstract mathematical concept of a vector
We are gonna talk about the abstract mathematical concept of a vector
Don't think of it as pointing in three dimensional space
Ordinary three dimensional space
We will discuss what space it points
Alright so let's talk about vector spaces
A vector space is a collection of mathematical objects
Like numbers is a collection of mathematical objects
And numbers, just the real number axis for example, is vector space
A special case of a vector space
It's a one dimensional vector space
Complex numbers are two dimensional vector space
We are going to be talking about vector spaces
For the moment I'm ()looking on dimensionality
I'm just gonna write down the mathematical notation
for an object in the vector space, and as I said, vectors space is just a name,
for a collection of mathematical objects
Completely abstract, a is a vector
And that's a notation for an abstract vector
It's Dirac notation, it consists of a vertical line a cricket line
and a letter in between, and that stands for the vector a
Whatever the vector a is
What can you do with vectors?
Well you can add them
()I'm not gonna tell you how to add them, I just tell you
given any two vectors a and b you can form this sum
And the sum is another vector
Let's call that the vector c
So a vector space consists of a collection of objects
which can be added
>> I'm sorry, vector versus vector space?
Vector space is a collection of vectors
The same distinction between number and numbers
Numbers are all the numbers, number is a specific number
So as I said, numbers is a special case for this you can add them
You could do something else with numbers
You can multiply them by another numbers
Well, eventually we will be talking about multiplying vectors , but not yet
What we can do is multiply vectors by numbers
Ordinary numbers or complex numbers
And we are going to talk about complex numbers
I hoped everybody is comfortable with complex numbers
If not, you got to quickly get to speed on complex numbers
But we do not, we don't need to know too much
You need to know that a complex number
is a combination of real number and imaginary number
And how to multiply, add complex numbers
And you need the notion of complex conjugate
How many people here are familiar with complex conjugate?
Most people, almost everybody, so I'm not going to go into it now
But basically for every complex number
There is another complex number for it's complex conjugate
It's a mapping between numbers and their complex conjugate
So it's an important notion, keep that in mind
We are just gonna come back
But for the moment, ordinary vectors let's call it, pointers
Pointers in space, ordinary pointers you can multiply by ordinary numbers
Positive or negative, a pointer with a certain length on that direction
If you multiply it by two, it's just twice as long in the same direction
Multiply it by minus one, it just became the same direction (length)
except on the opposite direction
Alright so yes you can multiply vectors by numbers
And in a complex vector space,
we are now gonna talk about complex vector space
you can multiply vectors by complex number
Now do not try to picture this in your head
as any kind of pointers in some direction
Just accept we are talking about a mathematical abstraction
Where a vector, any given vector can be multiply by any complex numbers
I'm gonna use, let's see what shall I use for complex number?
In my notes I use c, but I don't wanna use c
z, you know z is the standard notation, you know x + yi is equal to z
so you can take any complex number, sorry, any vector
multiply it by any complex number
And it's still some, I'm not trying to draw it for you
Stop trying to think about drawing
Vectors if there was a vector there was a complex number you multiply them
and it gives you some new vector, let's call it, let's call it 'a prime'
So you can multiply vectors by numbers, complex numbers
And that's about it, that's all there is to a vector space
Any set of an object for which you can do this is a vector space
Give you some examples of vector spaces, if a-s and b-s
If a-s and b-s are just real numbers
Then you can add them to make real numbers
But you cannot multiply them by complex numbers
and still expect to get real numbers
You can multiply them by real numbers
And get all the real numbers
So the real numbers are real vector space
How about the complex numbers?
A complex number a complex vector space ?
Yes , you can add them and get other complex numbers
Any two complex number you can add
And any complex number you can multiply by another complex number
And back to complex number
So the complex numbers are the simplest example of a complex vector space
Let me give you another example of complex vector space
This is incredibly complicated but still, pretty easy to write down
Take any function of a variable, let's call it phi of x
Now x maybe an ordinary variable, a function on a line
A function on a line, but it's a complex function on a line
It has a real and imaginary part, complex function on a line
Can you add two functions and get another function? Certainly
So functions, just functions are things you can add to get other functions
Can you multiply a complex function
by a complex number to get a complex function?
Yes, take any complex function multiply it by a complex number
You get another complex function
So functions form a vector space
Now that's a complicated idea, I don't wanna that complicated yet
So let's erase that from the blackboard
I will give you another vector space
Another complex vector space
Let's just make some symbols, a bracket
And put in entries, two entries into the bracket
And the two entries are themselves complex numbers
Alpha one and alpha two
Alpha equals a complex number
And alpha one and alpha two can be anything
The collection of such symbols is also a complex vector space
Here's the rule
Supposing you have two of them
Here's one and here's another one, beta one beta two
And you add them, what does that mean? Definition
With definition of the sum of two is called column
The sum of two columns like that is just to add the entries
Alpha one plus beta one, alpha two plus beta two
So given any two abstract symbols
in which the entries are filled in with complex numbers
Any two of them alpha and beta
We can add them and get a third one
So column vectors like this, column of two entries like this
satisfied the first rule, and the second rule is that
if you want to take a column and multiply it by a complex number
All you do is multiply each entry by the complex number
Multiply each entry separately and then you construct something
which is just z
So just pairs of complex number like this form a vector space
So very abstract concept but not very hard
How about triples of them?
Sure, from any columns like that
Now what you don't wanna do is add a column of two
to a column of three, there's no kind of rule for that
So column of different lengths form different vector spaces
Completely different abstract vector spaces
Any questions about the meaning, this is not hard, but it is abstract
>> are there an () part of a vector space?
Yeah I think it's also important to have a zero vector
The zero vector is THE unique vector
which you add to any other vector you get the same
the same vector
Right, I didn't feel like writing it down but they
>> the general closure requirement that they are all close
>> in a particular space?
Close under addition?
>> I think, right
And close up at the multiplication
>> I think you have illustrated
That's right
>> is this same as the matrices ?
Matrices, ya, this is a, usually the term matrices in this class in any case
Will be reserved for square matrices
Square matrices are collection of numbers which form square ways
Many rows and columns, but the general notion of a matrix can have
different numbers of rows and columns
And the vector would be a matrix with only one column
in this case two rows
So yes this will be a special case of a matrix
But you know in many context one reserve the term matrix for a square matrix
And I will use it that way, I will use the term matrix to mean a square matrix
So I didn't want to use that terminology
Okay are you thoroughly saturated with abstract mathematics?
This should be straightforward for you
#okay now we introduce another abstraction
Another abstraction,
basically it's the abstraction of given a complex vector space
The complex conjugate of a vector space
is sort of the space of complex conjugate vectors
just like you can have any number a complex conjugate any complex number
There is a complex conjugate to go with it
So in that sense the complex number system
has a dual version which is the complex conjugate of the original numbers
So do the complex conjugate vector spaces
and roughly speaking, the complex conjugate vector spaces
The dual vector space, usually call the dual
Is roughly speaking the complex conjugate of the original vectors
We will make it more precise as it goes along
But what it is is a separate space
whose elements are in one to one correspondent
to the element of the origin vector space
So if there is an vector a in the original space
Let's write it this way
then there is a vector in a dual way
Called the dual vector space
But as I said it's more or less complex conjugate
And it's written this way
It's just written as a backward Dirac symbol
We will learn this things as bra vectors and ket vectors
No this is the bra vectors this is the ket vectors
For the moment they are just symbols
An example, if the vector space is just the space of complex numbers
Then the dual vector space is just
the space of complex conjugate of the numbers
And so there is one to one correspondent
between vectors and their complex conjugates
Let's write down first some postulate about the complex conjugate vector space
And test it out by saying
if we can find a concrete representation of the notion
Write down some abstract postulate and check
Just what we did here
We said here's a concrete representation
of the notion that we wrote down over here
Let's write down the abstract postulate about the dual vector space
So first of all, for any vector there is a dual vector
They are in one to one correspondent
Next , if you take two vectors, and you add them together
Then the dual of the sum is just the sum of the dual
So if you take a vector which is
made up out of the sum of two other vectors
Then it's reflection in the dual space
is just the sum of the individual dual vectors
These are postulates, these are postulates if you like
But they are not so obscure
The third assumption is that if you take any vector
And multiply it by a complex conjugate, ah sorry, by a complex number
Then it's reflection in the dual space now anybody wanna guess?
Of course it involve the dual vector a, but not multiplication by z
Or multiplication by complex conjugate of z, z star
z star is the complex conjugate of the z
This would be true for complex number if you take a complex number
and multiply it by another complex number
Then the complex conjugate of the whole thing
is the product of complex conjugate, that's all it is saying
So we think of the dual vector space
as basically just the complex conjugate vector space in some sense
Okay let's see if we can make any sense out of this
In terms of this columns vectors here
>> Is a plus b the same as b plus a?
Yes, a plus b is the same as b plus a, good question
When you add vectors and you can see that from here
Alright should have, sorry, somebody else asked me
if there is any other rules on the definition of the vector space
Indeed there are, among other ones
That maybe order-ness it doesn't matter which order you add
But you can see that here the sum of two vectors
is just given by numerical adding the complex numbers here
And of course numerical addition of complex number
it doesn't mean out of which way you order them
So that's a good point
Okay so let's come back now to, let's put this up on top
And come back to this concrete non abstract representation
of the complex of vector space
Here we have a vector
This object is representing the vector a
The one that I erased with beta, that's representing vector b
But right now I don't need the vector b
What about the object if this object represents a
Then what is the object which represents the dual vector
The dual vector the corresponding dual vector
And the answer is, it's the same pair of number except their complex conjugate
The same pair of numbers, not quite
Their complex conjugates, alpha one star, and alpha two star
But just to keep track, they were talking of a different vector space
We write it in row form, not as a column, as a row
This is just a trick to remember
that this object belongs to the dual vector space
That this object belongs to the original vector space
A bit different
Alright, so the dual vector space image of alpha one and alpha two
is alpha one star, alpha two star
That's the dual vector, I know you can check, you can check
With this definition, are the postulates namely if you add the two vectors
and then take the dual, that whether or not you get the sum of duals
Then you can check whether you multiply this by a complex number
And then mul- , and then take it to, or just multiply by it's complex conjugate
The answer is yes
So just laying out a pair of complex numbers like this
makes a vector space, and the dual vector space
The same pair of numbers except complex conjugated
and lay out in a row, lay out in a row
just to remember that it's not the same creature,
doesn't live in the same space
And that's the idea of a complex vector space
As I said again, very abstract but very easy
#final concept
Alright it's not the final concept but a (final concept)
The n plus frist concept, I'm not sure what n is
How many people find this hard?
It's not very hard, how many people find it familiar?
Quiet a lot of people find it familiar
Let's, those don't find it familiar apparently didn't find it hard
That's also good
The product of the two vectors
The inner product of the two vectors
The inner product of the two vectors is
the analog of the dot product for pointers
The analog of dot product for pointers
The inner product between two vectors is quickly speaking
The inner product between a vector and a vector and the dual of the vector
Given two vectors let's call them a and b
One does not form the product with a or b
The inner product, instead, one takes b and
construct it's image in the dual vector space
And then takes the product of vector a to the dual vector b
In Dirac's language, you take a ket vector and you multiply if by a bar vector
And when you do so, you make a bra-ket, bracket
A bracket of course is this thing over here, and the two together
I think this one is call the ket, this one is called the bra
Bra, ket
So the inner product of the two vectors is really a product of two vectors
And the dual of the vector
Now is this the same as multiplying the bra vector a with the ket vector b
Question, is it the same to multiply the bra b to the ket a
or a bra a to a ket b?
The answer is no.
It is not the same operation, but in fact they are closely related
The axiom, we are still talking about the axiom
The axiom is that these two are related by complex conjugation
A complex conjugation a to go from the ket vector to the bra vector
A complex conjugated b to go from bra vector to the ket vector
So this is product of a, roughly speaking, times b star
This is the product of b star times a
This is the complex conjugate of this
So another postulate of an axiom of a complex vector space
is that the inner product of a with b
is the complex conjugate of the inner product of b with a star
>> what do you mean in normal vector space
>> ... quantum mechanics... for sake, I means
>> there will be inner product just all the same vector space
In ordinary vector space?
>> this is still called the inner product even though it's
>> one of the special thing with complex conjugate?
The usual vector spaces that you think about are real vector spaces
And for real vector space, for real numbers
there is no difference between numbers and it's complex conjugate
So the real vector space satisfied the same postulate
Except that the complex conjugation is completely attribute operation
>> but in the other vector space if you take the two product
>> of two complex vector and it doesn't involve any conjugation
>> you just multiply the components up
Yes you could, you could invent such a thing
Then of course the inner product of a vector with itself would not be real
That's okay, who cares?
So you can invent such things
turns out not to be terribly useful in quantum mechanics context
So ,you know, it's largely a question of what's useful
And what's useful wines up being this concept
Alright, I guess you could, you could certainly define such a thing
It's not a commonly define thing
Doesn't seem to have a lot of use
This structure occurs in all kinds of places, not only in quantum mechanics
So this complex vector spaces are very very common things in mathematics
And okay, let's check now, and see if we can postulate a construction
for the inner product of the dual vector beta
Remember when you complex conjugate,
when you take times the original vector alpha
This is supposed to be now
I guess I call it b a
And I haven't written down the notation for b
And the notation for a
Column vector for a, row vector for b, complex conjugated
I will tell you now what the rule is
Again we are making up rules which will satisfy postulates up there
And it's very simple construction, it's just beta one star times alpha one
plus beta two star times alpha two
Another word you take the first entry of the dual vector
Times the first entry of the vector with alpha
Add it to the first entry and second entry times a second entry
So it's just the generalization of multiplying beta times alpha
But it's also a generalization of dot product
If you remember the dot product of ordinary vectors
You simply take up the sums of the product of the components
If you have two pointers, they are labeled by components
Both of them, then the dot product
is just sums of the products of the components
Does that satisfy the rules up here?
Where did I write the rules
I think I have erased the rules
The rule was
>> It's up there, the last one
ah I've lost it, okay
What happen if you interchange alpha and beta or a and b?
And this becomes alpha one star, alpha two star
Times beta one beta two
If I interchange them, and that's equal to
alpha one star beta one plus alpha two star beta two
And that's just the complex conjugate of it
That really is the complex conjugate
So interchanging alpha and beta or a and b
Really does interchange, not the value of the product
But it's complex conjugate
That's the notion of a complex vector spaces
And an inner product on a complex vector space
Now let's just take a couple of special cases of inner products
What about the inner product with the vector itself?
Or the vector with it's image in the dual space?
Let's take the product of a with a
What do we know about that?
Well first of all let's, I'm setting b equals to a
That tells me the inner product of a vector to itself
is equal to it's own complex conjugate
I just substitute it for b a
The inner product of vector with itself
was equal to it's own complex conjugate
What kind of number is equal to it's own complex conjugate?
A real number, so the inner product of a vector with itself
is always real, it's pretty obvious just from here
If we take alpha and multiply it by it's image
I get alpha star alpha, plus alpha two star alpha two
Each one of these is real
Not only is it real, it's also something else, positive
Alpha star alpha , a number times it's own complex conjugate is always positive
So it's real and positive
The inner product of a vector with itself is real and positive
And it's consider to be the square of the length of the vector
The square root of the inner product of a vector with itself
defines the length of the vector
So complex vectors have real lengths
Real and positive lengths, also the square of
both the square and the length itself are defined to be positive
So that's not too obscure, every complex vector has a length
Which is the square root or the sum of the square of it's components
Square know mean multiply by complex conjugate
#next notion, important notion
The notion of orthogonality of vectors
The notion of orthogonality of vectors is a very important one
Now I give some examples in a few minutes
The notion of orthogonality between two vectors
Is exactly the same as it is for ordinary vectors
The inner product the rear-dot product if you like
The inner product is zero
If the inner product of two vectors are zero
It is set to be orthogonal
That defines, or perpendicular
Okay so two vectors are orthogonal
if the inner product between them is zero
Let's see if we can make up some orthogonal vectors
It's easy
Oh, oh oh, what about reading,
what about take the inner product the opposite order
It's just a complex conjugate of a zero
The complex conjugate of a zero
As zero is zero, so saying that the two vectors are orthogonal
it doesn't matter which order you put them in
The notion of orthogonality doesn't depend on order
Although the general idea of inner product does
So we now have a notion of orthogonal vectors
In a real vectors space,
how can you define the dimensionality of real vector space?
Well give me a definition of dimensionality
There are many definitions of course
Anybody have one?
>> the () matrix of a vector
Yeah, but let's work it in a more abstract way without the
Yes, of course that's correct
The maximum numbers of orthogonal vectors if you can find in the space
So if a vector space is two dimensional
Ordinary two dimensional vector space
There are two mutually orthogonal vectors
You can not find a third vector which is orthogonal to both of them
So the maximum number of mutually orthogonal vectors
In three dimensions, I've got three mutually orthogonal vectors
Of course there are many sets of mutually orthogonal vectors
But given three I can not find the fourth one
So three dimensional vector space
has a maximum number of three mutually orthogonal vectors
and the same is true, or the same definition
it's definition is true for complex vector space
The maximum number of orthogonal vectors that you can find
is equal to the dimensionality of the space
It does correspond to the number of entries here
The number of components , if it's the same you could prove that
As exercise, prove that the number of components of vectors
is the same as the number mutually orthogonal vectors
But let's just talk,
Are there any mutually orthogonal vectors I can write down?
Sure, loads and loads of them
But the very simple case would be one zero
Now one and zero, are one and zero complex numbers?
Well real number are special cases of complex numbers
So real, complex number can be real
Here's one, and here's another one, zero one
This one has the one in the first place
This one has the zero in the first place, you get the idea
The inner product is zero times one plus one times zero
Okay, so the two vectors or
Let's just write it in terms of column vectors
one zero and zero one
One zero and zero one are orthogonal vectors
The inner product of this one with the dual of this one is zero
That's because one times zero plus zero times one
This is zero
So there is plenty of orthogonal vectors around
But in two dimensions this is two dimensions
Once you found two of them, you can not find the third
So as exercise, prove that there can be no vector
which are both orthogonal to this and orthogonal to that
That's not hard to do, very easy to do
Oh ,year, "zero zero" is always orthogonal to everything
So one should be careful and say the maximum number of non zero
Orthogonal, mutually orthogonal vectors, good point
Alright, that's a mathematical interlude for tonight
Complex vector spaces
And the next time we will discuss how this space of states or what it means
Is the space of states of a simple qubit
to be two dimensional vector spaces?
Very very different than saying they consist of a point and a set
The space of state is in fact a vector space
And try to make contact with the mathematics of vector spaces
And the strange things that are happening
or seem to be happening over here with these
These funny properties of measurements
That's where we want to go
Learn some physics, some experimental physics blackboard up there,
and we've done some abstract mathematics over here
And next time I want to connect them and show
what the abstract mathematics how we represent or
how it can be use to represent this unusual kind of logic of qubits
>> Is it restricted to a pattern,
>> Is it going to be meaningful to define the multiplication operation
>> created two by two (raches)?
>> It should be beta one alpha one
You are asking? Yes the answer is yes
Yes absolutely, we will construct inner products outer products
so all sort of products
Ya, ya that's right
The outer products of the two matrix or two vectors as the matrix ya
Of course how do you represent it or just, well
The outer product of two vectors represented in this way
It is a matrix but we will come to that
>> all the postulates applies to the vectors and functions?
>> it's less obvious than
A vector space of function can be thought of as column vectors
but the entries are continuous
So we have alpha, alpha is the function
And the alpha of the first entry and alpha of the second entry
Out of that we have a continuous family of alpha
Alpha evaluated upon x 1, alpha evaluated upon x 2
Alpha evaluated upon x 3
And of course we can't really write it literally as
a discreet collection like that
But if you like think of these alphas here, alpha one alpha two
Is just the function of the two variables
A function of an entry one and two
Instead of a function of an x,
is a function of variable which would be either one or two
So yes, complex function forms complex vector spaces
The inner product, we will discuss that
>> () oriented apparatus turn at the angle of theta
>> If you consider the sequence of inputs going to outputs
>> the portion of minus one to one is given by close I tell you that
>> Is there anything interesting about the distribution of minus one
What does it mean?
>> Well like high order statistics?
Oh oh oh, they are just completely random, completely random
These are completely random variables
You are talking about the relationship between different replications
And whole bunch of space you subject them all to the same, the question is
I think you are asking whether there are correlations between them
No, no, they are completely independent uncorrelated variables
>> So is it still the variable ()
>> Does it make sense to say that when you are measuring a qubit
>> you are affecting it, so you are actually preparing a new state
Yes yes yes, that's absolutely right
>> That's why first time you get something and the second time you just
>> keep to them
And there is a big difference
between classical mechanics and quantum mechanics
In classical mechanics you can measure something
sufficiently gently to not affect it, to not disturb it
In quantum mechanics whenever you measure something
you always disturb it
So this is an example of how measuring something disturb it
and turn into a new state
And let's say that is a good point, yes
Okay
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu