Stanford University
Going way beyond the course
The model we talk about is Hamiltonian for energy
Is just C time P
P could be positive or negative
The wave function for a given P is just e to the IPX
And is nothing better about e to the plus IPX
Or P being positive or negative they are both perfectly acceptable plain waves
But one of them has positive energy
And one of them has negative energy
Just reading off here
Now negative energy is not such a good thing in the real world
Negative energy is not such a good thing in the real world
because if there were particles of negative energy
The world will be unstable the vacuum would not be,
an empty space would not be the state of lowest energy
you could take empty space which we could say has zero energy
and just start putting in particles of negative energy
Particles of negative energy will lower the energy and
anything that lowers the energy tends to be favored
You can make lots and lots particles, more and more particles
more and more negative energy
you have to get some positive energy from someplace
You have to get some positive energy from someplace
But you could for example radiate photons
And at the same time produce more and more of these negative energy
Particles, if there were particles of negative energy
The empty space would just be unstable
Unstable with respect to creating more and more
positive and negative energy particles
You can, you have to conserve energy so you have to do both
If there is only positive energy particles by contrast
there is no way that energy conservation will allow you to make them
If they are the only positive energy particles in the vacuum has zero energy
it's the lowest energy state and nothing can happen to it to create particles
so good stable world requires all particles to have positive energy
relative to the vacuum, this is not a good stable world
okay so what you do about it?
Well it was Dirac who understood what to do about it
but only in the case of fermions, now what are the fermions?
Fermions are simply particles that cannot be in the same state
Two of them cannot be in the same state
That's a rule, where that rule came from?
It comes from relativistic quantum field theory
But it's the same as the Pauli exclusion principle
If you know a little bit about chemistry
you know that the two electrons in an atom can't be in the same state
and you have to fill the atoms with particles of different energies
Different states, and the same is generally true
Particles that participate in the Pauli exclusion principle
are called fermions
Why are they called fermions I don't know
They should be called Pauli-on such obviously should be called Pauli-ons
And particles which don't participate in a exclusion principle
are called bosons, but of course properly they should be called Einstein-ons
But it was Einstein for studying them
Nevermind, fermions and bosons, fermions can't be put in the same state
bosons can, so Dirac said, look I have a very simple solution to all of this
just imagine that the vacuum empty space
is really a state in which all the particles of negative energy
are present simultaneously filling up the vacuum
you simply can't put any more in because you are not allowed
to put particles in the same state
but everything else is empty
In fact if you were to say, think about that for moment
let's assume that the real vacuum is a state of absolute lowest energy
absolute lowest energy, now take absolute empty space
would you think of is ordinarily empty space?
Is that the state of lowest energy?
No, I can put one particle of negative energy in, lower the energy
So there are state of lower energy
Whatever state you say I will find another negative energy particles to put into it
and lower its energy,
the only way to have the state of absolute lowest energy
is to simply fill it, full, full of all the particles which have negative energy
another words all the particles with negative momentum
sounds crazy but it turned out to be right
but you can only do that with particles which have the property
that you can't put more than one of them into the same state
If you can put more than one into the same state it would be no inability
to keep dumping negative energy particles into the vacuum
so this is a reasonable theory, it's Dirac's
It's a very simple basic baby version of the Dirac equation of what it is
and it's okay theory for neutrinos
Or for one-dimensional neutrinos
It is not a good theory for photons
photons are bosons and you simply can't play the same game
if there were negative energy bosons
you could simply dump them into the same state
more and more and more of them, it would simply destabilize the world
So no this is not good theory of bosons
It's a good theory for fermions
but that's taking us way beyond this course, this course of material
We've covered in a sense, a lot about the foundations of quantum mechanics
and very simple quantum mechanical systems
We've covered almost nothing about
what we could call the applications of quantum mechanics
Not even the applications of quantum mechanics
but studying quantum mechanical systems
we didn't even get to the harmonic oscillator that's a disgrace
but when I finish with quantum mechanics
next quarter we are gonna to do relativity and field theory
but then we are going to have to come back to quantum mechanics
in order to study more about the basic structures
that appear in quantum mechanics
So it's sort of embarrassing to teach a whole course in quantum mechanics
and never get to the harmonic oscillator
but that's where we are
So you can ask your money back I don't know
On the other hand, it does seem people have a lot of fun with entanglement
I didn't expect such a, a response particularly to this
Some of them are extremely interesting and well done
Some of the chatter back and forth on the Internet
I actually did follow it and sometimes it was a generally good
and sometimes excellent
so I, got some some sense of satisfaction of teaching that
We will go on a little bit today about Schrodinger equation
not the general Schrodinger equation but special Schrodinger equation
That Schrodinger actually wrote down
The connection with the things we've learned up till now is the wave function
And the wave function is simply the amplitude that
the particle is located at a particular position
in other words it's the inner product of whatever state vector happens to be
with the state of definite position
We can also write a momentum space wave function
The momentum space wave function just the
projection of the same state whatever it happens to be
onto a momentum eigenstate, eigenvector
momentum eigen vectors and the position eigenvectors
Or rather the momentum wave function position wave function are related
and they are related by Fourier transform
That's the basic structure of position and momentum
If the particle has more than one direction to move in for example
let's suppose it can move in the x-y plane
then you characterize the position of a particle by two coordinates
The two coordinates communed
you can't measure both the X and Y position of a particle simultaneously
Now is that something that follows automatically from
what we set up till now?
No, not at all, it's really an empirical fact
It's an empirical fact that the structure of the quantum mechanics of particles
only conforms to, to experiment if we assume that
the different coordinates with different directions
the particle can move and commute
That means the wave function is not really a function not of a single variable
but a functional collection of variables
the collection of variables being the position in the
various coordinates of the particle
If we have several particles then the wave function becomes
a function of the coordinates of all the particles
We are not gonna go into that today
it's the, I just tell you that the wave function thought of
the wave function of a collection of particles
It is not a function of three-dimensional space
It's a function of all of the coordinates of all of the particles
In the same way the phase space the phase space of a particle
is described by a collection of a large number of coordinates and momenta
in the case of classical physics, the wave function of a particle
is a collection of a system,
It's a collection of a, the function of the collection of all the coordinates
So for example if you have 10 to the 23rd particles
Psi would be a function of 10 to the 23rd coordinates
So that's, that's the basic structure
and you can go to momentum space by Fourier transform
and write the wave function instead
As a wave function of all of the momenta of all particles
you can even have mixed situations mixed representations
Where you may describe a wave function in terms of coordinates
of some of the particles and momenta of the other particles
This is also allowed
But we are gonna focus on the case of one-dimensional motion again
We will come back to that and just discuss the behavior of the wave function
It's properties, just a little bit
Mainly properties in Schrodinger equation
First the uncertainty principle
Where does the uncertainty principle come from?
It comes from the fact that x and coordinate p don't commute
whenever two coordinates or two observables don't commute
It becomes impossible to measure both of them simultaneously
because there are in eigenvectors which are eigenvectors of both observables
In particular the eigenvectors of X are extremely different
Every eigenvector of X is extremely different from every eigenvector of p
The eigenvectors of X are sharp narrow highly localized functions in space
And the eigenvectors of momentum first of all complex
e to the IPX, but their real and imaginary parts
are oscillations over all of the space
And so it's space filling
They are not space filling, it's not that the particle fills space
It's just the particle is every where equally likely to be everywhere
when it's momentum is known
So that's the most primitive observation of the uncertainty principle
If you know the position of the particle
You certainly don't know it's momentum or
If a particle is in a position eigenstate
It's very far from momentum eigenstate
If it is momentum eigenstate, it's very far from a position eigenstate
That's the most primitive version of it
You can say more qualitatively
And then we will come to quantitative,
come to quantitative for precise theorem at the moment
But if we look at the wave function as a function of x
And it's relationship by Fourier transform dP over the square root of 2 pi
Psi twiddle of p, e to the ipx
And I won't bother writing the other relationship
The other relationship is the one that writes psi of p in terms of psi of x
And just start fooling around, trying to construct Psi of p or Psi of x
One from the other by Fourier transform
And you will very quickly discover that the narrower the distribution in x
The boarder the distribution in p will be
That's the property just of the Fourier analysis
That the narrower psi of x is
The boarder psi of p is, and vice versa
That psi of P is very narrow, it means that it just
It's just basically a single plane wave,
It is very broad in x, and so that's a pattern of Fourier transform
The narrower the function is, the broader it's Fourier transform is
That's the qualitative understanding of the uncertainty principle
But let's try to do it a little bit better
Let's try to see if we can define the notion of uncertainty
And then to see if we can prove a theorem
I'm gonna prove a slightly simplified version of the theorem
mostly because there's just too much on the blackboard
if I prove the full general theorem
I will prove a simplified version of it
But the simplified version of it contains the basic ingredients
Alright first of all, what is meant by the uncertainty in a variable?
You have some distribution for that variable
and the first thing to do before discussing the uncertainty in it
is shift the axes so that the average of x, let's say this is
Let's say this is X, so that the average of X is zero
you can always do that, if the average of X is not zero
Let's suppose you have some wave function like that
X equals to zero is over here
If you put your center of coordinates over here
Obviously the average of X the expectation value of X will be negative
If you put your coordinates over here, the the average of X will clearly be positive
and as you move the origin, you will eventually find the position
where the average of X is exactly equal to zero so
Let's simplify our story by shifting coordinates
It's just a shift of coordinates, just shifting our coordinates
until the average value of X is equal to zero
average of X is equal to zero
Then what would, we've done it, the average of x is equal to zero
what is the uncertainty? the uncertainty by definition
is the average of X square,
and looking at the average of X, is zero because anything on this side
is balanced by something on this side
X is positive over here X is negative over here
so looking at the average of it the average will cancel
if you choose your axes in the right place
But the average of X square, X square measured relative to this
located x here, will not be zero
X squared is nonzero here, x square is nonzero here
In fact that's the only place where the X square is zero
Just right at the origin, so there is no way that the average of X squared
can be, can be zero
in fact the broader the wave function,
the larger the expectation value of X squared will be
That's clear, so a good measure, a good measure of the width of the distribution
You can call the uncertainty of x,
and that is the definition really of the uncertainty of an x
It's the average of X squared
the average value of X squared with a given probability distribution
Given that the average of x itself is equal to zero
That is the uncertainty of X,
And that's just called a positive number, delta X squared
and the broader the distribution the larger it will be
How do you calculate it if you know the wave function?
Very simply you take the integral of Psi star psi of x
That's the probability to find the particle at X, times X squared
that's the expectation value of X squared
That is the average of X squared
The probability to find the particle at position X times X squared
that's the definition of the square of the uncertainty
that's the square of the uncertainty of X
What does it say? It's the definition but it's a good definition
Let me rewrite it up here,
Delta x and I will square it, is equal to the integral of psi star psi
Times X squared dx, alright now what about the uncertainty in momentum?
the uncertainty in momentum is defined in a very similar way
Oh, one other point, and this is equal to psi X squared psi
It's the expectation value in the state psi of x x squared,
Thought of as a quantum mechanical
This is the quantum mechanical formula,
the expectation value of X squared that's the uncertainty
What about the uncertainty in momentum?
In fact for that matter what about the uncertainty in anything?
The uncertainty in anything assuming it's average is equal to zero
is just the average of the square of that quantity
that's the general definition
Incidentally if you are if you don't want to shift the coordinates
so that the average is equal to zero
you can use another definition, and the other definition is that
It's the expectation value of X squared minus
the expectation value of x, squared
So two different things, the expectation value of the square of something
is not the square of the expectation values
In particular, if the expectation value of X is equal to zero
it does not follow the expectation of x square is equal to zero
This is a more general definition of the square of the uncertainty in x
But as I said you can always shift your axes around
so that this is equal to zero, I just choose this one here
okay what about the expectation what about the uncertainty of momentum?
The uncertainty of momentum is defined in essentially the same way
You can define it if you like using the Fourier transform the wave function
and then it would just be, I'm not going to use this definition
but let's just do it, delta p squared would be the integral psi twiddle of p
psi of p times P squared dP
This would be the probability that the particle has momentum P
times P squared integrate over p,
but I'm not going to do it this way
What I'm gonna do is just observe this quantity over here
has nothing but, psi p square psi
And now I'm going to work in the position representation
We can do that because we know what the operator p is
when it acts on a wave function psi of x,
what is P do? what does the operator P do
when it acts on a wave function in the, in the X basis
what it does, well first of all whenever you take expectation values
or inner products, you will have a integral of dx to do
From the bra vector here you would have psi star of x
The ket side of this is P squared time psi
What is p squared? P is minus i d by dx
I'm using that now,
momentum operator p is minus i d by dx
And p square is just minus d second d by dX square, second derivative
that's what a p square is,
twice with P once and then twice,
So, this is equal to the integral dx psi star of X, d second psi by d x squared
with a minus sign, the minus sign coming from minus i times minus i
Hey, look at this and you worry a little bit
There is a minus sign here, how can the uncertainty in P be negative?
What does it mean to have a negative uncertainty of P?
There is a minus sign here, what's going on?
What's going on is that the integral here is negative
That's all that is going on
How do you see that the integrals are negative?
You integrate by parts, so I will just remind you the rule for integrating by parts
is if you have, I'm gonna use this over and over
Two functions F and G
Then the integral F dG by dx is equal to
minus the integral dF by dx, time G dx
This is true as long as F and G go to zero appropriately at infinity
So that the boundary terms don't contribute to the integration by parts
Just look at the structure of it, I will use it over and over
You can switch the derivative from one factor to the other factor
at the cost of a minus sign, that's the, that's the basic rule
Okay so let's, this is a second derivative
Second derivative is also of course a first derivative
Namely it's the first derivative of the first derivative
d psi by dx
Let's do a integration by parts,
All we have to do is switch the d by dx to psi star and change the minus sign
Okay? So this becomes d X, put the dx over here,
the d by dx can switch to the psi star at the cost of a change of sign
So this becomes plus and this becomes d psi star by dx
Now look what we have here, we have d psi by d X
And we have d psi star by dx
This factor is the complex conjugate of this factor
It is just complex conjugate of each other
and what happens if you multiply a complex conjugate of a function
by it's complex conjugate?
First of all it's real, and second of all it's positive
So the integrand here is positive, the sign got changed
to plus, and this is most definitely a positive integral here
so P squared, this is the expectation value of P squared
>>Do we know that the average of P is zero?
We can always shift P until it's zero
Now the real question is
Can you have both the average of X and the average of P equal to zero?
That's not so obvious, the answer is yes
You can always, you can always shift for us to shift X equal to zero
and then you can shift the p equal to zero
There is a trick, you know I think of coming but
let's come back to it, ask me again, I don't want to get off the track
The answer is yes, you can take a wave function and shift it both in x and p
Until both of them have average equal to zero
We will come back to it, I will explain to you why in a little while
But let's suppose we've done that
And let's see if we can find a relationship between the uncertainty in x
and the uncertainty, they are none in relationship
But it is supposed to call as a relationship in mathematics
but a inequality is what I want, an inequality,
the inequality should be such that
When delta x is small, delta p is big
delta p is small, delta x is big, or better yet
the product of delta X times Delta P cannot be smaller than what
Than h bar, now I've lost h bar in here
Because I set it equal to one
We would put it back later, but if you want to put it in here
Now we should probably put it in here as one of the h bar squared here
The H bar squared here, and the H bar squared here
but let's not, do I have the right place? yes I do
But let's work with h bar equal to one and later on
when we are finish I will put back the dimensional quantities
Okay so here we are,
What tools that we have to construct inequalities?
It's basically one of the zillion inequalities in mathematics
but probably the most famous and most useful
and the only one I know it's a particular useful is the triangle inequality
Everybody know the triangle inequality?
Some people do, some people don't
So I will tell it to you, and it comes in two forms
It's a statement about triangles of all things
What it says is if you have a triangle
that the sum of any two sides is bigger than the third side,
Obviously true right? The sum of this side and this side,
Why is that?
Because the shortest distance between any two points is the straight line
So the shortest distance between these two points is this one
Any other two sides or sum of the two sides is certainly bigger
So if we have three sides, there is also another version of it
Tell you what I think I'll prove the other version,
but you know the other version pretty well
Also let's call this one A, let's call this one B, let's call this one C
Okay so A+ B is bigger than C,
or A+B is bigger than C
|A|+|B| is also by the same argument it is the same thing
is bigger than |A+B|, if these are vectors, think of these as vectors
Here's a vector A, here's a vector B
C is not A+B , it's A minus B in this case
I think I want it this way, A B C
Okay still a triangle, A+B is bigger than C which is the same as saying
It's bigger than A+B, let's square it, let's square it
and this becomes A square, square the side of A, plus B square,
plus twice |A|, |B| is bigger than this guy over here
What's the square of A plus B?
It is A squared plus B squared plus twice the dot product of A B
where did they get that from?
I wrote that A+B squared is just A+B dot A+B
That's the square of the length of a vector and
that's A squared plus B squared, plus twice the dot product of A and B
and so we have now an inequality from which
we can erase A square and B square from both sides
Here's another form of triangle inequality
Let's erase the two-s, what it says is if you have any two vectors
Given any two vectors, here's one vector, here's another one A B
That the product of the set,
the length of one of them times the length of the other
is always bigger than, these two disappears
It is bigger than the dot product
There is another way to think about that
What was the dot product in terms of length of A and length of B
and something else
What else do I need to know to calculate the dot product?
Cosine of the angle, so A dot B is of course nothing but
A B cosine of the angle
Cosine of an angle is always less than one
So the triangle inequality is pretty trivial,
It simply says that the magnitude product of the magnitude of two vectors
is always bigger than the dot product between them
because the dot product always has a cosine
Now this is true for vectors in two dimensions, three dimensions
100 zillion dimensions, it is even true for vectors in complex vector spaces
It's just generally true for vectors in any kind of vector space
that magnitude defined as the square root of the inner product
of the vector with itself, that this inequality is true in fact
Let's write this a copy, and let's square it because
We are gonna use the square form, A square, B squared is greater than
A dot B square, I just squared the, I might have done anything ..
That's the inequality that we are gonna use
Yes it should be greater than or equal to, the only time it is equal
is when A and B are on the same direction
That's right, greater than or equal to
Cosine theta is equal to, it's equal to one
That's going to be our, other trick, so I don't think I need this anymore
We will come back to it, yeah we will
In a look it looks promising we have a Delta X squared here
Sort of like A squared, we have a Delta P squared here sort of like B squared
And we want to show that it's bigger than something
So the trick is to define the right A-s and B-s in terms of psi and x and so forth
and then just use the theorem,
but I'm going to make one simplifying assumption
I've already made two simplifying assumptions
that the expectation value of X and P are zero
that I will show you how to arrange
And that is, there is no trickery here,
The simplifying assumption I'm going to make only because
I don't want to fill up the blackboard with more algebra than I need
Than necessary, this is something you can sit down with
And go through it for the more general case
I'm going to assume that the wave function psi of X is real
if I didn't, we'd be chasing around psi-s and psi stars and
I would eventually tire you out and you would probably
lose the thread of the argument
so I'm going to assume that psi is real
It will save us some algebra it's not general
but it's very easy to fill in the steps for complex psi
Easy but it takes a few more lines
and I just I just after sitting down and doing it on a piece of paper
I just decided it was too much for a blackboard presentations to do
that if you do it for the simple case, so psi is real
Okay so here we are, we can get rid of the psi stars
and I think I lost in the equation here
Using the fact that P is minus i d by dx, we proved that
this is equal to integral d psi star by dx, d psi by dx,
We should mind you, just quickly remind you how we did it
P squared was a second derivative, well minus second derivative
And then we do integration by parts
Take one of the derivatives and put it over here
What we are trying to prove is the product of this times this
is bigger than something, product of this times this is bigger than something
okay and to do so, is just, think of A and B as vectors,
in fact you can think of A and B as either bra vectors and ket vectors
Since psi is real, it doesn't matter whether they are bra vectors or ket vectors
But here is what it gonna be, one vector A,
I'm writing them now in vector in the bra-ket notation
The triangle inequality is perfectly true for bras kets
as well as for ordinary vectors
Alright so the vector A is going to be describe
It is going to be the vector whose wave function is not psi of x, but x psi of x
A is the vector whose wave function is x psi,
That's another words it's x, operating on psi
And B is going to be the vector P times Psi, or basically minus i
d psi by d x, when I write equals here I mean to say that
A is a vector whose wave function x psi of x,
B is a vector whose wave function i d psi by dx
We are gonna apply the triangle inequality to that
Okay, notice that with this definition here delta x squared
is a squared, look at it, the inner product of A with itself
A squared is just the integral of psi star psi times x square
So this is here A square, with this notation
What about this one? This one here is essentially
B squared, inner product of B with itself
How come I don't have a, I have a minus i d by dx here
If I put minus i d by dx over here, I have a minus sign times minus sign
which is minus one, How come I don't get,
how come I have a plus one and minus one?
Complex conjugation, so this is B squared, that's A squared
And A square times B squared is this, it is also delta x squared
times delta p squared, so delta x squared, delta p squared
A squared B squared, the triangle inequality is literally talking about
delta x squared, delta p squared
So now let's look at the other side of the inequality here
The other side of the inequality is A dot B square
So let's compute A dot B, it's the inner product of these two vectors
and then we squared it, we take the absolute value and square it
Because we take the absolute value I don't have to keep track of i-s minus i-s
In the end they will all go away, because they take the absolute value
And so the inner product of A dot B is going to be equal
It is going to have an integral, oh, one thing
I did say that I'm going to choose psi to be real
So all of these psi stars don't matter they just psi
Everyplace there is a psi star, you can think of it as psi
Okay so let's take A dot B squared that's going to be A which is psi of x, x
x is written as this in the opposite order
And then times B which is going to d psi by dx
As I said I'm not worried about psi-s or i-s
For the simple reason that in the end I'm going to take the absolute value
So that doesn't play any, that will play no role
And let's look at this quantity, now we have A dot B squared
So I can multiply this by itself, if I want to multiply it by itself
I can multiply it by another integral of the same type
y d psi by dy, this is d x, this is dy,
What I'm doing is writing the same thing twice
So if I can evaluate this I'm also evaluating this
Okay so here's the trick, the trick is to say d psi by dx times psi
Does that ring a bell to you? d psi by dx time psi?
>>
No no no, not the derivative law, in the derivative law
It was in the denominator, you are on the right track though
It's the derivative of the square of psi,
It's one half the derivative of the square of psi
Derivative of the square of psi is equal to twice psi d psi by dx
So apart from the fact that there are a two
What we have here is x times the derivative of psi squared with respect to x
Everybody see that? You are allow to if you don't
Okay, I can remove this psi here and replace this by psi square
And at the same time put a factor of two, one half,
That give the same thing with the other factor
Same thing here, psi squared, by another factor of two
which makes all together a factor of a quarter
And as I said this is, I don't know why I'm doing it
but these are just y square,
but it's a square by writing the same thing down again
Okay next, integration by parts, you have a derivative here
It's a derivative of psi square, but still just a derivative
and when you have a function times a derivative to be integrated
you can switch the derivative to the other function
At the cost of a sign, but really it has no cost of the sign
Because this is another sign from this one over here
So there is no real cost in sign, besides we're taking the absolute value
So this is equal to integral of psi squared
times d x by dx, and likewise overhere integral psi squared dy by dy
dx by dx, that's familiar, that is just one
And this is just squaring the same thing again
We are finished, we are finished because what is this integral of one quarter?
Forget the quarter, what's the integral of psi squared?
Psi square is psi star psi, if psi is real
Psi star psi is the same as psi square
What's the integral of psi squared? one
It is the integral of the probability of all space
So each of these integrals is one if the wave function is normalized
We assume that the wave function is normalized
We assume the state vector is normalized
This whole thing is just one quarter
And we have proved now the uncertainty principle from the triangle inequality
That delta x squared times delta p squared is bigger than one quarter
One quarter I remind you came from two factors like this
Or if we wish to just we can just write this is
We just take the square root of both sides
Delta x, delta p is bigger than one half,
Now what about units?
x and p are not inverse to each other
so the product of an x and the p can't be a pure number
What is inverse to an x is a p over h bar,
So really this is delta p over h bar if I put back the units
Or basically delta x delta p is bigger than a half h bar
That's, this is the theorem that asserts the uncertainty principle
That's the uncertainty in position times the uncertainty momentum
is bigger than h bar
Now this would be true for any direction in space
Pick any direction in space, take or any particle any coordinate
Any generalized coordinate in mechanics
It's uncertainty times the uncertainty and
the corresponding conjugate momentum is bigger than h bar
So that's a bigger than h bar or over two as a matter of fact
Any questions about the uncertain about this particular version
of the uncertainty principal?
>>Yeah, another term,
>> zero, right?
>>after it times a variable B, it's integral of F time G minus derivative
>>the opposite derivative
Let's call it F prime G plus G prime F
Now if you integrate this equation right this
If you integrate this equation, this is the integral of F times G
Plus the integral of G times F is equal to the integral d by dx F G
But the integral of a derivative is just the difference between
the integrand at the two end point of integration
So this is FG between the two end points infinity and minus infinity
The symbol stands for FG evaluated at infinity minus
FG evaluated in the other end of integration
And what I am assuming is that psi goes to zero at infinity
which would have to do if it is normalized
If it is a integral as finite, the probability distributions is normalized
It means that the wave function has to go to zero, so this is zero
So this is just a rule that you can interchange
where you put the derivative at the cost of a sign
Okay, any other question about the uncertainty principle?
>> and see I don't know if some small point in the
No it's not small point,
when you prove that something is bigger than something else
You can then ask a question can it ever be equal to that something else?
The answer may or may not
You know, you may have prove the inequality
which was not the tightest inequality we could have proved
Could have been somebody come along smarter and proved
A tighter inequality that's got a be bigger than something else
A stronger inequality, in this case it is not true
You can't find wave functions for which delta x delta p is equal to h bar over two
So that co-minimal uncertainty wave packs
So it's really, it's not a nontrivial one
>> It doesn't apply to time and energy?
Well yes, it does, but the circumstances under which you use it
are less clear and I don't really have time to explain now,
at some point in these courses we will probably want to think about it
but do remember that the time dependence of wave function
The time dependence of a wave function psi of t is a function of time
It is a sum over the eigenvectors of the energy,
Let's call it sum over all the energy eigenvectors of e to the minus i Et
That's time, times the energy eigenvector times a, times a function let's call it
Let's call it Phi of E,
So the relationship between the wave function as a function of time
and the wave function as a function of energy is once again
you sum up things, energy with phases like this
to get things as a function of time, that's the Fourier transform relationship
So it's, but exactly how you use it is, I'll give you an example of how you use it
If you have some wave function moving past you
Moving past you and you ask how long does it take
for the wave function to actually pass you
and this could be a light beam incidentally
but how long does it take for the wave function to move past you?
Another words what's the uncertainty in the time in which the wave function
might have maximum, maximum,
how long does it take the maximum to get past you
that you can call delta t uncertainty in time
that the wave function arrived right at your nose
It's related to the uncertainty in the energy of the wave function
the bigger the uncertainty in the energy, well, let's say it in the other way
The smaller the uncertainty in the energy,
the bigger the uncertainty in when that wave packet will pass you for example
For example that's the energy time uncertainty relation
So any pair of things which are related by Fourier expansion
and this is a Fourier expansions, writing phi of t as a sum or an integral
over oscillations, any two things which are related in that fashion
will have the uncertainty principle
There are lots of other conjugate pairs like this
The angle of, supposing you have a rigid body rotating about a point
Where the angle theta characterizing its position,
then the angle theta and the angular momentum
are exactly in the same kind of relationship
Uncertainty in angle times uncertainty in angular momentum
This is also has h bar over two also
So very similar kinds of things
Any other kinds of questions?
Let's turn to the Schrodinger equation
The Schrodinger equation is a equation for the way
wave function changes with time
It also governs the way expectation values,
if you know how the wave function changes with time
Then you can try to do how the expectation values of observables
change with time
One of the things we would like to do is to see the relationship
between the motion of wave packets governed by the Schrodinger equation
and their classical counterparts namely the motion of systems
Systems in this case being the particle
We would like to see that as long as the wave packet is narrow
and not to crazily spread out and not, you know it has a nice bell shaped curve
And stays a bell shaped curve for some length of time
That the wave functional center of the wave function moves in a way
which is familiar from classical mechanics
We need to be able to do that make any relationship between the classical
and the quantum mechanical things we've been talking about
Okay now we talked about this, I'm gonna, let's, let's first write the
general Schrodinger equation, I'm gonna take you back a couple of lectures now
Take you back a couple of lectures
and go through the derivation of how a wave packet moves
The answer is the wave packet moves
so the center satisfies a classical equations of motion
I'm not going to do that in a new way
I'm gonna go right back to the old way that we've already talked about
and to do that, refresh the wall in order to know how the wave function changes
We need to know the Hamiltonian
And let's just remind ourselves how it works
The way state vectors change with time
i d psi dt is governed by the Hamiltonian acting on psi
If we let it take for our Hamiltonian
P squared over two m, that's the Hamiltonian for classical particle
Why we should take it for a quantum mechanical particles
It's not obvious, and what might we add to that to put some
To put the particle in a force field
We might add a potential energy function
Potential energy function might be plus V of x,
Okay so that would be the classical Hamiltonian for particle
moving in a potential energy function V of x
and we can take that we can lift that right from classical mechanics
and think of it as a quantum mechanical Hamiltonian
and then check afterwards,
Is the wave packet really moving the way classical mechanics would say
that the, that the classical particle moves
Alright, so let's try that, in a little while
we will just work with this abstract equation here
but let's just see what it says
A H on psi, H on psi,
Instead of working with abstract ket vectors,
we can work with wave functions
and what this equation would say would be i d psi of x by dt is equal,
Now p squared, what is p?
p is minus i d by dx, p squared,
that's minus d by dx squared, or d second by dx squared
There is a one over 2m, minus one over 2m, times psi
But what is V of x? Is V of x an operator?
Yes V of x is an operator
by definition this is a definition now
I told you what the operator x does,
The operator x, we multiplies a wave function, just multiplies it by x
The corresponding thing for a general V of x
is the meaning of the operator V of x,
is that it multiplies the wave function by V of x
We didn't talk about that much, we didn't talk about functions of x
The function of x is just defined in the obvious way
As thought of as operators, they operate on wave functions
just to multiply it by d of x
>>
Functions of operators, yes V of x is a function of position
X multiply psi of x, V of x, also multiplies
and you can take this as definition,
The, um, when you make a definition of course,
you later wanna prove that it's a useful definition
You not just make definition, you make definitions and then show that
they are the either are valuable because they are easy to work with
Or they are valuable because they relate things
to previous things you already knew
or what I'm wanna shows is that this definition of how V of x acts
That the Schrodinger equation will in fact make particles move
according to classical orbits, or at least make wave packets
insofar as they don't spread too much,
move according to the classical equations of motion
Alright so, that's one term, d sec one over 2m
Second derivative of psi, and the other terms is just plus V of x, times psi of x,
When V of x acts on psi of x, they just multiplies it
And this becomes the Schrödinger equation
This is the Schrödinger equation for how the wave function changes with time
Also depending on time,
Let's at the same time write, now I want to do with this
I'm gonna be interested in d psi by dt
So I think I'll multiply in a way there is an i
What do we do? If we multiply, if you wanna get rid of an i
You would multiply by minus i right?
Minus i times i is one
We multiplied by minus i,
That would give us minus sign with an i here
And put a minus i here, that's psi dot if you like
The left-hand side of psi dot, Let's also write down d psi star of x and t
with respect to t
It is not a new equation, it's just the complex conjugate of this one
and that one will be minus i over 2m, d second psi star by d x squared
plus i V of x, psi of x
>>
I think I got it right,
Did I make a mistake?
Oh yeah, good, psi star
Those are the Schrodinger equations
They are equivalent to each other, I just wrote them both
Because I'm gonna need them both,
Now what do we wanna do?
We want to see how various expectation values change with time
If we identify the expectation value with more or less
the center of the wave packet
If the wave packet looks like this
The center of the wave packet will be close to the expectation value
And so let's identify the center of the wave packet with the expectation value
and ask how expectation values change with time
See if we can work it out
Alright, so let's start with x, let's see if we can calculate d by dt
of the expectation value of x, and that of course is d by dt of the integral
Psi star of x, x squared, no just x psi of x, dt, d by dt
Another word it's the velocity of the center of the wave packet
That's all this is, it's the velocity of the center of the way packet
Why does it change?
It changes because psi changes,
How do we know how psi changes?
We know how psi changes, because we know the Schrödinger equation
So this is gonna be a little exercise, a little bit too tedious for my taste
To do at the blackboard, it's not very tedious
But still, I may cut little pieces, picks shortcuts
But I will tell you when I do
Okay so this is what we want to calculate
and is of course x is just x, it's not dependent on time
but psi star and psi are dependent on time
So when I differentiate, I will get the term from each one of these
and this will give me integral d psi star of this
I will write d by dt,
d psi star, x psi, plus integral psi star x psi dot
One term coming from differentiating with respect to time psi star
Another from differentiating psi, each one has x in there
And now of course this is just psi star dot,
First thing is we don't really have to calculate both of these
These are complex conjugates of each other
We have psi star dot here, we have psi dot here
We have psi here, psi star here, and x is real
So in fact, all we have to do is calculate one of them
and add its complex conjugate
That is all we have to do or equivalently just take twice the real part
Adding something to its complex conjugate,
the imaginary parts cancel, and it's twice the real part
So we can use that, I'm not sure I need it, but
let's, It's twice the real part of this
Twice this, and keep in mind that we throw away anything that's imaginary
We throw away anything that is imaginary
because we add the complex conjugate and we throw it away
Okay so now let's plug in d psi star by dt over here
And that gives us minus i over to 2m
d second psi, let's see what we do, it's a plus some psi
Plus i, it's the upper equation there,
d second psi by d x squared, and there is a minus i V of x, psi
Okay, now the first thing we can see immediately
is that the term of V of x, is pure imaginary
The psi star, there is an x, the psi, psi star psi is certainly real
x is real, V of x, the potential energy is real
And there is an i there, so the first thing to conclude is that
the V of x doesn't contribute at all, it doesn't contribute at all
because when you multiply, you add the complex conjugate, it will cancel
So in this fact in this equation we can throw this away over here
Psi star x, V of x psi, that's real, and imaginary part cancels
So you can throw this away,
Okay next what's the next?
Integrate by parts, it's always the next step
Always the next step integrate by parts
We have here a derivative, It is the second derivative
but a second derivative is also a first derivative
Let's write it that way d by dx, of d psi by dx,
incidentally partial derivatives have no, well yeah, they do mean something
They mean the derivatives with respect to x without changing time
So that's our equation and now I want to integrate by parts
which means I want this d by dx over here to shift to the other factor,
I wanna shift it to the other factor, I'm gonna have two terms
Let's look at what those two terms are
The first term, the d by dx will just hit x
What does that give? What is d by dx? one
So that will give me twice integral psi star
The x will disappear when d by dx hits it
and there is d psi by dx, alright d psi by dx,
This derivative got shifted to here
There is an i, I think over 2m right?
There is an i that I left out, over 2m
Oh, where else did I miss out?
Integration by parts, minus, that's one term
Now again you might think this is dangerous i here
We should throw it away, because it's imaginary,
but it's not imaginary its real
We will see that in a moment,
we will in fact, we will see exactly what it is in a moment
But lets do the other term, the other turn has an i over 2m
i over 2m, there will be an x, the x does not get differentiated now
x and then there is d psi star of x,
and now the derivative hits the psi star,
and we get derivative of psi star times derivative of psi
Okay, this derivative now hits the psi star,
There is an i here, an explicit i, and this is to be integrated over x
Still underneath the integration here, how about this?
What's the reality property of this? Is this real or imaginary?
This is probably a minus, ya there is a minus
But it's imaginary, this is the complex conjugate of this
And x is real, so this integral here, the integral here is perfectly real
it gets multiplied by minus i and then the whole thing is imaginary
It will get eaten when you add the complex conjugate
So the only thing that's left is this, i over 2m with a minus sign
Times psi star d psi by dx,
I'm gonna tell you exactly what this is
What is minus i d by dx? It's p right? It's p
Minus i, d by dx is p, so what this is?
It's the expectation value of p divided by m
P over m, just look at it,  minus i d by dx is the same as p on psi
multiply by psi star, that's the bra vector, integrated over x
That's just taking the inner product,
In fact it's real, in fact it is really real
It looks imaginary because of this, but if you go and study it carefully
You find its real and what it is
It is the expectation value of the momentum divided by m
So now we've proved an interesting theorem
We've proved that dx by dt is equal to p over m
We've seen this before,
this is the classical relation between velocity and momentum
Mass times velocity is momentum
Now what we found is that this is going to be
a feature of the motion of a wave packet
If we have a wave packet that moves in a nice way
so that it holds itself together
What you may or may not do, but if it does,
If for an regime of parameters with a wave packet moves
like a nice, nice wave packet, then we will find that
the expectation value, it's momentum defined in this way
will be related to the expectation value of the velocity of the wave packet
through the standard classical mechanical equations
Okay that's half of mechanics, what's the other half of mechanics?
We found that d p, oops, I just give it away
dx by dt is p over m, what's the other half?
dp by dt, that is Newton's law
time derivative of momentum is called force
So let's see if we can do the same thing with momentum
>> you said that if everything is presented nicely
>> we didn't have a nice assumption of theorization
>>it just look classically it fit in nicely
Right, ya, there was no there was no assumption here
There will be as we'll see a certain assumption in the other equation
No assumption here of that type,
If the wave packet is really crazy, it might not mean anything very sensible
but still, that was a,
Nothing I get up till now depended on
the approximate notion of how wave packet moves
Okay we got this,
Let's see if we can get the other half
Now I don't guaranteed to get through it
without all sorts of errors and i and minuses
Let's try this one,
p the average of p is gotten by acting with p on psi
And that's minus i, that would give us minus i which I will put over here
But then, d by dx, d psi by dx
We could put the d psi, we could put the derivative over here
integration by parts, the sign change but I will leave it over here
>>remain of x
>>
No, no, we want the time derivative of the momentum
What would you like to see?
You want to see the time derivative of the momentum?
It is governed, let's write this equation
P dot is equal to force, that's it,
What is force in terms of the things I've written on the blackboard?
Minus dV by dx, so this is what I am gonna show,
minus dV by dx, but I will show it in the form that
d by dt of  the expectation value of the momentum
It is minus the expectation value of dV by dx,
dV by dx is also a function of x, since V is a function of x
dV by dx is a function of x,
It's called the force, or what this says is
the average rate of change of momentum is the average of the force
The force, dV by dx with a minus sign
Okay so that's what we wanna show,
We wanna show dp by dt is dv dx, that's all
And how we're gonna show it?
Once again I'm gonna show it by using Schrödinger equation
It tell us how things change with time
Okay so let's see now, It's a little bit unpleasant I'm not sure
Alright, when I debating, let's start working it out then let's
At some point I may say well I know this goes away and this doesn't go away
We will say how it goes
So first of all this goes as the integral psi star dot times d psi by dx, minus i
And then there is another term where that come from
differentiating psi star with respect to time
There is gonna to be another term where d by dt will hit psi
Okay, so what will that be?
That will be again minus i, integral psi star,
Now the order of differentiation doesn't matter
So this can be written as d by dx of psi dot
Just wondering at one point I'm gonna regret
not having done integration by parts
But it won't matter because we do the integration by parts
I will regret it, I will regret it, I will just go ahead
Is there an extra i?
No I don't think, no I don't think so
I think it's right, okay,
Oh you know what, I think it will be convenient to integrate this one by parts
If I integrate this one by parts I will get a plus i here
and d psi star by dx here, another reason it's convenient is
because the thing in here is the complex conjugate of thing here
Psi dot star, well that's a complex conjugate of psi dot,
d psi by dx, that's the complex conjugate of psi star
But notice it's i times the difference
What do I get when I take i times the difference of two complex conjugates?
You get a real thing again
So I think it's just the real part of this?
Well let's just keep going on, my eye, let's just keep going
We can erase this and remember in the end
That the answer has to be twice the real part of this
twice the real part of this, and we don't have to keep track of both of them
Okay now what do we do? We plug in the Schrödinger equation
And pray like mad that all goes well
Okay so psi dot is equal to i over 2m
d second psi by dx square minus i V of x psi,
This i cancels this i gives us the minus sign
Well this i here so we make minus
and the i over here time the i over here, I think it will make a plus, plus
We have some of the unpleasant thing, how unpleasant let's see
Not too bad, this piece I believe is pure imaginary, it is, it is,
This is pure imaginary over here,
The way you see it, the way you see it is again integrate by parts
Just this piece here, if I integrate this piece by parts
We will get a derivative, we will get a term with a single derivative of psi
And a second derivative of psi star,
Okay, what we will discover is basically the difference between a thing
and its complex conjugate
There will be a minus sign, let's just see it here, ya let's do it
If I differentiate, oh sorry, integrate it by parts
That'll bring, the derivative over to here
It's pure imaginary, I know that it is
Whenever you have a quantity complex conjugated
Times a derivative of the unconjugated thing you integrated
Tt's always pure imaginary,
We have used this trick before
I'll just tell you right now this piece is pure imaginary
It's not gonna be of any significance
The significant piece is integral d psi star by dx, V of x psi
That's all it's left after we take into account the
Little intricate details of complex conjugation V of x
I can't remember whether we doubled it or not yet
I think we doubled it, I think we doubled it, ya we have to double this
Or add it to it's complex conjugate did I say it right?
Add it to it's complex conjugate, I think
In fact let's do that right now
Let's add it to it's complex conjugate plus the integral of psi star V of x
d psi by dx, alright let's take this and complex conjugate it
I've taken this and complex conjugate this, and it is real
Okay now we are almost there, we have d psi star of x dx times psi
Let's pull out V of x, pull away out here
V of x times this
Now what is d psi?
d psi star by dx times psi plus psi star times d psi by dx
It is the derivative of psi star psi with respect to x
This is derivative of psi star times psi, plus psi star times the derivative of psi
That is nothing but the derivative with respect to x of psi star psi
So let's put that in,
And the next step integrate by parts
Integrate by parts that will take the derivative, derivative over here
And it will give me minus the integral of psi star psi, times dV of x
If I put the psi here on the right, and what is this thing?
The integral of psi star psi times dV dx, that's the expectation value of dV dx
This whole thing is dx minus the expectation value of dV dx
In other words it's exactly this
So we found after a slight bit of painful integration by parts
a little bit of algebra, and throwing away some things
which I told you they are pure imaginary which they were
We find that dp by dt is exactly equal to minus dv by dx
But in the sense of expectation values, in the sense of the expectation value
You know why do I say, this this also is exact
I didn't do anything illegal here, I didn't do any approximation
I will tell you where the use or where it maybe important that
the wave packet have a nice shape
The expectation value of dV by dX is not the same as
V or d, let's just take V, the expectation value of V of x
No let's call it F of x, force,
The expectation value of F of x which is after all minus dV by dx
The expectation value of function of x is not the same thing
As the function of the expectation value of x
This represents the expectation value of X at the center of the wave packet
and this is a function at the center of the wave packet
It is not the same thing as a thing we calculated in general
This is the expectation value of F of x
When they give you an example with a very very different
They could be extremely different, suppose for example that
F were equal to X squared
Supposing the force happen to be X squared
And supposing the wave packet consisted of a pair of bumps
Is that what I want? I think that's what I want
Yes that is exactly what I want
What? Centered around zero. What is the expectation value of X?
What's the F of the expectation value of x? Zero right?
On the other hand what was the expectation value of X squared?
So enough zero, this one has an X squared equal to the X squared of this
It's certainly nonzero
So when wave packets are nice, not nice single bumps
which are mainly characterized by the center like this
Then in general you could not write that
the time rate of change of the momentum is equal to
the force evaluated at the expectation value of X
It's only if the wave functions are nice
And so that concentrated over a fairly narrow range
If you concentrate over a reasonably narrow range
then the expectation value of F of X is the same as the F of the expectation value
This is where we have achieved a little bit in saying
This looks like a classical equation of motion
that depends on the wave packet, they are nice and coherent and localized
One of the circumstances under which
a wave function will remain nicely localized
I will tell you what the circumstances are
The circumstances are the particle is heavy,
If the particle is heavy and takes two things
the particle being fairly heavy and the potential energy
not having too many spikes that having spikes in it or something like that
Spikes when the wave function hit spikes,
it tends to break up, for example
If you have some sort of wave function coming in a nice way,
Wave packet coming in going to the right
And it hits a point structure here, what will it do?
It will spread out all over the place like that
Wave function will disintegrate all over the place
If on the other hand it hits a very smooth potential of some sort
Then it will go through the smooth potential
moving more or less according to the classical equations of motion
So you know, we don't expect quantum mechanics
to reproduce classical mechanics in every possible circumstance
We expect it to reproduce quantum mechanics in circumstances
where particles are heavy and where potentials are nice and smooth
and don't cause a wave function to break up into little pieces
Or disintegrate or scatter all over the place
Okay, let's see if there are any other odds and ends that I want to
You know not tonight, we don't have time for it
>> what sort of physical situation
>> will correspond to potentials that break up the wave packet?
Well, the situation which is bad tends to be when
When the potential has structures and features in it
which let's say have some sign associated with them
Some structure which we could call delta x
Some sign associated with the structure here
And where delta x is significantly smaller
than the uncertainty in position of the particle
If the structures of the, what do we wanna call it then,
The features sharp features of the wave function take place on the scale
which is much smaller than the, than the size of the incoming wave packet
Then it will break up the wave function into a lot of the pieces
Each one will scatter the scatter of different dimensions
into different directions,
Okay let's
>> In the case of  Classical mechanics
>> itself, it's working out right?
No no no you shouldn't expect
Basically when the features in the potential are shorter than the wavelength
shorter than the wavelength of the of the particle
It will break it up into, alright
Now if you were to take a bowling ball and you would ask what is delta x?
Well let's see, typically it's true that, typically delta p times delta x
the rule is bigger than h bar, but in many reasonable cases it's of order h bar
Now p that's about as concentrated as you can get it
But ordinary macroscopic object,
the uncertainty principle is pretty well saturated
delta p times delta x is more or less about equal to h bar
Why that is so is a very complicated question, but very complicated
What is delta p? Delta p is the mass times the delta velocity
So uncertainty of velocity times the uncertainty in position
is h bar over m, and if I put a bowling ball down on the ground
You know very well that the uncertainty of velocity is not very big
The uncertainty of the velocity is, in particulars,
as it gets heavier and heavier you might expect the uncertainty in the velocity
get smaller and smaller
In any case, there is an m down here, and so whatever delta v is
as m gets small, as m gets smaller and smaller
delta x will get bigger and bigger right?
delta x will get bigger and bigger, right
And in particular it will tend to get bigger than the features in the
in the potential, So in a highly quantum mechanical limit
where mass is very small and delta X tends to be big
The wave function will move under the influence of a ragged potential
which are which it sees as being much sharper and much more featured
than wave function itself, that's when it breaks up
On the other hand as m gets very large
delta x gets small, delta x will tend to get small, as as m gets very large
and so for a large bowling ball
the wave packet might be very very concentrated
and when it moves through here, it moves slowly like a tiny wave function
and the tiny wave function thinks that these features are very very broad
moving through broad smooth features doesn't disrupt the wave function
and break it up into pieces
So large mass smooth potentials is the limit of classical physics
light mass and abrupt potentials is more quantum mechanical
>>Just to get a feel about what you mean about large and small
>>if you, an electron, large enough to be of classical
>>
It's the interplay between the shape of the potential and the mass
If you take a very very smooth potential of the kind that you might make
let's say a couple of capacitor plates,
capacitor plates separated by a meter, well not a meter, a centimeter
Where the smooth electric field between them
Then the electron will move through it in a nice coherent
as most classical particle do
On the other hand if you take the potential associated with the with the
core of the atom, the nucleus, that has a sharp feature in it
And that sharp feature will, if an electron wave comes in and hits it
It will scatter all over the place,
so it's a interplay between the mass and the sharpness of the potential
>>Can you do an experiment to show that
Absolutely,
Of course you can do it, no problem, electron very easy
The classic experiment was done in 1911
It wasn't done with electrons, it was done with alpha particles
Alpha particles come in and hit the gold nucleus
Gold nucleus is a small thing, and the result was that
the gold nucleus when the alpha particle comes in
The wave or quantum mechanical wave of alpha particles comes in
Hits that tiny gold nucleus, and it get scattered in all directions
That's why Rutherford was a bit surprised to see that
To see alpha particles get scattered right back at him
And what does it tell him? It tell him the nucleus was very small
He just have a beam of alpha particles some of which hit the center
Some of which went through here,
Alright, but in fact what we really had was a wave
And the wave came in hit the tiny gold nucleus
and get scattered all over the place
And with electrons, yeah, sure, you are gonna use it
That's what happen to accelerators when electrons
hit small targets, oh photons do also, photons do also
Electromagnetic waves as they hit the structure of objects
with structure smaller, smaller than the wavelength
they get scatter all over the place
If they hit very smooth things they tend to propagate
according to the geometric optics
For example if you have a piece of material
with a position varying index of refraction
If that index of refraction is varying very smoothly very slowly
over the wavelength of the photon
Then geometric optics is a good approximation
If on the other hand you have a diffraction grating of
distance comparable or smaller than the wavelength of the radiation
Diffraction grating will spread out all over the place
So it's it's not just the electrons electrons protons and anything
Okay, if there are no other questions,
I'm gonna go home, my son have a baby
For more, Please visit us at Stanford