Stanford University
Well, let's begin, I'm gonna review very quickly, I hope quickly
We describe a simple system consists of one qubit
I'm gonna change that terminology a little bit
I'm gonna start call the qubit a spin
Don't worry about what it has to do with spinning at the moment
Of course, more important is that it's a little pointer
Now I use the term pointer,
I began to use the word pointer to refer the vectors in three-dimensional space
while I was writing I realize that's awfully awkward unfamiliar terminology
And I decided it to replace it with another term, the standard term three vectors
Vectors in three-dimensional space
I may sometimes use the term pointer
but I think I more likely to speak of three-vectors
By three-vectors I mean vectors in a real space
The more general concept when I simply say vector
more likely I'm speaking about the abstract notion of a vector space
and the elements of the vector space
Just to warn you and keep the language clear
Now we've talk about this qubit which has now become a spin
it has some of the character of being a little three-vector in space
There are some sense or other in which it point into that direction
And that we can confirm by an experiment
As I said before, once we start thinking about quantum mechanics
We really do have to think about system and their connection with the apparatus
Apparati? Is that the word call apparati I'm not sure? Apparatus apparatucee?
Anyone know the plural of apparatus?
Or just apparatus? Okay, just apparatus
We do have to think about the connection with the apparatus
That measure them
And we don't get away with just ignoring it
What's the difference? First of all I tell you
what basic difference in classical physics and
quantum mechanics and quantum physics
In classical physics measurement can be arbitrarily gentle
Arbitrarily gentle means you can find out
any thing you want about a system in principle
by inter reacting with something that changes anything about it
by the arbitrarily small amount
For example you want to locate a location of a particle in classical physics
How do you do it? You shine some light on it
You shine some light on it and you make an image
Of course you have to use light which in small enough wavelength
That you can resolve the object, this is true
But there is no limit of how weak a light signal can be at a given wavelength
You can make the light signal as weak as you like
So it carries as little energy as you like, as little momentum as you like
Let it interact with the thing you are interested in
Form image, and after the image has been form, it can't be magnified
Not magnified in the sense of making it bigger
But what's the right word for amplify?
It can't be amplified
So the experiment itself can be arbitrarily gentle
And still find out anything you might want to know about the system
The result of that is experiment can always be done
which have not effect what ever on future experiment
On subsequence experiment for example right afterwards
That's classical physics
Quantum physics is not like that,
quantum physics is such that experiments inevitably change systems,
any experiment to measure something will change something else
It's almost as though the experiment that measure coin
was such that every time I look at the coin
the coin jump up in the air and randomly flip itself
We know that doesn't happen,
we can measure the state of the coin gently without changing it
Quantum mechanics, not so clear, well it is clear
It is clear that cannot be done
Okay, let's but we are gonna call it a little bit
before we move on to more about vectors spaces and operators
and mathematics of a quantum theory
I want to talk a little bit more about the logic of it
And in what way logic in quantum mechanics is different
than logic in classical physics
Let's go back to our spin and our apparatus
The spin is a, we draw a little arrow
whether they are truly correspond to anything looks like a classical or not
is irrelevant, we have to draw it on the blackboard and
Anything I draw on the blackboard will be classical
Just because ink and pens are classical or approximately classical
The apparatus has a window that has a number that comes out of it
Numbers appears in the window tell result of the experiment
And it all start to happen to have a direction in it
which tell you which side is up
How to orient it, in fact I might have a whole set of three-axes
to tell you how to orient it
But that's not important just the up back is what's important
and when the apparatus is pointing up
In fact no matter what the direction the apparatus is pointing in
When interact with the spin, it produces a number in the window
And that number in the window is either plus one or minus one
No matter what the apparatus is pointing in
No matter what has happen to the spin before it()
When the apparatus is pointing up we will say that what it has measured
is the z component of the spin
Let's pus some axes in here
Z up, x to the right and y out of blackboard
And when the apparatus is pointing up,
we will say that it produces an experimental number
Which measures the z component of the spin
It's not particularly interesting to think of it as having a directionality
when we say it's the z component of the spin
Imagining it that the object here has a sense of directionality to it
How can we test it has a direction to it? A sense of directionality to it?
Well, we can prepare the spin
in the state of what we think as pointing up
by simply letting it interact with the apparatus
And when the apparatus appears with a plus one sign in it
We say, aha, the spin is up
And if we do it again with the same apparatus pointing at the same direction
with the same spin, we will get up again
And up again and up again, in that sense quantum mechanics
are out(allows)for reproducible the experiments
If you measure the same thing several times in a row
with the same apparatus
You will get the same answer over and over
So things are not that weird
That's also important because we have to have some
concept of reproducibility of experiment to result
in order to make any sense out of things
so this is a good thing
When you measure something and you measure it again again and again
you get the same answer, yeah
>> so how is that (inaudible)
You are gonna come, we are gonna come to it
Well I didn't say that experiments are so necessarily so ungentle
Then when you measure anything you affect everything
The answer is you affect something
In this case when you measure something you don't affect that same thing
if you measure the same thing again
You will get the same answer
Okay now you could say that now I have detected the spin is up
Let me turn the up of the apparatus completely over
And point down
If this were a thermometer measuring the temperature
I don't think we will expect
it to detect minus temperature if we turn it over right?
No with any kind of decent thermometer
So therefore to say the temperature does not have a sense of orientation
Certainly not at incident
On the other hand if there is a true spin
And we turn the apparatus over
If initially the apparatus told us that the spin was plus one
after we have turn it over and do the experiment again
It will register minus one
So it seem to indicate that there is a sense of directionality
And of course,
the same thing is true no matter what direction we hold the apparatus in
If we hold the apparatus in the horizontal direction
And come along and detect a spin we know nothing about
We have not yet made a measurement on it
Maybe somebody else has made a measurement on it
Maybe some agent available to us who some secret person
has done something to that spin
But we don't know, okay we don't know about it
We come in with our detector and we make a measurement
What will we measure again we will measure plus one or minus one
And if we are beginning to think of this thing
as having a sense of direction to it
We might say that we are measuring now is this x component of the spin
Whereas previously we were measuring the z component of the spin
Let's give them names
Sigma z which is the component of the spin along the vertical axis
At the moment yet I'm not asking you to think this notion of component
is the same as the notion of component in the classical physics
Just the name for the moment
And sigma z when measure is plus one or minus one
The same happens when we turn the apparatus on it's side
And we measure the same procedure
we measure something we can now call sigma x
And sigma x is always plus or minus one
And the same thing if we turn the apparatus around
So that it's facing front or in fact
no matter what direction we orient the apparatus
It always give us plus or minus one
This will be a little bit strange more than a little bit strange
If thie object really were a classical vector
Perhaps a vector of unit length
If it were a vector of unit length
And this detector is really measuring the component of spin along it's own axis
There is no way that it will just give plus one or minus one
A component of the vector
even if the vector is required to have exactly unit length
Here's a vector with exactly unit length a point,
a three-vector exactly unit length
If we turn it and do other things with it
So the x component and z component can be any number
between minus one and one
So this is a funny vector if it's a vector at all
But it still have a sense of orientation and
the result of the experiment do seem to change when you rotate the detectors
In particular if you begin by orienting the spin along the z axis
in the up direction, let's call this up
That means sigma z is equal to plus one
And then rotate the apparatus
Detect it again, you won't necessarily get plus one
In fact you may get plus one, or you may get minus one with equal probability
You can do the experiment over and over and over again
Half the time you will get sigma x equals to plus one
half the time you will get sigma x equals to minus one
Even though you know sigma z was exactly equal to plus one
In which case, so, ah sounds funny?
But what is true is the average value of sigma x will be one
Sorry would be zero,
if the initial starting point of spin that was up along the z axis
Same for the y axis
If the initial value of the spin was prepared to be up along the z axis
And you rotate the apparatus to the right orientation
Again you will have equal probability
So the average value of sigma y would be zero
You can even go beyond that
You can say let's start with the apparatus not vertical
But let's start the apparatus along the x direction
Use it to prepare the spin
so that it's known to be pointing horizontal along the x direction
and sigma x is equal to plus one and do the y z experiment
Always we will get random but equal probability for up and down
Or plus or minus one, you go a little bit further
Of course I'm quoting
what will be the result of the experiments on spins
I haven't done such an experiment I don't think I could
But I have no doubt if I have a student to do it,
this is what will happen
>> suppose you start out we have not prepare the spin at all
Doesn't matter, okay go ahead
>> so it could be up or down or x or y or z
>> we don't know what it is, right?
>> We set it up so that the apparatus on the side along the x axis
okay
>>and then we do measures
Yeah, we first do one measure before we do anything else
Yeah, let me come back for a second, let me come back for a second
You are right, we won't do a lot of experiments
and a lot of measurement in quantum mechanics
There are two distinct way to do quantum mechanics experiments
So it really doesn't matter which we do
We can imagine having a large number of identical spin
prepared from the beginning
however they are prepared
And we can do experiments with a large number of them
Or we can do a repeated experiment on the same spin
There are logic stand to doesn't matter which we are talking about
I will tell you when it matters
But at the moment all we are talking about is one spin
You said, start the apparatus horizontal
stick the spin to it and detect it, what you get?
What you get will either be plus one or minus one
You can then take the spin out of there
Give it to your friend who does magic with the spin
you don't know what it is, you don't know what the hell he does with it
He flips it around juggles it, puts it in his pocket, takes it out
gives it back to you and tells you to do it again
Again, you will get plus one or minus one
And maybe that he did nothing,
in which the second time you get the same answer as the first time
Or maybe he turn it over which you will get the opposite answer
But whatever you get, there will be plus one or minus one
then if you do a repeated experiment
knowing that nothing else was done to the spin in between
You will get the same answer at the same experiment
Okay, that's
Okay, let's be a little more general,
let's suppose we orient the axes of the director in any direction
So let's make a notation for the direction
A unit three vector
Unit vector in three dimensional space
are always indicated by putting a little hat up of the symbol
So this is a unit vector along a particular axis
We start with the detector along with the axis m
not horizontal not vertical not in or out
But just the cardicorter() in some complicated way
That's m, that's m
We start with the spin, let's start with the spin
Previously having been oriented or prepared along a different axis
The n axis, how do we do that?
Well, I should have gone, I should have gone a little slower
We start the detector along the n axis
Do an experiment and discover that along the n axis
the spin comes up plus one
Then we rotate the apparatus into the m direction
And we do another experiment on the same spin
It will either come up plus one or minus one along the m axis
Never in between,
but the average value of the spin along the m axis here will not be one
It will not be minus one
What will it be? It will be the cosine angle between m and n
Another words, the component of m along n
How do we write that, let's write that
Let's write a formula for that
The symbol of averages in quantum mechanics
are parallel angular brackets like this
This one is called the bra, this one is called the ket
And the whole things make a bracket
which is British for bracket
Okay the average value of sigma m
Knowing that it's originally oriented along the n direction
And measure along the n direction
There is a cosine of angle between m and n
Which can also be written as n dot m
The ordinary dot products of the vectors
Or just the component of n along m
The spin is oriented along n direction
you measure along the m direction and the answer is plus or minus one
But on the average it's what a classical physicist might have expected
if you measure the component of the spin
which is oriented in one direction along some other direction
This is exactly the component of m along n
If you do the experiment many many times and collect averages
It seems that average quantities do behave like vectors
Or like three-vectors
But the individual experiments are very resistant
to giving any answers other than plus or minus one
Okay, so this now
>> The apparatus doesn't know how to give the answer (inaudible)
Doesn't know how to get any
You might try to build another apparatus does better
But it won't be better
>> I'm not sure I understand the set up is actually prepare the
the spin along the n axis
You measure it along the m axis
Then you get a random answer but random-biased
Biased in such a way that the average is in that
For example what it means when m and n are the same direction?
That you didn't rotate it at all
What is n dot m indicates?
One, right, and that would just be the indication
that you got the same answer if n was up,
then you did the experiments to get it up and up and up
Over and over and over again
Okay,
>> What is ... here? Would it be more accurate
>> say the expected value of the n times m goes to average?
No, no no, my friend I love to say expected value
It is not the expected value
If I gave you a probability distribution which look like this
What would be the expected value of it? How?
At least the expected value would be the one right in the middle
But the average value would be the one right in the middle
Expected values and average values are very different in general
And this is the average value,
the average if you average the quantity
then you get the standard sense of averaging, standard average
It's also called the expectation value but again that's a misnomer
That's not the value you expect necessarily
>> So when they try, if I think about this right
>> the spin, the only we got the spin is
>> when we measure you get plus one or minus one right?
Right, it's all we know until we do a lot of experiments
>> the z component that has to do with
>> there is nothing to do with the figure
Well, there are different experiments that you can do on a spin
The result of these experiments can be use
Or the particular experiment you do
Can be used to label what it is you measure
>> guess what, for what point are you doing with the spin
>> antagonly, it's up and down
>> plus one or minus one whatever that means we don't know
>> there is some geometric meanings
Yeah, there is no geometric meanings to begin with
But we did discover that by turning this thing over
we always get the opposite side
Well, let's not even tell us that there is some difference
Between the apparatus up and apparatus down
It's not like a thermometer measuring temperature
Some notion there that is different to the up and down
And then if we turn on the side we find out in some sense
it does behave on an average like a vector
On the average
But it is what it is
>> that vector changes in prepared?
>> it's that when you prepared, you may have
>> if you got average it one way, and then you prepare the average another way
>> it may have a z component, is that correct?
Yeah, so it is what it is, so I've told you a fact
Facts are if you first prepare by putting your apparatus along n direction
And then measure with the apparatus along the other direction
The average value of the results would be n dot m
But ever single event would be plus one or minus one
Nothing left to say, say it any way
>> if n is in the same direction or opposite direction with m
>> Then it's not just an average, it repeats itself
>> what if you takes the other
But if a number or result can only be plus one or minus one
And the average is plus one, it mean every event is plus one
Okay, let's talk about logic a little bit
A problem of quantum mechanics is that logic
the logic of a quantum system is different than the logic of a classical system
but our brains are classical systems incapable of thinking in quantum logic
Nevertheless we can get a glimmering of what quantum logic is like
By thinking about this experiments
We can either talk about the calculus of these propositions
Or the nature of the states of a system
Space of states of a system
Let's start with the space of states of a system
Space of states of a system being classically for a moment
They are set, they are set of possible states
Here they are, heads and tails, six five four three two one for the die
Particle on a line would have infinite number of states
But the state form is set as some type
The proposition about the state of a system is basically a subset
It's a subset of states for which the proposition is true
So for the die, my proposition that the die shows a even face
That's a proposition and it's true for half this states of die
And so it correspond to the subset of two four six
The contradictory statement, the NOT statement
NOT the die shows an even face
That's obviously the equivalent to the statement
that the die shows an odd face
And so in classical logic, the NOT of the statement
The NOT means the contradictory of a statement
If this is the statement mean the same is true
for the subset of states in here
But the NOT statements is the statement
is the component of collection of things which are not in there
Okay, let's go to our spin
Proposition, the spin is up along the axis
What's the not of that?
The not of that is if we measure the spin along the z axis
We get something else other than one
The only other possibility is minus one
So the spin equal minus one along the z axis
Is the NOT statement of the spin is up along the axis
So logic make some sense
But we begin to find very peculiar difference
when we start talking about the operations of combining proposition
to the use of AND and OR
AND and OR are different in quantum mechanics
than they are in classical mechanics
I wanna lay that out
It's so interesting and so rarely explained that's sort of like to explain it
>> in the classical example like the die
>> the universal set is finite in terms of the elements in it
number of states
>> then you jump to quantum mechanics
>> and things like that is called plausible time
>> Is that make a difference?
All the possible of what?
>> All the possible experiments that you could do, not limited
Ya, you are getting at something important which we are going to get to
It's clear that in some sense the number of states of this spin is finite
It's just up or down, if we measure it along the axis
On the other hand it also looks like we can tilt the apparatus in any direction
And prepare the state in any orientation along any direction
So it looks like there is infinite ambiguity in the states of a system
This is what, this is the whole point of trying to understand the state of system
Understand the connection between
the continuously different directions of electron could point in
and in fact any time we measure it along we are getting axes only up or down
But we will come to it
It's a good question, but we will come to it
Okay, let's talk about the calculus of propositions
I gave you two propositions A and B
I can form two combination of them A OR B and A AND B
Let's just see what does that mean in terms of sets
If we have two proposition this one is A this one is B
Then A AND B means the set of states which belong both to A and to B
So it's the intersection of the set A and the set B
called logically the intersection or set theoretically the intersection
It's basically the AND operation
This point is in A and it's in B
Okay, that's straightforward
And given any two propositions, you can always form
And the, the right way to say it, is this is the point of set here
from which the proposition A and B is true
A AND B is true here and it's true no where else
What about these two? These two subsets A and B
A AND B is still a proposition, but it's always false
There is no state for which A AND B is true
Alright, so there are As and Bs that you can put together
I mean, my friend san jade() over here is weight 600 pounds
And my friend uh, let's get another one
There are combinations which A AND B is always false, obviously
Alright, in particular if you take A and NOT A, it's always false
But still, the definition of A and B is the intersection
And it's true for all states in the intersection
OR is a little bit more complicated,
at least there are two versions of OR
There is the exclusive OR or inclusive OR
In the English language when we usually use OR
we usually means the exclusive OR
When we say that, I'm Jewish or I'm Catholic
I ordinary mean that I can't be both, alright that I can't be both
So the usual OR is the exclusive OR, the one you normally think about
But in logic the term OR is the inclusive OR
It means A, it's true if A is true, it's true if B is true,
it's true when both of them are true
It's the inclusive OR , so I can correctly say
I am a physicist and I am a father, that's true
But I can also say I am a physicist OR I am a father
And it's also true, why? Because both of them are true
So that's the inclusive OR
Inclusive OR correspond to the union of two sets
If I have A and I have B,
then the inclusive OR is everything in both sets
Or either sets, anything - not in both sets
Anything in either sets or in both sets
The exclusive OR with correspond to things in one set
but not the other set
The exclusive OR include, we are not always
When I was speak of the OR, I always mean the inclusive OR
So that's AND and OR, what else can we say about it
They are not very much
We are now going to use that concept to try to formulate a set of AND and OR
and statements about a spin
And then ask how would we verify it, how would we verify them
How would we verify them, what does it mean when we verify them
Okay so let's take two proposition A and B
to be sigma z is equal to plus one, and sigma x
This is A and this is B, sigma x is equal to plus one
They are both propositions, we will know how check either one of them
If we want to check sigma A, we will turn our apparatus vertically upward
And we measure the spin, we will check it true or false
If we wanted to find out if B is true of false
We will turn the apparatus on it's side
In classical logic, if there are two propositions
you can form a combination A OR B
Let's start with A OR B, so we will take A OR B
And let's think about checking it's true value
Is it true or is it not?
Alright who design an experiment and try oh,let's circle back the steps
Let's imagine a hidden ghost in the world has previously unknown to us
Unknown to us, has originally oriented the spin upward along the z axis
First we know, we know nothing,
but the ghost in the world has oriented the spin vertically upward
Just, it doesn't matter, but we could start that way
So the spin is upward, and let's check that if A OR B is true
How do we begin? Let's begin by measuring the spin along the z axis
We put our detector or our apparatus in vertical direction
And we measure it, what do we get?
We get plus one, we got plus one
because the ghost in the world has made them to begin with
We don't have to go any further, A or B is true
A or B include the possibility that both A AND B is true
But all requires to be true is that one of them is true
And we've just discovered that A is true
So A or B is definitely true, so let's do the experiments in another way
in order which would not matter if we are doing classical physics
And the reason it doesn't matter when we do classical physics
It's when we do an experiment that has no necessary affect
on the outcome of latter experiments
The experiment is gentle enough
So let's do the experiment on the opposite order
Instead of first finding out wether A is true
Let's first ask if B is true
And then we will come back and ask if A is true
Alright, secretly the spin is pointing up at the z direction
So the ghost knows that, but we don't
So we come along, knowing nothing about the spin
And why should I measure it? Why should I measure A first?
Let's first measure B
Let's first measure the x component of the spin
What do we get?
We get either plus one or minus one
We get plus one or minus one with a fifty percent probability
So there is a fifty percent probability that B is plus one
But if B is not plus one, it doesn't mean A or B is wrong
We still have a chance that when we measure A
It will be plus one
Okay, the problem is in measuring B first time around
We orient, we prepare B along the x axis
Whatever we can, whether it is this way or this way
We have prepared that spin along the x axis
What would that experiment give when we measure along z axis?
Fifty percent probability of being up and fifty percent probability of down
That means we have a 25% probability of finding both
that sigma x was equal to minus one and sigma z is equal to minus one
We have a 50% probability in the first experiment
that sigma x is not equal to one
And then in the next experiment
we have another 50% probability on top of that
That sigma z was not equal to one
We have a net probability of one quarter
that both A and B are false
When we did the experiment in one order
When we do the experiment in the other order
It is certain that A or B is right, right?
Because A is right
So whether it's true in classical physics
That the idea or A and B is symmetrical between A and B
The idea or the OR statement is A or B
If A or B is true, then B or A is true
And we find that in quantum mechanics
The concept of A or B at best can only be defined
in a way that the order should determine A or B
>> the propositions are incompletely specified
>> in the quantum mechanical case,
>> because you have to give order right?
>> It doesn't like the particle has certain spin
>> which said that's right
Ya, that would, that would also say that any attempt to
think about the logics and experiments are different in quantum mechanics
>> in other words you measure A and B and certain
No, no, no, no, no, let's go back
I said the ghost in the world
makes the spin pointing up along the z axis
That's, we don't know that, but that's true
Then if we measure sigma z first
Under the circumstances, we will certainly find that A or B is true
But we measure under the same circumstances
The same degree of lack of presence of knowledge
We measured B first, we find out that there is 25% chance that
A or B, this composite statement here is false
>> So I have a question, the operation A or B result is now going to be
>> a possibility of 25%
Well, not only that, but you have to specify which order you add A and B
So, alright, that's in itself an elementary something new that
the OR statement does not unify the statement that were in symmetrical way
>> Question? I confused when we, the thing we are prepared to it
that doesn't matter, just to simplify the story,
It wouldn't matter
>> but we enter the experiment with new B that's
>> (inaudible) the apparatus on the side
>> and I thought what you are saying is
>> now do this multiple time would get an average
Yeah, but we are not doing it, we are trying to find out
>> but you are saying, what you say is
>> when we do that measurement on the side we are preparing the spin again?
>> and that would say that from then on we should always get plus one
Plus one for sigma x, but then if we go for sigma z
we would get an random answer, measuring one and measuring
>> we are gonna get a random answer for the first inspection?
Think about it, I can't stop the class for
>> Question, if you have a measurement device ()
>> to measure two different particles
Why have you jumped to two particles?
>> I've been wondering the measurement does it spin vectors
What? I don't know
Okay, that was all review, the next thing which I was going to review
But I'm not going to because it take too long, it's vector spaces
I will just remind you real quickly, the vector space are such elements
You can add elements, this is not something you would do with sets
You can add two sets of course to make a bigger set
But there is no natural single element which is the sum of two elements
So the elements of the set, namely the basic individual objects are not
things that you can add and make new elements
The space of state of a quantum system is a linear vector space
and that means given any two states you can add them in some sense
and make another state, that's what we are going to explore
This logic, this peculiar logic, this peculiar distortion of logic
turns out to be the logic of vector spaces
So logic which is embedded into structure and spaces
in a very neat and tidy way
And that's ultimately why vector space is important
Okay, so let's remember the vector of things that you can add
If there are two vectors A and B, you can add them
You can multiply them by complex numbers
Every vector has a dual vector, which is kind of its complex conjugate
If we call this object ket vectors because they are the second half of a bracket
Then the ket of bra vector which are in one to one correspondent
which are for every ket vector there are a bra vector
But it starts as if that it's a complex conjugate
So there are two dual vector spaces
And you can take in the product of a vector
A bra vector and a ket vector
So the bra vector and the ket vector can be combined together
It gives a complex number, the inner product as a complex number
And it satisfy there's equal to the complex conjugate
The complex conjugate of the opposite order
So if you take a complex vector and a complex vector space
You take the inner product interchange the two vectors
Then it's equivalent to it's complex conjugation
That's pretty much what you need to know
That allows you to define given the idea of a inner product
That allows you to define the notion of a length of the vector
We don't usually think of the length of the vector
We usually think of the square of the length of the vector
And the square of the length of the vector
Let's say the letter is A, is the inner product of it's own conjugate
Or it's own dual, usually we say it's the inner product with itself
But that's slightly abuse of terminology
And this is always real
The reason it's always real because if we interchange A and A
We just get back to the same thing
But this tells us the inner product of A and A is it's own complex conjugate
It's own complex conjugate, it's real, it's also positive, that's easy to prove
And it can be thought of the square root of the length of the vector
It's analogous to, closely analogous to a dot product
with a three-vector with itself
If A and B were three-vectors then we wouldn't distinguish the bra and the ket
But we would write that A dot B is the dot product between the two vectors
Analogous to this
And we would also write A dot A was the square of the length of A
The inner product of a vector with itself
can be thought of as square of the length of the vector
And finally there is the notion of orthogonality
Two vectors are orthogonal when their inner product is zero
Same definition for dot product
When the dot product between two vectors is zero
Those vectors are orthogonal
Those are the definition that we need for a vector space
The other definition is the definition of the dimensionality of the vector space
How many dimensions does the vector space have?
And the way to decide that is
by asking the maximum numbers of orthogonal vectors
You can find in the vector space
For ordinary vectors, let's say in two three four five dimensions
this is obvious
In two dimensions I can take a vector, just pick any vector
make a unit vector just by shrinking it's length to unit length
Then I look around and see if we can find another orthogonal vector to it
Yeah, in fact I can find two, one point to this way one point to that way
But that's not a important distinction, we find one other direction
Or one other vector that apart from the numerical multiple
Apart from the numerical multiple
there is one other vector which is orthogonal to it
So there are two mutually,
the maximal number of mutually orthogonal vector you can find is two
If you go to three direction you can find a third one, but no more
If you find a fourth one, you are out of directions
So three-dimensional space has three orthogonal vectors
Four dimensional has four and so forth
And same thing is true for complex vector spaces
We describe the version of complex vector spaces
Which is just column vector, alpha one alpha two alpha three...
And their dual, which is a row vector
Which would make up out of the complex conjugate of the variable
So once we have a vector, we can start looking for vectors orthogonal to it
Vectors which are perpendicular in this sense
Find the other one that look like third one
look for the fourth one, however many you find
You will eventually run out of direction
That's the dimensionality of space
To a special case in which there are only two entries here
It's a two dimensional vectors space
you can only find two mutually orthogonal vectors
You can find many pairs of mutually orthogonal vectors
In real space, they are just these, these, these
Pointing in different directions
But once you find two there won't be any other one
Okay, so we have the idea of mutually orthogonal vectors
Now we have to state what is the connection between the vector space
and the space of possible states of a quantum system
The quantum system that we are gonna deal with
is still very primitive and simple, a single spin
Until we get the hand on that, we won't move to more complicated things
>> Is that in the illustration that
>> the orthogonal vectors have to be perpendicular to each other
That's what orthogonal means
>> so suppose you have a qubit that tilt to a hologram
>> it's still three-dimensional but the system is not perpendicular
Perpendicular and orthogonal are synonymic terms
Perpendicular and orthogonal both mean right angle
You are confused by something but I don't know what it is
Ya, ya, I know you are, but
Perpendicular orthogonal, right angles are, they mean all the same thing
>> I think when you say linearly independent it's orthogonal
>> but if you (inaudible)
That's true, let's not confuse it, this is right
Linearly independent that is different than orthogonal,
orthogonal is linearly independent,
but linearly independent is less strong than orthogonal
These two vectors like that they are linearly independent
But they are not orthogonal ,both orthgonal, okay, let's come back
The state of a quantum system is a postulate forming a vector space
Form a complex vector space
In fact the space of a symble system we are discussing
form a two dimensional vector space
Let's write down some vectors, we know some states
We know that for example that is a state that can be prepared
in which the spin is pointing upward or downward along the z axis
We characterize the state by the experiment that we did together in that state
That experiment as the apparatus vertical upward
and it created a state of the system which either could have been down or up
But let's say it's up
We can label that state in a number of ways
We can call it up, we can call it down
We can call it plus... up and down is the same as plus and minus
We can draw them with an arrow that is up and down
What other ways could we, ah we can write it as sigma z equal to plus one
And sigma z equal to minus one
They all mean the same thing, up down, plus minus
Sigma z equals plus one, sigma z equals minus one
All the same thing, alright?
So there are two states that we know about that can access
Or we can prepare it by turning the apparatus upward along the z axis
Let's give them names, these state of vectors in vector space
according to hypothesis and it can be called, let's say up and down
If this is true the vector space is simple, just two-dimensional vector space
And that means that any vector in that space
can be written as some linear combination of up and down
Another words, every vector in two-dimensional space
can be written in terms of two basic vectors up and down
So enough to write any state whatever, up and down
Okay, so what about those states by tilting our apparatus along the x axis
We get something different; it's not the same thing
It's not up, because up means up along the z axis
It's not down, because down means down along the z axis
And we know they are different,
because we know the result of the experiment
on these two different kinds of states will generally be different
So we can call those states technically (?) left and right
It's up and down, it's right and left
There are two other states, we can draw them this way if you like
It also correspond to sigma x equals one and sigma x equals minus one
And we could label them if you like, label them right and left
Finally we know that if we could turn on apparatus
so the apparatus was pointing along the y axis
We can access to more states, I think we can call those in or out
Into the blackboard and out of the blackboard
So there is in and out, into the blackboard and out of the blackboard
And they correspond to sigma y equals plus or minus one
We could label them in and out
All of the logic that I describe to you and all of the experimental results
As we will see, we will not see it immediately
Took some time to understand all of these
It is all summarized by a few statements
but the first of which is that space of all states
of the simple systems is two-dimensional
has only two independent states which means that these other things
can be written in terms of up and down
So let's go to the general linear combination of up and down
and ask what they mean
Let's take a vector, I guess we can call it a A
which is a form, the coefficient, the complex coefficient alpha one
times up plus another complex
I suppose we should call this alpha up, alpha down times down
The alphas are complex numbers, the complex vector space we multiply
It could be real numbers, but in general they will be complex numbers
Let us suppose we knew what that meant
What kind of state is that, where it came from
Some new beasts, it's not up, it's not down somewhere in between
Next postulate, the next postulate is that if we were to measure up and down
If we were, if somebody prepare us with a electron in this state
And we measure up and down, we will find probability up and down
And those probabilities would be probability for up,
It's the square of the magnitude of these coefficient
And the probability for down is equal to alpha star down and alpha down
Another words, it's basically the square of the coefficient
Or the square of the component of A in the direction up and down
It's alpha,
it's essentially the components of the general vector along the two axis
Up and down
There is something that I failed to tell you
It's also a postulate, there are many many postulates
But you can see they fit together in a neat package
There are probably a few postulates which I'm saying
I bet we can reduce it down to four postulates, four axioms
But rather than try an axiom and applies it
Do a little more informally
What's the relation between up and down?
are they negative to each other?
No, they are orthogonal, now that's a postulate
The basic postulate is that the thing is measurably different
the two states are such you can cleanly tell the difference
between them by experiment
They are orthogonal,
orthogonality literally means they are sufficiently different
That you can, with a single experiment or probably or maybe a few experiment
to tell the difference between them uniquely
I will tell you what it correspond to a set
You might say that two sets are orthogonal if they don't share any elements
This is not a standard terminology, but you might say it anyway
They are orthogonal they do not share any elements
That mean they are distinctively different
There is no chance that an experiment would confuse two of them
Experiment that a nice experiment to distinguish them
will not lead to any ambiguity
The same is true for up and down
There is distinctly different of up and down
If you measure up, you will measure up again and again and again
And the version of that in quantum mechanics
Or the implication of that in quantum mechanics
Or the vectors is the thing that correspond to
physically unambiguously different situation of orthogonal to each other
So up and down, or orthogonal to each other
What if we have a combination of up and down was some coefficient
Then it's the probability of be up and probability to be down
And the probability are given by alpha star alpha up
And alpha star alpha down again, this is a postulate
We will see in a moment what it correspond to
Well, what's the relationship between
the probability for up and probability for down
The answer is if we add them we get one
And therefore alpha star alpha plus beta star beta is equal to one
Any reasonable state of a system which has a total probability one for
All the different things that can happen
should satisfy the sum of the probabilities
or the distinct probabilities should add up to one
So that said, alpha star alpha plus beta, not beta
Alpha up star up, alpha down star alpha down
Did I use beta before? Should equal to one
But that's equivalent to the statement of inner product A with itself
is equal to one
Only to think about it
Prove this
Prove that alpha star alpha summed over up and down
is equal to the inner product of A with itself
It does follow from the postulate
And the assumption that u and d are perpendicular unit vectors
u and d are perpendicular unit vector like that assumption
that is orthogonal to each other
That unit vectors, if they are not unit vectors
you can change them into unit vectors
And then you can prove that the inner product of a vector with itself
is just the sum of the squares of the conjugate times itself
That's a little thing to prove
But what does that say, that says the physical state correspond to
a vector in a vector space with a unit length, a unit vector
A unit standing for the fact that the total probability is one
So states are only equal to vector in a vector space but they are unit vectors
The other term for unit vector is normalized vectors, normalized vectors
Normalized is another word for unit
So all physical states, all states or what you can do
to that electron spin or anything else
Correspond to unit vectors
And given any such unit vectors the probability associate with it are
alpha star alpha up, alpha star alpha down
So that's a bit of information
But wait a minute, what happen to these other vectors right and left?
What happen to right and left?
Right and left seem like different state
But according to the postulate,
right and left must be linearly combination of up and down
It's not too surprising because if you prepare right or left
then measure up or down, you get plus one or minus one
That's all it is, plus one or minus one
So it's not too surprising whatever left or right is
It's somehow a combination of up and down
And that statement is buried in the properties of vectors
So let's look at the state left and also the state right
What do we know about it?
Well, we know that it must be a combination alpha up up plus alpha down down
We can also write that in the form of column vector alpha up and alpha down
Number one,
number two, supposing electron is created pointing along the right direction
The x axis, what do the probability for it to be up and down? Remember?
Half, half, that means alpha up star alpha up must equal to half
And alpha star down alpha down must equal to half
Let's make a guess, let's make a guess, the simplest guess would be to put
one over square root of two and one over square of two here
Alpha up is one over square of two, if alpha up is one over square of two
What is alpha star alpha? One half
This one is also one half
Now we could put, we could put some other things
There is one ambiguity is there
We could put a minus sign here
Or we can put a complex coefficient in front of here
Without changing the magnitude of it
We will come back to that, we will come back to what that means
We will come back to what that ambiguity means
But let's take this as a working hypothesis for what the state right is
That lead us to the state left
What do we know about left?
Well, right or left is physically distinguishable by a single experiment
You can orient your apparatus along the x direction
Measure sigma x, and determine unambiguously whether it correspond to right or left
What does it mean about the vector right and left?
It means they are orthogonal
Orthogonal or physically measurable distinct are the same things
So that tells us that left right should be equal to zero
Incidentally we have assumed that up down is equal to zero
Up down, orthogonal, by symmetrically
it's nothing different between the x axis and z axis,
so if the two vector up and down are orthogonal stands for reason that
two vectors left and right must be orthogonal
here's right, is there a vector orthogonal to it, ya?
There is a vector which is orthogonal to it, what is it?
One over square of two up, minus one over square of two down
Now it's the ambiguous to put the minus sign here or here,
Either way would work
We will find out there is no physical difference between those two possibilities
We will find out later there is no physics, and the overall sign or a vector
So here is one which is orthogonal
How do we check this is orthogonal to that?
Well, let's write the row, here's a column vector describing right
Let's write down the row vector on it,
That's not the column vector, here is the column vector
The column vector describing right is one over square of two
One over square of two, that's these two
What is the row vector describing left
If we want to take the inner product
We want to combine the row vector with the column vector
So the row vector describing this right over here
is one over square root of two minus one over square of two
And to take the inner product between them
You take the product of first coefficient times the coefficient
Plus the product of the second one times the second one
Standard rules, by taking the inner product
between a column vector and a row vector
You match the first component with the first component multiply them,
second component with the second component, multiply them
and go right down to the, to all the components and add them up
okay, so what's the answer?
One half, sorry, one over square root of two
One over square root of two is half minus, one over square of two
This inner product is zero
So we found a second vector which correspond to right and left
A candidate if you like for right and left
And what's more you will notice that this vector also has the property
That the probability for it to be up and down is equal to half for each one
Why? Because the square of this one half,
and the square of the magnitude of this one is one half
So we have a nice symmetrical relationship between left right and up and down
Incidentally it's kind of interesting
Supposing them, where is my eraser?
Alright, it's kind of interesting, I've written right and left in terms of up and down
I could of course to write up and down in terms of right and left
Let's see what we get
If we add these two equations the downs were canceled
And we will just get up
We will get two over square, we will get square two that's two over the square
two times up equals to right plus left
And then divided by square of two
And we will find that down is equal to right minus left over square of two
So you see it's completely reciprocal relationship between them
If we began our experiments with the apparatus along the x direction
We might have started, we might have started with left and right
And come to the conclusion that up and down are combination of left and right
Okay, that leaves in and out, what about in and out?
Is there a third pair of vectors, in and out?
Which stand in the same relationship to right and left and to up and down
As they stand to each other, there is a third combination which has
Which is symmetrically defined
Let's put it up here
We have up and down, and they are orthogonal to each other
We have right and left, right which is equal to one over square of two
We can write it as up plus down, and left
And same thing one over square of two times up minus down
We also have right left equal to zero
More over we have something that we are not going to write
But I will say it anyway
If you start in right and you say what's the probability for up and down?
It's one half
If you start left and you ask the probability for up and down
What happen if you start with up and down
What's the probability for right and left?
Well, it's also one half
We know it's one half from the physics of the situation
But it's also true if we rewrite up and down in terms of right and left
The coefficients are also one over square of two
So they are nicely symmetrical to each other
Alright so that leaves us with the last possibility
Or the last perpendicular direction in and out
Okay so let's try to guess, it's gonna have an up
And it's gonna have plus and down
But it's gonna be some coefficient here
And we don't know what those coefficients are yet
What do we know about the coefficients?
The complex in general, in general they are complex
>> there's not just be, the square would be one half
The square would just, or the magnitude of the square has to be one half
We also know that the coefficient here have to be such
That in and out are perpendicular to each other
And we also should find that if we rewrite in and out
in terms of left and right, the coefficient should also have modulus one half
just by symmetry
Turns out that enough to determine them completely
I'm not gonna prove it that's a homework assignment
but that's nice homework assignment
Let's see what the requirements are
The requirements are that in out equals to zero
That both in or out when written in terms of up or down
Should have coefficients whose magnitude is a half
Square magnitude is a half
When also when written in terms of left and right
The same corresponding coefficients here
Should have magnitude plus or minus a half
That is enough to determine the coefficient in terms of up and down
With a small ambiguity which is not interesting
I will tell you later what that ambiguity is
There's no physics in it
First of all is the overall sign of the vector hat has no physics
We will see and find out
Alright what is the solution? The solution is the one here
And the i here, with a square root of two you have to put
one over square of two, and one over square of two
And out is the same thing, up, minus i over square of two, down
Let's write them in terms of column and row vectors
>> so that will be the i over square of two on the in vector?
Well i one yeah, is that what you are asking?
Actually I had it right, it was one times i
We can write these in terms of column vectors
Let's write the various column vectors, up, what would you write for up?
Well, we can write one zero, up is just up with no down component
Down is just zero one, a one in the down place and a zero in the up place
What about right? It's equal to one over square root of two
One over square root of two
Left, that's equal to one over square root of two
minus one over square root of two
Now let's put in, in is one over square root of two,
i over square root of two and right, sorry
Out is equal to one over square root of two minus i over square root of two
First question, is this orthogonal to this? How do we check?
We take this times the complex conjugate of this
And take this times the complex conjugate of this
That's the rule of caluculating inner product
We could constructing the row vector, we don't need to
No let's, let's, let's, we don't need to
Remember the row vector has complex conjugate entries
But it's easy enough to do the inner product
The inner product is the sum of the product of the entries
times their complex conjugate
Alright so one of these has to be the complex conjugate
What's the product of these two complex conjugates?
One half, it's just one half
So this one times this gives you a one half
And how about this times the complex conjugate of this?
Minus one half, minus one half
Minus sign over two, what is the complex conjugate of i over square root of two
Minus sign over square root of two,
so we have to multiply minus sign over square root of two
times another minus sign over the square root of two
which gives us minus a half, i times i is minus one
So that gives us minus a half, if we add them up we get zero
So yes, these two are orthogonal to each other
The magnitude of the coefficients here
the square of the magnitude of the coefficient here is equal to a half
which proves the in states or the out state
the probability of being up and down is one half
How about the probability of being left or right?
How might you figure that out?
Say it again?
Definition of i is the square root of minus one
So i times i is always minus one
i is not, oh sorry, this is
This i is not in
Okay, I and Out, Right and Left, Up and that's the way it is, Down
And go back through out all the pages and change it
Actually we can could have change it more easily, just change this i to capital I
But that would be, that would be bad form
>> Is there anything about this coordinate system
>> that implying a left or right hand coordinate system?
Very very good question and the answer is yes
But we will come to it, yes that's a very very good question
What is this in here is telling us that it's a right hand coordinate system
That or a left hand coordinate system
And I didn't want to go there yet, but we will come to it
We will come to it when we explore the Pauli matrices
For the moment, we just, we are doing, we are sort of guessing away
Bumbling through, trying to find the right vectors
to describe the various states of the system
Okay, this is my proposal if you like
My best guess for the moment for what the states up down
Those are basic, we start with those, in terms of those right and left R
and not in and out R
Now what you could do,
we saw that you could rewrite that up and down in terms of left and right
I've shown you how to do that
And that means you could write i and o in terms of left and right
You could check what the coefficients are
I hesitate to do it because I'm sure of bumble it
In the other hand I tended to do it because I'm not sure to get it right
I will take one shot at it, one shot and if it doesn't work out
Okay, up is left plus right, down is left minus right
With a square root of two
So let's see if we can figure out what in is first
Let's just do in, in is one over square root of two times up
What did I say up was? Up I said was left plus
is left plus right, left plus right
But with a one over square root of two
That gives me one half
It's left over two, plus right over two, that's scary
And then plus i over square root of two times down
Anybody remember what down was?
Left minus right over here, let's
That will give me left, right over another square root of two
minus left over another square root of two
So the whole thing look like
>>Is that two one halves,
>>No, the second term, no, let's go back, right there
>>You get a half and then you got a two
And this could just be one half, the square of two right
Did I have it right?
Okay so what do we get, we get the coefficient times the left
So here we are, I is equal to one half, one minus i over two
Was that right? One minus i over two times left plus
I think it's one plus i over two times right
>>I think you would write O instead of I?
Here? I think we are doing I
But I'm not sure, doesn't matter
Uh, I think we were doing this one
Up is left plus right, and down is left minus right
The same i
Okay, now, what's the magnitude of the two coefficients here?
Then times it's complex conjugate
Let's check, I don't see any square root of two in these things,
Do you see any square root of two here?
You might have expected some square root of two huh?
Nevertheless, I maintain you take this kind of complex conjugate
I hope that was true
I maintain that if you take this kind of complex conjugate
You will get one half, let's check it
It's one minus i, times one plus i over, two times two is four
One minus i plus one plus i, where is the law?
It's two, it's two over four, which equal to one half
Another word, this coefficient here,
although it does not contain any explicit square root of two
It times it's complex conjugate is equal to one over two
So the magnitude of this complex number here
is one over the square root of two
It's written in the form that you don't see any explicit one over square root of two
But the magnitude of this one over square root of two
And so is the magnitude of this
The implication is that if you started in the state I, into the blackboard
And instead of measuring up or down
You measure left or right, the probability would be a half, alright?
So we found three mutually relate, not, orthogonal to each other
Up and down is not orthogonal to left and right
They are orthogonal to each other
But they are not orthogonal in the vertical direction
But each one, if expanded in any of the others
would have coefficient whose magnitude was one over the square root of two
So they are symmetrically related in that sense
And what does it means?
In effect, if you start with anyone one of them
And measure the other component, if you start with up or down
And measure sigma x and sigma y, you will get probability a half
No matter what you start with, any one of these three combination
Any one of these six combination and measure a perpendicular combination
you always get probability plus or minus a half
Now I've put in here some postulates about what probabilities are
without telling you, but I think we were coming along pretty well
We have some mathematics here which is telling us
That these three collections, or pairs of vectors
are nicely symmetrically related to each other
That's the most important fact, yes,
You know we don't have to, this is orthogonal to this
Oh sorry, three bases, three bases at angles with respect to each other
That's a good question, the question is could we find, excellent question
Could we find another double
Let's call it big and little, no, we are already used the l
Uh, fat and skinny, fat and skinny
Can we find another pair such that fact is orthogonal to skinny
And the inner product that's what it actually came down to
Or that the expansion coefficients of each one in terms of the other kind of bases
are always equal to one over square root of two
or always one half in magnitude?
The answer is no, there is no third, there is no fourth combination
that's in the same relationship, that's not obvious, that's not obvious
It is a fact that we live in a three-dimensional world
It's exactly the fact that we live in a three-dimensional world right?
It's exactly the fact that the statement of
three-dimension of space can be represented
in two-dimensional, in two-dimensional vector space terms
Alright let me tell you something else, which is true
If I give you a column vector, let's say a column vector
Alpha one, alpha two
Or it's just the coefficient of the expansion alpha up or alpha down
If you like
The question is how much freedom is there in the alphas
such that it doesn't change the physical nature of the state? How much freedom?
Does every combination of alpha up and alpha down
correspond to a different state?
The answer is no
First of all, the total probability has to add up to one
So that's one constraint right there
that alpha up star alpha up plus alpha down star alpha down is equal to one
That's another fact that we have not got to yet
But we will find that every physically observable quantity
always associate with a state
Always involve an alpha times the complex conjugate alpha
You will find that, it's, we won't put it in
It will emerge just as the consequences of the postulate
But what it says is that if you multiply both of the alphas here
By the same phase factor, does anybody know what are the phase factors?
The phase factor was a complex number of the form e to the i theta
of unit length, doesn't change the magnitude of either coefficient here
That if we multiply every entries by the same phase factor
It doesn't affect anything, that means that
if I just give you two complex numbers here
there are two redundant piece of information
that really don't have anything to do with physical character of the states
First is the over all magnitude,
because the over all magnitude should always be such that
that sum of these square roots add up to one
So that means one core constraint if you like, and the redundancy
The redundancy is that if you multiply both entries by the same phase factor here
It also doesn't change the states
So then you could ask,
how many independent variables are there which characterize the state of a system?
Of this system, how many of them are there?
Well, let's count, there are two independent variables
If we don't worry about either of this constrain over here
How many things does it take to characterize two complex numbers?
Four, four real numbers, right?
But now, one of them doesn't count, because we have to satisfy the constrain
That the total length of this must be equal to one
One of them doesn't count, but also the another one doesn't could because
The overall phase if we are to multiply everything by the same phase factor
Here it also doesn't count, doesn't change the nature of the states
So two of those four parameters are irrelevant
to the physical character of the states
How many of that leave over? Two
Two real numbers
How many numbers does it take to characterize the direction of a unit vector?
Two
What do they call? Longitude and latitude or something like that
Just the direction of the vector can be characterized by the two angles
These two pairs of number are the same
The fact that it takes two real parameters
to describe a two-component vector like this
is closely related to the fact
it takes two real angles to describe the direction of a three-vector
in ordinary three-dimensional space
If we would have added more components here, it would be more complicated
Yes there is a deep connection between the fact that
Very deep connection between the facts that
we only find three independent combination of this
Three independent combinations, and the fat and skinny
We can't find fat and skinny basically they won't be there
Not without increasing the dimensionality of the vector space
That's in fact very deeply connected with three-dimensional space
Space was nine dimensional or something like that
We would not be able to represent
the direction of a little arrow in it quantum mechanically
Like two component vectors
We will need more components
>> it seems like just physically you would take three because
>> two would specify the collection but you could say
>> whether it is plus one or minus one
No no no, the plus one or minus one
>> inherited from the space right here
Yeah
>> How does it stay alive if you have three complex numbers in vector space
You mean if you want to study some higher dimensinoal space?
Oh god we have to figure it out that how many questions
and how many directions and how many parameters are there to
That's more complicated, that we are not gonna try
I got to tell you I got really scared when I realize
we won't get any square root of two by doing this
>>this map is based on three space? (inaudible)
Yes it is, all of what you said is true
>> If you say that there is nine dimensions,
>> would this experiment still agrees?
It would be a version of it, It would be a version of it,
It would be more complicated and
you couldn't describe the spin of a particle by just by two components like this
It will take more components
>> What would be the apparatus of it?
Spinner theory, similar things, similar things
Don't try to, look, this is enough for now
Understanding this, if we run to four dimensional space like this
We would need four component object but ...
The three to four would be
>> You said the states which was corresponded to
>> what about the (inaudible)
But of course if you add two unit vectors you can get a none unit vector, you can
But then, the rule of the state of the system are divided through
divided through by a overall factor until it's normalized
They have a same significance as
probability distribution which don't summed up to one
You can always go back and say somehow somewhere along the line
I got some answers for probabilities which add up to something greater than one
I will just divide through by
tell the probabilities to find the normalized probabilitie distributions
So in intermediate steps of calculation might well be
presents of vectors which are not normalized
But at the end of the day, the states of the systems are normalized vectors
Normalized vectors, and with no memories of of their overall phases is
There is a mathematical term for that
Questions?
I've gone through a lot of stuffs
We will make it more precise
And the next time when we discuss observables
In particular when we discuss what the mathematical nature
of these sigma x and sigma y and the sigma z-s are
For the moment we just specify them sort of by experiment
So you hold your apparatus this way and measure something call sigma x
And you hold it that way and measure something call sigma y
And we use some symmetries namely
the equivalence of different directions of space
to guide us into finding expressions for the various physical vectors
describing different orientation of the spins
But we haven't been very rigorous about it
It's been no, I've made no pretense of really
a mathematical clear theorization of these things
Sort of see to the plan and guessing to a logic stance
Next time we will make some rigorous postulates
about what these things really means
And their relationship, these things and these things
and what the relationship between them is
The vectors and the things that you measure, these are the states
But these are the things you measure about
And the question is what is the connection between them
Okay, any more question about this?
>> About these lectures like the sequence on the web
I imagine they are, but I don't remember,
there is not only one way to think about quantum mechanics, so I bet they are
And you know if you sitting through this for the third time that's your problem
Believe me, I'm sitting through it for the
>> was that the phase factor that we could ignore?
The answer is yes, I think so
>> was that the phase factor we are gonna be doing anything?
Well, mostly we would be saying, look, it doesn't matter, it doesn't matter
The, okay, let's talk about the mathematics of ignoring something
Ya, that's right
You know that's true, let's talk about the mathematics and ignoring things from
Alright the point is zero dimension right?
A circle is one dimensional, there is one parameter and an angle on it
But supposing I tell you there is no significance
to tell you where you are on that circle
There is no significance whatever or points on that circle
equivalent to every other point
And you might say, well, for all interesting questions
A circle is just a point
If you can ignore where you are on the circle
There is only one point on the circle
You are either on the circle, if you are on the circle
The circle is one point
You can say the same thing about
That's another example, what's the other example?
No, let's take this example
If you have, what is that complex number?
A complex number is a point on the plane
But for some reason the angle where you are on the plane doesn't matter
The only thing that's interesting is the distance
But now supposing you have two complex numbers
And all I tell you is that if you have two complex numbers
The thing which doesn't matter is the sum of their phases
The sum of their phases, the sum of their angles
Then there is still one angle left over which maybe important
The difference of the angles
So I have two complex numbers
And I tell you, for reason that I haven't specify yet
That the overall phase which can be thought of the sum of the phase angle
If the sum of the phase angle for whatever the reason
plays no role in the physics of the situation
There is still the difference of the angle there
That's exactly what the case is, the sum of the angle
You know the complex numbers is that going to these entries here
is of no physical significance
We counted up four real parameters for two complex numbers
The overall magnitudes of it doesn't count because we divide that out
That removes one of them
And then the sum of the angle doesn't count for whatever reasons
That removes the other one that leaves you with two real numbers
And that's in correspondence with the two real number it takes
to pick the direction in space
A lot of subtlety, but nothing really difficult
The mathematic is really easy
The mathematic for quantum mechanics is easier
than the mathematic for classical physics
Two by two matrices are very simple
Mathematic is easier, it's unfamiliar
>> there's something that always been lately unsettling
>> when we get to the heart of the idea of up and down
>> are along a single axis, one pointing this way one pointing that way
>> Why they would be orthogonal now?
Orthogonal doesn't mean perpendicular in three-dimensional space
It means physically distinguishable
It means unambiguously distinguishable
Left and right are not distinctly distinguishable uniquely from up and down
Why? Because if you have a thing oriented along left and you measure up and down
You might get up
>> So you think of two orthogonal axis being two independent variables
>> you could vary independantly?
Yes, that's right, you could vary independently the probability of up and down
Of course they have to add up to one, alright?
They have to add up to one,
but ignoring the question of whether they add up to one
You have the freedom to independently vary the coefficient in terms of u
The coefficient in term of the d
And in fact they have to add up to one, it is a fact
Don't confuse orthogonality in space of states
with orthogonality in three-dimensional space
The analog idea in phase space or in configuration space of classical system
Orthogonality of two probability distribution
Let's think of, suppose you have phase space
Or configuration space of some classical system, the phase space
And I give you a probability distribution
A simple probability distribution might be zero everywhere except for some patch
Where the probability is uniform
Okay, the analog of orthogonality between two distinct probability distribution
is that they don't overlap, they are non-overlapping
There is no ambiguity
That's the analog of orthogonality
Up and down don't relap
If you are up, not down, if you are down, not up
Now if you think about, there is a situation
in which orthogonality is the same in space and in the space of states
It's the polarization of the photons
Polarization of photons is a little bit different
We will get to it because it's a little more complicated
A little better if we have different word for perpendicularity in space
Or orthogonality in space of state, different concepts
I mean, it's very much what's going on here that
Being oriented along right, can I do an experiment
which can distinguish between a spin pointing up and a spin pointing down?
Yes, you can bring your apparatus over to it, detect it
If it's up, it will point one, if it's down, it will point minus one
It will give you a minus one
Can you use that apparatus to tell you uniquely the difference
between a spin pointing in the x axis or the spin pointing along the z axis?
What would you do to tell the difference?
What would you measure?
No matter what you measure, it's not gonna uniquely tell you the difference
If you measure sigma z, you will get plus one,
but it doesn't tell you anything about sigma x
It doesn't, you could have gotten sigma z equals to plus one because
it was pointing along the z axis and you got a certainty one
Or it was pointing along the x axis with a probability of a half of pointing up
There is no way to tell
There is no way to tell by a single, well-defined experiment
Where the spin was pointing, let's say, up, or out
>>What if you measure the photon can tell you of that?
With one experiment of photon either will it come on and off
From that you can not tell uniquely
No you can not tell
That's exactly the same as measuring the spin
If you get up in your measurement
If does not tell you whether it's initially up
Or was initially side way with a probability half up
There is no unique single experiment you can do to distinguish this from this
There is a experiment you can do to distinguish this from this
That's what makes up and down orthogonal
But down and left not orthogonal
They overlapped, they overlapped
And in fact the probability that if you were in left
That you measure down when you measure sigma z
That's a measure of the overlap between them
They are overlapped which means in technical language they are not orthogonal
>> You originally said you didn't know it was perpendicular to upper z,
>>and we measured that out
What we are trying to do is confirm the proposition which has been up
Or the z component of the spin is up or the x component of the spin is up
That's a single proposition, it's not two proposition
It's been up, or it's been up along z, or it's up along x
It's a single proposition if the first detection
measured the spin up along the z axis, we are finished
And since we set up before hand, we know in that case we would did
At the right hand side
Okay
>> Would it be right to summarize that propositions are not commutative?
Uh, yeah, propositions technically correspond to projection operators
Projection operators are not commutative
It would be proper to summarize that, it's part of the point you know
Depends on which order you
>> So you caution us of trying to visualize
>> So is the sigma along the z axis or on x axis
>> Isn't that a visualization?
It is, it is, it is, it is ,it is
Well ,you know, yeah, you know it is , it is a visualization
Do keep in mind though this interesting fact that on the average
The spins, if you measure many of them, many many of them,
The average value do behave like a component of a little vector
In particular if you take a large number of these things
And you make sure if they all pointing upward
And then you measure some oblique component of them
with your apparatus being tilted, then the average that you will get
for the oblique component would just be the projection of upright vector
on to the oblique direction
And exactly as if you are measuring the component of a vector
So the upshot is, if you have a large number of them
In many cases you can visualize with classical physics, after all
Classical physics is still to large extend the approximation of systems
which consists of many many parts which all behave
simultaneously the same way
>> More question, is there any properties which describe this unique
>>relationship between that (inaudible)
well, I suppose, I suppose there is
You better be more specific then that
Eigen invariants does have to do with phase factor here
Well it does have to do with them
But it does have to do with them
But we can't get into that right now
>> Things which get me confused about
>> calling the measurement of the (inaudible), in classical sense that
>> but it's not like, you can't really say what value before we do the measure
>> we can only say what it is after you do the experiment
but then, once we measure it, we can measure it again
And the same thing again, that will be consistency
>>Put it in a certain state that we will
>> If we get the same exact preparation over and over again
>> it will give you a distribution
That's right, you can't always think that a system has a property
It's just your job to find out what it is
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu