stanford university
Alright, well
A mathematical interlude we'll begin with
Mathematical interludes again about linear algebra about vector spaces
but the idea of operators
But before we do I want to let it before we get operators
I want say a few more things about vectors
A few more bits about the mathematics of vectors
Most of these bits have to do not so much
with deep mathematics as with good notation
Good notation is worth than offer a lot
when you can just manipulate symbols in ways
uh... that are sort of prearranged
and uh, do it easily and comfortably
there's an enormous benefit in that
when doing abstract mathematics certainly
but also the abstractions a mathematical abstractions of physics
The abstractions we are going to talk about
were largely due to Dirac, Paul Dirac
who really was the one
who saw into the way quantum mechanics really fits together
So let's talk about that
We have a space of states, the space of states
which will come back to is as I said a linear vector space
meaning to say you can multiply states by numbers
to get new states is abstract vectors
abstract vectors
maybe I uh, threw maybe I threw too much in
when I say space of states, just the abstract vectors
you can multiply them by numbers in our case complex numbers
and you can add them
and there are two kinds of vectors, they are bra vectors and ket vectors
They are roughly speaking related by complex conjugation
uh, and a vector space has a dimensionality
The dimensionality is the maximum number of orthogonal vectors
that you can find in that space
And once you know what the dimension of spaces is
you can look for a basis of vectors
The basis of vectors is a mutually orthogonal collection of normalized
get the terminology down
orthonormal basis
Ortho means that they are all orthogonal to each other
normal means normalized
And normalized simply means that the vectors are of unit length
A collection of them that is maximal
in other words that you can't find any more
because there are no more directions left
That defines a basis and the number of them is equal to the
uh, the dimensionality of space
Given such a basis, you can make
you can write any vector in the space as some kind of sum
over those basis vectors
So we can write for any vector A,
that is equal to sum
over i, i here stands for the basis vectors
Of course a basis is not a unique thing
just as there are many sets of mutually orthogonal vectors
in three-dimensional space
There are many sets of mutually orthogonal vectors
in an abstract vector space, but we pick one
We pick a set, set and we pick that set and we label i
we can write any vector
as a sum alpha of i exactly these alphas which uh,
refer a moment to go
Alpha of i is a set of complex numbers is a sort of complex coefficients
times the ith basis vector
The ith base vector uh
are labeling i
This is a ket representation
But now all we can do with this
is we can take the inner product with it
I want to try to calculate these alphas of i's
in terms of some quantities involving the vectors themselves
Alright so what we do
is we take the inner product of both sides of the equation
with the basis vector j, the ket vector j
On the left hand side we get the inner product
of the vector A which is the thing we're trying to express
and that's equal to the sum over i,
alphas of i, times the inner product of the vector j
with the vector i
But the inner product of vector j with this vector i
is either one or zero
It's one if i and j are the same vector
and zero otherwise
Why? Because they are orthogonal if i is not equal to j
and then normalized
namely of unit length if i does equal j
So this bracket over here, this product bras and kets
is just a Kronecker symbol delta j k
sorry, delta j i
zero or one
and when you do sum
and it just picks out one and only one contribution
the contribution in which i is equal to j
so on the right hand side, you just get alpha j
No sum
Sum is collapsed to a one term
and that's now equal to j A
So what we learned?
we've learned that the coefficient here
in the expansion of any vectors is
just the inner product of the jth vector
with  the target vector, the vector we're trying to describe
uh, the fact that I wrote a j there is irrelevant
It could also be alpha i
It doesn't matter which i or which j
ith coefficient is in the product
now I can use that
to rewrite the sum up here
I now know what the alphas of i are
for these guys over here
so let's rewrite this
sum over i
I'm going to start with alpha i
sorry with i
and then write alphas of i
I'm going to write alphas of i next to it over here
in the opposite order
That's, that's allowed
nothing uh... or nothing
non commuted at this stage
now I want to write alphas of i
so I write i A
that's a basic formula, that any vector
can be rewritten in terms of its
coefficient or in terms of its inner product of the basis vectors
times the basis vectors themselves, summed over i
It's kind of a pretty formula
and it comes back over and over again
what it says is whenever you see this summation
of i times i in that form
you can sort of throw it away
It's just A equals A
But it's an expression for a vector in terms of its components
I saw that so one simple fact
the same thing is true for bra vectors
exactly the same thing is true for bra vectors
and you would write it in the following form
a bra vector, there's also a sum over i
of the inner product of bra vector with the basis vectors
times the basis bra vectors
The basis bra vectors are just complex conjugates
if you like their basic basis, ket vectors
both of these equations are true
and we're gonna find out that they were enormously useful
they were enormously useful
and powerful
even though they were very very simple
all right now we come to the notion of linear operators
states in quantum mechanics are vectors
We thought a little bit about how that works
in the case of a single spin
observables, observables mean the things that we measure
the things that we measure
the objects that we measured the quantity that we measure
the observables are related to linear operators
in the space
So what is a linear operator
and it'll take us the rest of the evening
to understand in the detail what has to do with the observables
So put that out of your head for the moment
we just doing a mathematical interlude now
what is the notion of a linear operator
A linear operator is a process if you like
which you apply to vectors
Somebody or other I can't remember
who might've been John Wheeler
likes to describe these things as machines
You would say a linear operator
is a machine with two little ports in it
into one port you put in an input vector
and then you turn the wheel and outcomes an output vector
So it's a thing which acts on an input vector
to give an output vector
so let's uh... call M a linear operator
Linear will come to, so far we're just talking about operator
a machine in goes one in outcomes another one
and we'll talk about what means to be linear in a minute
so M is some operator and that means
that given any vector when M acts on it
It's simply gives another vector, unique
Given any A, it gives a unique B
That does not mean
the converse may not be converse
opposite may not be the true, may not be
Uh, that given a B on this side
that there's only one unique A
that gives rise to that B
But it is true that M applies to any vector A
gives an unique reflection of A
which is the process M acting on A
Now what does it mean for M to be a linear operator
Well, first of all, M can act on Z times A
With Z times A is a vector
That's right, that's right
M can act on Z times A
Z times A is itself a vector
Because you're allowed to multiply vectors
by complex numbers
Z is a complex number
The rule about linear operators is
if they apply on constants times vector
they just give back the constant
times what they would have given on A
I thought it just means that Z, a complex number
a complex number can be brought through M
M acting on twice A gives twice
what M would give on A
M acting on three times A gives three times
what M gives on A
M acting on i times on A, a complex number, i
just gives i times M would give on A
That's the first rule about linearity
And the second rule about linearity is
that if M acts on the sum of two vectors, A plus B
then what you get is just the sum
of what the machine spit out for A
and what the machine spit out for B
What the machine spits out when you put in A plus B
is just the sum of what comes out
M times A plus M times B
and that's it, that's the notion of a linear operator
No more to it than that
At least that's the full set of rules about linear operators
Now that's even more can be concrete about them
You're going to manipulate with them
Let's suppose that M times A equals B
Here we reduce B as a piece of the input
But now B is the output
just letters I can use in any way I want
M times A equals B
I am interested in the component of B along the axis i
but that I mean
these objects over here the alphas
They are the components of the vector A
along the various basis vector directions
So alphas of i's of, the components of the vectors
and I'm interested in the components
of the output vector
I would like to know in a concrete way
what are the components of B
To find out, I just project them onto the direction i
A M i
All I've done is in both sides of the equation project to
project this, put the inner product with the vector i
This by definition is beta i
Another words if I were to expand B
in the same way I expanded A
I would use the coefficient beta i
That's what we learned up on the top board
This is beta i
How about here?
What can I do with this rewrite things in terms of components
I want to rewrite everything in terms of components
Actually become Eric Mearre? Operations that you can do
Well, here is where we use this trick
Whenever you see a vector A, you can substitute for it
A sum
Let's do that right in here
where A is substituted i
I haven't substituted it yet
Now, the summation variables, not i in this case
i have used as the external non summation variable here
So let's sum over j
It doesn't matter what we call the summation variable
j, A
I've stuck in for A, the sum over components
times the jth vector
times the jth basis vector
But now, A times j goes to the top again
That's just alpha j
So we now have a formula
completely in terms of components
This is i M j
I'll get to this in a minute but it's a number
Inner products are numbers
M times j is a vector
and you can take it to the inner product to the i
and vectors
ket vectors have inner products with basis vectors
times j A, or times alpha j
That's equal to beta i
So all we have to do is give this object a name
What is this object?
just uh... tell you again
You have some operator with abstract entity
You have a collection of basis vectors
You apply the abstract operator to the vector j
and take its  inner product with i
and call this thing m i j
It's a number
and maybe a complex number
But it's a number
Another words, it's possible to characterize linear operators
by what we called them matrix elements
These are called matrix elements of the linear operator M
This times alpha js, summed over j
I left out the sum over j here
Let's put back in
sum over j is equal to beta i
If somebody hands you the collection of them i js
and somebody hands you a vector in the form of its components
you can then start sweeping through it
and calculating what the components of the output are
in terms of the input
m i j is a matrix
It has two indices
It's a square matrix
If the dimensionality of the spaces n
then m is an n way
m is an n by n matrix, the square matrix
It's a square matrix
Alpha can be regarded as a column
and the output is also a column
It's a column because A was a ket vector
and B was a ket vector
I saw another way to write the same thing
This is one way to write
M times A equals B
Well here's one way to write it
Abstract is another way to write it as a concrete sum
and the third ways to recognize that
this is just the multiplication of a matrix
times a column vector
You're writing the matrix M
by displaying all of its components
m one one, m one two, m one three, dot dot dot
m two one, m two two, dot dot dot
This is just an array that exhibits
the matrix elements will not learn the quality
the matrix elements of m
times the column vector A
alpha one alpha two dot dot dot, alpha N
and what is the rule this this of course is supposed to result
an output, which is beta one beta two, dot dot dot, beta N
What's the rule that's implied by this equation over here?
It's very simple
If you want, the first entry over here
You take the first role
and you take its inner product with a column here
and m, not the inner product
you can called it the inner product
m one one alpha one
plus m one two alpha two
plus m one three alpha three
right down to the bottom
That's exactly this formula, m one two
Sorry m one one alpha one plus m one two alpha two
and so forth
is exactly the standard rule
for multiplying a matrix by a column vector
So now we have a third way
to represent the action of a matrix on a vector
This is less abstract
It's concrete if you know the matrix elements
you know exactly what to do with them
The only thing about it is it does depend on
a particular choice of your basis vectors
The specifics of the matrix elements here
and the column vector will depend on your choice of
Once you pick a basis, you stick with it
But you could have chosen a different basis
in which case these components would have been different
The matrix elements would have been different
After all the matrix elements are themselves
related to the basis vectors
and so you lose something and you gain something
by going to a matrix type of presentation
What you lose is the geometric idea of a relationship
between two vectors
That's independent of the basis choice
What you gain is
a computational actual mechanical algorithm
for producing, for the machine itself
Here is the machine
The machine is a matrix
and what it does is a grinning through
m one one alpha one blah blah blah blah
That goes to the next row does the thing again
goes to the next row, does the thing again
and just spits out the uh, final answer
These things of course also true for ordinary vectors
in three-dimensional space
They are not specific uh,
We tend not to use them
as much as three dimensional ordinary vectors
But they're quite, uh, essential in quantum mechanics
Yes?
Student: It's a little getting ahead
Student: could be choice of basis that you make a different to
Student: whether or not you can see the solution to a problem?
Well, precisely you asked whether you can make a difference
to the way you see through a problem
Certainly a wrong choice of basis
can leave you completely confused
I think what you really meant is
can different choices of basis lead to
different physical answers
and that had better not be
Then you're doing something wrong
Student: yeah, smart, (mumble)
Yeah yeah it's often the case that uh
that a convenient choice a basis will
make your computations especially simple
at a bad choice a basis might make them horribly complicated
That's true but uh
but at the end of the day
the answers should not depend on it
the result of experiment
Okay so now we have, we have the idea of a linear operator
Operating on several different versions of it
Student: Question?
Yeah
Student: Is that general, it seems that
Student: within a definite operator that gives you a ket from bra vector
No, no, no
Linear vector act on ket vector to give ket vectors
Student: That's not the complex conjugation, not allowed
That's right
Complex, very good, let's, yeah, uh
The simplest kind of linear operators
is just multiplication by a complex number
I'll multiply A by a complex number and get another vector
Basically the same vector
but twice as long or something
That is a linear operator
You might ask whether complex conjugation is a linear operator
I take, I take the components of a vector
and replace them by their complex conjugates
The answer is no, is not
Uh, and you can check the definitions
multiplying the components of a vector,
or not multiplying by complex conjugating is not
What it does do is it takes a vector
and it's a different kind of machine complex conjugation
It's a machine which takes a bra vector to a ket vector
or ket vector to a bra vector
and that's a,
strictly it's called anti-linear operator
It's not anti-linear, it's just it's not the opposite of linear
It's just a word
Well, the reason to worry
the reason to call it anti-linear is
because the process of complex conjugation
is in some deep way related to anti particles
But we're not there yet
Yeah, all right, now let's talk, let's talk about ket vector
sorry bra vectors
So far we have defined a linear operator
to act only on ket vectors
But every linear operator can also be given a definition
We need a definition of course we haven't found it yet
We need a definition
But there is also a definition of any given linear operator
acting on a bra vector
Okay, let's see if we can concoct a definition
and then we'll stick with that definition
What might be the rules?
But the action on that same linear operator
when it acts on a bra vector
First of all, the standard notation
It's very very good to keep track of notation
and to use the same notation of rules
Now we need, but keeps things in order
When you act on a bra vector
put the corresponding operator on the right side of it
Alright it gives something
Take that something and take its inner product
The bracket around indicate
that M acting on A is itself an entities
and now let's take its inner product with another vector B
Well, if I removed the bracket here
I would have a symbol
which would look like this
A M B, and I really wouldn't know
if I am supposed to do is act with M on B
and then take the inner product with A
or act with M on A and then take the inner product with B
The answer is with the standard definition
of how linear operators act to the left on bra vectors
It doesn't matter
In another words, we define the action of an M on A to the left
such that and I will show you we can always do this
such that it doesn't matter
which way we do it
A M B is the same as A M B
uh, that you could remove the brackets
Ok, let's see that we can do this
In order to say it, let's start with the definition this way
Let's start with definition this way
Ok, so with definition this way
now I'm going to use that trick up on the top
When you write a vector by inserting
This is a name for this operation here
It's called inserting a complete set of states
complete simply means it's a basis
It did nothing
It took A, and rewrote A
but rewrote A in terms of its components
so let's do that over, on B over here
We can do the same thing over here
We write this is equal to B, j, j
Summed over j
I am not going to write the summations signs
maybe I'll put them at the end out here
Summation i and j
So it's the same vector with B
Then put M there
bracket around it, put M there
and I'll do exactly the same thing on the ket vector
Remember the ket vector can also be expanded
in the same way
So here we go, A, i, i
What we see here? We see, this is alpha star i
Why that I put the star there?
Because the bra vectors are complex conjugates
alphas of i is an M i j
i, inner product of i and times j
and then there is beta j
That's all we have here
This is summed on i and j
M with i on the left and j on the right that's a M i j
j beta, alpha i
and you can see from the way
that we've written this that it doesn't matter
if I first sum over j
and think of M is acting on the ket vector beta
or I sum over i
and think of M as first acting to the left on the alpha
you get the same answer
It's just a double sum of i and j
You have the same answer
and so if you define
Another words, you can define M in such a way
that it doesn't matter which order or the way you put the brackets
That easies your life
You don't have to remember whether you meant
M acts on B and then you take an inner product with A
or M acts on A and you take the inner product with B
Same thing
Ok, but there is a something, there is, let's
It's the power of a nice notation
But now let's consider another question
Supposing that a linear operator M on A gives B
Incidentally amusing A and B
all over the place in different ways
There was just two vectors
Here, A is the input vector, B is the output vector
So let's suppose that the machine M
when you stick A into it, out spits B
We could ask what's the corresponding bra vector relationship
Is there a linear operator which has the property
that wanted acts on
I'm not going to call it M yet
It's not M
Let's call it scripting M
Is there for every M which acts on A to give B
Is there corresponding scripting M
which acts on the corresponding bra vector B
to give the corresponding bra vector over here
Well, yes, there is
We are going to figure out
how to figure out what it is soon enough
But it is not the original M
One example would be what if
M was just multiplication by a complex number
then what is scripting M B
Multiplication by the complex conjugate number
So whatever M is
It's not necessarily the same as scripting M
and it would be the same as scripting M?
If it was multiplication by a real number
but it was multiplication by a complex number
then in general
generally it will not give the same relationship
We would normally just put a complex conjugate sign
if we want to operate in the other direction
Alright the notation that is standard,
this to say that the operator which one acting to the left
is the reflection if you like
it's the dual of the operator M acting to the right
does not called M
It is called M dagger
The dagger is an operator version of complex conjugation
It's an operator version of complex conjugation
or matrix version of complex conjugation
It's called Hermitian conjugation about
We'll get to these fancy words soon enough
Well, ok, this is abstract
but let's see if we can get to a concrete notion
M i j, the abstract operator
Is equivalent to a concrete matrix
if I give you the concrete matrix
that I'm giving you M
The question is in terms of that concrete matrix
is there a concrete matrix for M dagger?
The answer is yes
How do you find it?
We find it just by proceeding dead ahead
I would like to know, what the matrix elements
let's see which way I did it
Yeah, this is what I would call
the i j th matrix element of M dagger
I don't know what M dagger is yet
I have a suspicion
that something to do with complex conjugates
But this is its matrix elements
concrete set of numbers
Can we find out what they are?
Alright, yeah I think I have to step back for a minute
Let me suppose that M acts on the basis vector
to give i prime
i prime is just the result of sticking the basis vector
into the machine, into the M machine
and this is what it comes out
let's suppose that's the result
Now let's take j M i
That's equal to j i prime
All I've done is taking inner product with j
Here's the matrix element of the matrix M
and it's just this inner product that
that was a trivial operation
I didn't do anything, Ok?
I didn't do anything very significant
If this is true then by definition
then by definition, M dagger acting to the left
What does M dagger acting to the left give on i?
Ok, look at this equation here
M dagger acts to the left gives the bra vector B
So I thought that all the dagger does is
that it turns equation over
So what does M dagger acting on i give?
It gives the bra vector i prime
If M dagger acts on the bra i
it must give the bra vector i prime
It just flips the equation from bras to kets
So we have over here then is i prime j
That's the matrix element
that's this matrix element over here
Okay, so let's look at what we have
We have a matrix element of M is the inner product of j with i prime
The matrix element of M dagger
is the inner product of i prime with j
What's the relationship between these two?
Student: (mumble) complex conjugate
just complex conjugate
If you take two vectors, A and B
and you think of them in the opposite order
The bra A times the ket B versus the bra B times the ket A
the relationship between them is just complex conjugation
So this here is just a complex conjugate of this
So what we've derived is that the matrix element
the i j th matrix element of M dagger
is the complex conjugate of the j i th matrix element of M
So if I know the matrix elements of M
What do I do to get the matrix elements of M dagger
It's very simple
You complex conjugate but that's not quite enough
you complex conjugate and you interchange i s and j s
you interchange i and j, ok?
Another way to write it is that M dagger i j
is equal to M j i star
So now we know a lot
We know how to construct operators which act to the left
to do the same mapping
that they did when I went to the right
The bra A to the bra B
if the original operator do the same thing to the kets
Alright that's the notion of Hermitian conjugation
This is called Hermitian conjugation, The word Hermitian
is named after some mathematician
whose name was Hermite
and Hermitian conjugation is the process of
interchanging i and j and taking its complex conjugate
in terms of matrices
If I have a matrix
this is an easy way to remember it
M one one, M one two, dot dot dot
M two one, M two two, dot dot dot
If that's the matrix representing M
then the matrix representing its conjugated
its Hermitian conjugate is
to simply interchange rows and columns
That means reflecting it about the diagonal
and then complex conjugating
interchanging i and j
let's interchange m one two with M two one
you just flip it about the diagonal
and you complex conjugated
So if I want the matrix elements of the Hermitian conjugate
Well, I can't say any more
you just do what I said
You interchange rows and columns
and you complex conjugate
Interchanging rows and columns is the same thing
is reflecting about the diagonal
You reflect about the diagonal
Let's do it
and then you complex conjugate
Let me give an example
Supposing I have the matrix
Two, six plus i times seven
Four minus i and nine, nine plus i
ok, nine plus i
What's the Hermitian conjugation of that
Well, you first flip it
flipping it leaves the diagonal elements in place
interchanges the off diagonal elements
So you flip it
Two, nine plus i
six plus i times seven,four minus i
What is that process called of uh, flipping like that
Transpose, that's called the transpose
So flipping is the transpose
but then you have the complex conjugated
Complex conjugating just means
wherever you see i put minus i
So this becomes four plus i
one minus seven i and nine minus i
and that's the matrix
that represents Hermitian conjugate of the original matrix
So it's easy, it's easy, it's concrete
and it's also abstract it has an abstract side
The Hermitian conjugate just allows you
to turn in equation from a bra vector to a ket vector
and in terms of concrete matrix elements
You flip i and j
and you complex conjugate not defines M dagger
Now is that in generally matrices
a sort of as complex objects
and the notion of complex conjugation
is replaced by this Hermitian conjugation
simultaneous flipping and uh,
Now what is a real number?
A real number is one which is its own complex conjugate
If I write z is equal to z star
you jump up and you say
that is a real number
There's a corresponding notion for operators
It's the notion
and operator which is its own Hermitian conjugate
An operator which is its own Hermitian conjugate
That means you interchange and complex conjugate
you get back to the same thing
that is called Hermitian
Hermitian is the analog for matrices
or the analog for operators of real
Alright so what it says a Hermitian matrix
Now let's specialize to the case of Hermitian matrices
I'll just spell out Hermitian for you
Hermitian for matrices is the analog of real for numbers
A Hermitian operator or matrix is one which is equal
to its own Hermitian conjugate in terms of matrices
It's M i j, is equal to M j i star
Let's try to see if we can construct Hermitian matrix
Let's see we can construct a Hermitian matrix
The first thing about Hermitian matrices
is that diagonal elements are always real
take a diagonal element
for diagonal element i and j are equal
i j is the same as j i if on the diagonal
So that says that for the diagonal elements
they're always real
so Hermitian matrix first of all has real diagonal elements
Uh, one, seven, I like seven, minus two point six
on the diagonal
Off the diagonal
they have the property that when you reflect them
They simply complex conjugate
so we would put i over here
We would put minus i over here for Hermitian matrix
If you are would put four minus i over here
you would put four plus i over here
and if you have five over here
you put five over here
So Hermitian matrix has the property
first of all diagonal elements are real
and the off diagonal elements, not symmetric
But a different kind of symmetry
A symmetry when you reflect them the complex conjugate
That's called a Hermitian matrix
A Hermitian matrix has an enormous importance
and Hermitian matrices have enormous importance
in quantum mechanics
They represent the observable quantities
The measurable quantities
The things that you can measure
We're gonna come to that
We're going to do a bit of that
especially for the single spin I hope tonight
But before we do we have to know a little more about Hermitian matrices
In particular we need a concept
a concept of eigenvector and eigenvalue
I know I'm going fast and I know I'm quite aware that if you don't know
these ideas you're going
you have to struggle tonight to keep up
but they're standard ideas
There're lots of textbooks on linear algebra
You can find it and you can sit down quietly
and then learn these ideas in about two hours
I would say two three hours
Ok, so let's talk about Hermitian
Let's first talk about eigenvectors and eigenvalues
(erase the whiteboard)
We can even think about these things incidentally
in ordinary three-dimensional space
within a vector space
just the space of ordinary three vectors
Uh, there are operators, the represented by matrices
and those operators, operators on vectors to give other vectors
and typically if a matrix is all interesting
if operator is all interesting whatever mean to be interesting
Well, it's a little bit complex
It would generally have the property
that if you put a vector into the machine
the vector comes out
will be pointing in a different direction
That would be generally true, generically true
Ah, so directionality is not preserved
by linear operators as a rule
On the other hand there may be particular vectors
and typically there are particular vectors
uh, that when you apply in matrix
Those vectors would depend on
which matrix you talking about or an operator
There may be specific vectors associated with
the specific operator
that do simply get multiplied by numbers
Another words that come out in the same direction
An example, an example of an operational
a linear operational on a vector is a rotation about
an axis that can be represented by a matrix
Uh, in three dimensions
if you rotate the vector space about some axis
Then generally speaking
an arbitrary vector will wind up in a different direction
However there is one particular direction
for which that doesn't happen
namely along the axis of rotation
if you rotate about the axis of rotation
The vector comes out pointing in the same direction
It comes out multiple of itself
Now in this case, simply equal to itself
Alright, that's the notion of the eigenvectors of an operator
They are the vectors if there are any
They're not necessarily any
For example in rotations about two and two dimensions
There are no eigenvectors
There are no directions which come out
No directions which come out unaffected
But, so in general may or may not be the, eigenvectors
But if there are eigenvectors defined in the following way
Again I'm gonna use M for the generic operator
M acts on an eigenvector
Let's call the eigenvector I
I for eigen and now of course I is not for eigen
Eigen becomes an E
But I am going to call it I anyway
If M acts on one of its eigenvectors
Eigenvectors are not things
which are independent of the matrices
Given a matrix or operator
it has certain eigen directions or certain eigenvectors
and the rule is, or the definition
is the set of vectors
which just get multiplied by numbers
Let's call for the ith eigenvector here
The eigenvalue is called lambda I
and simply multiplies the input
Now different eigenvectors
of the same matrix will have different eigenvalues
There may be and in general
that's the generic situation
If there are several eigenvectors
they will have different eigenvalues
However the eigenvectors are not completely unambiguous
If you take an eigenvector and multiply it by a number
the result is still an eigenvector with the same eigenvalue
If I multiply this equation by a complex numbers z
I can bring the complex number z through
and I'll find out that any numerical
even complex numerical, multiple over
an eigenvector is also an eigenvector
Uh, so strictly speaking you should talk about eigen directions
the set of vectors, uh, is uh,
uh, including
or not worrying about their length so speak?
But in any case this is the direction of an
this is the definition of an eigenvector
Alright, some matrices have eigenvectors
Other matrices don't have eigenvectors
There's something important about Hermitian matrices
Or Hermitian operators
Hermitian operators is not only have eigenvectors
They have a complete set of eigenvectors
Complete means
that there are enough of them to expand any vector
and even better
they have orthornormal family of eigenvectors
In general different eigenvectors
have different eigenvalues as I said
But it will be true that matrix Hermitian
it has n, the dimensionality of the spaces n
there will be n mutually orthogonal eigenvectors
Another words, the eigenvectors of Hermitian matrices
defined a basis
I'm going to let you approve part of that theorem
It's a very easy theorem to prove
I'm gonna prove the other half of it
I'll prove the half, that says that
if you have two eigenvector with different eigenvalues
and that's the generic situation
The eigenvalues are all different
If you have two different eigenvectors with different eigenvalues
we'll prove that they're orthogonal to each other
Your job is just to prove
that you won't run out of eigenvectors
until you have n of them
That's not hard
It's not hard
In any case it's true
Alright so let's prove
that if we have two eigenvectors
Let's, M is a Hermitian, right?
Let's, M is Hermitian
M equals a Hermitian matrix
I use matrix as an operator anonymously
which means that M equals M dagger
Okay, let's suppose that M is Hermitian
and it has an eigenvalue lambda I
The first observation
is that the eigenvalues of Hermitian matrices are real
That even comes before when I said previously
If there is an eigenvalue is real, Ok?
How do we prove that it's real?
Let's prove that it's real
Well, let's take this equation and flip it over
into a bra equation
To flip it over into a bra equation
I flipped I, I take and then replace it by M dagger
Well that's not going to do much
because M is equal to M dagger
And on the right hand side, I flipped I
and what will I do with lambda in general?
Complex conjugate, complex conjugate lambda
So far we haven't proved that it's real
Every time you flip from bras to kets
you have to complex conjugate all the numbers
that are there
Alright, but now, assumption, M is Hermitian
So it's equal to its own Hermitian conjugate
And now we have this equation
Now let's take the inner product
of both of these equations with I
and the upper equation
we're gonna take the inner product
on the left with I
and what does that give us that gives us I I
times lambda I
Let's do the same thing over here
except now multiply on the right
This and this are obviously the same
M with I on the left
and I on the right is the same as this
But this is not obviously the same
not unless lambda is equal to lambda star
I I here are the same as I I here
That cancels out
and therefore we come to the conclusion
that if a matrix is Hermitian
if it's equal to its own Hermitian conjugate
Then its eigenvalues
are equal to their own complex conjugates
and they are real
Eigenvalues of Hermitian matrices are real
That's the first step
Now let's prove
that if we have two different eigenvalues
the corresponding eigenvectors must be orthogonal
Now remember what orthogonal means
from a physical point of view
It means physically distinct
that is an experiment
that you can do to distinguish the two of them unambiguously
That's what orthogonal means
from a physical point of view
Let's prove that the eigenvectors
of M with different eigenvalue are orthogonal
Different eigenvalues physically descent distinguishable
You should keep that in your head
Okay, so here we are, let's, let's start with M on I
equals lambda I I
And M on J equals lambda J J
two different eigenvectors, I and J
First we'll do
is turned this one over
and turn it into a ket equation, uh, a bra, it is a ket equation
We take this one and turn it into a bra equation
so that looks like this
J, M dagger, but M dagger is the same as M
equals the real number lambda J
eigenvector, eigenvalues of Hermitian matrices are real, times J
Now here we have, okay, so we, we have
two equations
what can you do to them
so that we can relate them
What we can do with them to relate them
is to multiply this one by J on the left
|1012
and this one by I on the right
and we will get the same expression
on the left hand side of the equation
So let's do that
J, J, I, I
What we have on the left is the same
in the upper and lower equation
What we have on the right is not necessarily the same
so that requires that it's the same
Requiring that it's the same says that lambda I
minus lambda J
times the inner product of J with I must equal zero
I've just written a fence
I've just written that this is equal to this
and then transposed
That's lambda I minus lambda J
times the inner product of J and I equal zero
Well, if the product of two things and I have two things
lambda I minus lambda J  and the inner product of J and I
The product of two things are zero
it says unambiguously at least one of them is zero
It usually says one of them is zero, Ok?
The inner product of I and J may or may not be zero
But let's take the case what we know
that the eigenvectors correspond to
different values of the eigen
sorry, the eigenvalues are different
That's what I'm interested
I'm interested in eigenvectors
corresponding to different values of the eigenvalue
So by assumption lambda I is not equal to lambda J
The conclusion is that the inner product of I with J
must be equal to zero
So what does that mean?
That means that I and J are orthogonal
So now we have a theorem
the eigenvectors of Hermitian matrices
with different eigenvalues are orthogonal
Uh, let's just take the generic case
where all of the eigenvalues are different
We will come back to what happens when some of them may be the same
It's not important right now
if all the eigenvalues have to be different to each other
Then all the eigenvectors
are mutually orthogonal to each other
If there are enough of them
and your job is to prove enough of them
they form a basis
Another words this collection of things called I and J here
is a special case of the kind of basis
which we labeled with small I and J
But it's the basis of eigenvectors
that's the basis of eigenvectors of the Hermitian operator
as I said Hermitian operators
will be identified with observable quantities
and to say that eigenvectors are orthogonal
has something other to do with physical differences
that are measurable unambiguously
between those states of the system
Ok, we are now prepared to state
the principles of quantum mechanics
We have enough mathematical information
or enough mathematical formalism
to state the entire of show
we can put on the blackboard now
what quantum mechanics is and what it says
and uh, what the rules are
or what the correspondences are
what the mathematical
sorry what the, uh,
what the physical meanings of these various things are
You won't get there
You won't understand this the first time around
It'll be foreign
it'll be to kill your what is it talking about
But of course we will work it out in an example
so we'll see how the ideas work
so don't get disturbed
if what I throw at you now sounds a little bit meaningless
That's ok. By the time we'll finish some examples
it should be clear how we use this
Alright, first of all there are measurable quantities
The result of a measurement is always a real number
It takes at least two measurements
and to somehow to compatible measurements
two measurements that can both be performed simultaneously
to measure a complex number
The basic ingredients and basic measurables are real numbers
that's what's comes out of your detector
You can measure two of them
if you can measure two of them
If it is possible to simultaneously measure two things
and put them together into a complex number
but really is just two measurements
So each measurement, each thing that you measure
has a real result associated with it
The physical measurables, the called observables
quantum mechanics called observables
the things that you can measure
The observables are identified with Hermitian matrices
or Hermitian operators
Observables, it's not a q, what like a q from
(hand writing)
I want to write equals
are represented by, I'll just put an arrow
are represented by Hermitian linear, of course, operators
First thing
Let's just say, in the study the spin
in the uh, in the uh, in a Rough Lose way
we saw them identified some observables
The observables that we identified
with the components of the spin
The observables that we could identify
were associated with our apparatus point apparatus in some direction
and measure the spin along those directions
we said, we called if we measured the spin
along the z axis, we called it sigma z
We can measure it
or we could turn our apparatus on its side
and measure sigma x
Or we can turn on our apparatus soon
from the x axis to the y axis and measures sigma y
We talked about those things
We didn't talk about sigmas being Hermitian operators
We haven't talked about them being operators at all
But we did talk about measuring them
these will become Hermitian operators in time, Ok?
Next, the possible values
that a given observable can take on
What are they for sigma z?
One of the possible, plus or minus one, right?
The possible observable values
measured in an experiment
those observable values are the eigenvalues
They're real because the matrices are Hermitian
The eigenvectors, what about eigenvectors?
The eigenvectors correspond to states
States, vectors, states, vectors
The eigenvectors are the states
in which the corresponding quantities are definite
Another words in which the measurement of them
is unambiguous
Let's, let's follow through on this here a little bit
For all three of these observables
the eigenvalues had better be plus or minus one
Okay now let's come to the eigenvectors
The eigenvectors, for example
the eigenvector with a given eigenvalue
is a state of the system
where if you measure that particular observable
you will be definitely get the eigenvalue
associated with that eigenvector
So the eigenvectors, those are
We should have a backwards
we should put eigenvectors on the side
and on the left side the physical meaning of them
the physical meaning is the states in which
observable has unambiguous result
Example, we talk, for example
about the states up and down
Those are states
in which sigma z had definite values
When you're up, sigma z is definitely one
when you're down sigma z definitely minus one
Any other vector
sigma z is statistically is plus or minus one, but with randomness
So up and down must be the eigenvectors of sigma z
Left and right or the states
in which sigma x was unambiguously
either plus or minus one
So left and right must be the eigenvectors of sigma x
What the sigma x is?
We are trying to figure out what sigma x is
knowing it eigenvalues
or its eigenvalues and its eigenvectors
And what are the other three
other two called in and out I think
In and out were the eigenvectors of sigma y
So we have three connections
and now a fourth connection
Given a general state, not an eigenvector
not an eigenvector
Given a general state A
somebody made an electron or a system of some sort
and left it in the state A
then we can talk about what is the probability
that we measure the eigenvalues of M
at different values
There may be several different eigenvalues
in this case they would be plus one or minus one
but more generally
thousand eigenvalues million eigenvalues whatever whatever the number is
Labeled by the, the label I
What is the probability that when you measure M
you get lambda I?
That's the last piece of thing here
so left-hand side we put probability
physical meaning probability
and I'll write it just as the probability
to measure I
No, to measure lambda I
I'm sorry, to measure lambda I
that the result of the experiment comes out
a particular eigenvalue of the observable M
Whatever M is
That is related
not related to, it's essentially equal to
Two pieces come to two steps
First, you calculate if you have the vector A
The vector which to start the state of the system
You take its inner product with the eigenvector I
the projection of A onto I
the component of A in the I direction
now that in general is a complex number
That is not the probability
You multiply it by its own complex conjugate
to get a real positive number
and that is the probability
We can multiply this by its complex conjugate
or we can just write it I, A this
I A and A I are complex conjugates of each other
We can also write this as the absolute value of I A squared
The individual components
before we square them are called amplitudes
They're called probability amplitudes
Probability amplitudes are things
which you multiply by their complex conjugates
to find probabilities
They are real
They are positive
and that's the fourth, the fourth postulate
of quantum mechanics
That I know are independent
I use them because uh
because they are reasonably intuitive
In fact, you can probably get rid of
at least two of them and prove them from the others
But we don't need to do that
This is a good starting point
Uh, and these are the basic postulates for quantum mechanics, ok?
The other postulate is that
when you're measuring a quantity
you prepare the system
in a state of definite value of that quantity
I won't bother write that down
When you measure something
you are in a fact
pushing it into a state of definite value
of that quantity depending on
what the outcome of your experiment is
If your outcome measures some particular
the outcome of an experiment
to some particular eigenvalue
That means you push the system into the state
into eigenstate of that quantity with that eigenvalue
I won't write that down
It takes too many words to write that down
Student: What's that P? the probability?
This? This
Student: yeah
Student: That's the P with?
Student: I can't recognize your handwriting
Probability
Probe, it's probability probe
It's Probably probability
Yeah, (laugh)
This is the probability of measuring lambda
Oh, what is lambda I?
Lambda I, the probability of measuring lambda I
is the square of the inner product of A with I
It's if you like it's the projection
of A onto the I th direction
of the component of A in the I direction
Now, there's an implication here
there's an implication here
about the nature of state vectors
coming from the assumption
that total probabilities are equal to one
Student: (mumble)
What's that?
Student: It has to be normalized?
Yeah
Let's work that out
If you want the total probability to add up to one
then you want the sums of all these objects
when you sum over I over various possible values of,
that you can measure
You want that the equal one
so you want the sum over I
for any allowable state A
We want the sum of A, I, I, A to equal one
Now I is a basis
and if you go up to the top equation there
You have equations
which tell you how to deal with
exactly this combination
What is the sum over I of I I A?
It's just A
So what this says
is that the inner product of A with itself should equal one
The total length of A should be equal to one
That's not too surprising that
That's what this is
This is the sums of the squares of the components of A add up to one
For ordinary vectors
that would say the length of the vector was one and that's what this is
The length of A is equal to one
It's equivalent in terms of the alphas
We got really on the alphas up there
and also that's equivalent to the sum of alpha star i alpha i equals one
Well I, capital I
and so there is one combination of the alphas
this is one real equation, not complex equation
It's a real equation
and that means is one real combination of the alphas
which has to be constrained
Alphas are not completely free
Or the alphas are not completely free, this uh,
Roughly speaking, the sums of the squares are sums of them
times a complex conjugate has to add up to one
So that means is less, fewer, independent quantities
you thought
There is another fact which we have not gotten to yet
We will get to it
You could sort of see it from here
All probabilities any probability
that you ever may want to measure
or that you ever may want to
uh, to calculate or compare with experiment
is always connected
with a real quantity like this
The collection with such real quantities
is invariant under a certain operation
The operation is multiplying the state vector by a phase
Everybody know what means to multiply a number of thing by a phase?
You multiply by the e to the i theta
If you multiply all the components of A
by the same overall phase
then every probability is unchanged
Every probability is unchanged
uh, even if you rotate basis, it's unchanged
So physical quantities don't respond to a change of the phase
That means there are two fewer degrees of freedom
two fewer parameters in the specification of the state
Then the collection of complex numbers
that would define a vector in the abstract space
Two, one is the phase, the overall phase
and the other is the magnitude of it
We'll come back to that
Okay that uh, that's taken us a long way
Uh, you're probably saturated but I am not
so we are going to continue
I am in high
Student: Question?
Student: It has to be positive, can't be negative, right?
Yeah, this is always positive
Thing times its complex is always positive
Student: Is the evolution postulate?
Is what? is what?
Student: evolution postulate
We haven't, yeah, we haven't gotten to that yet
How things change with time, yeah
No, we are into the level now
of where we are in classical physics
when we just said the state of the system
is just a point in the, uh, among a set of things
That's about where we are
That's how far we've gotten
We are not talking about how things
how things change
the particular how the states of systems change
We will come to that
Student: Back to the beginning
Student: we had this example of measuring its q bits
Student: and you had some angle
Student: and you got to cosine theta, right? So
We'll do it, well
Student: Ok, I get my question was
Student: we somehow get the idea that
Student: the cosine theta is the average of the measurements
Student: shouldn't it be cosine squared?
Um, um
Student: No?
I think you own (laugh)
Student: Can you say that last part one more time that we can
Which part?
Student: When you measure something
Student: you push it into the state you are measuring
No, when you measure something you get a result
The result is statistically determined
Meaning to say that you may get one result
you may get another result but once you get that result
then you know what state the system is in
it's in the eigenstate
of the quantity that you measured
with the eigenvalue that came up on your detector
Remember, when we had our apparatus
and we measured sigma z
we said that not only measure sigma z
but it prepare the system and state of definite sigma z
It leaves over in the state
in which sigma z is definite for the next measurement
That means leaves it in an eigenstate of sigma z
Ok, let's apply this (cough) to the spin system
You own very general formulation
and now we want to try out to see how it works
Alright, so I want to start with
the three observables sigma x sigma y and sigma z
and see where I can learn about them
First of all, sigma z
Now let's start in the basis associated with
the measurement of the spin along the z axis
Let's take that as appropriate basis
Sigma z two eigenvectors by
from the experiments
so we talked about we would have learned
that we've done the experiment
That sigma z has two eigenvalues and two eigenvectors
The two eigenvectors we've called up and down
and they are associated with sigma z
equals plus one and minus one
There must be eigenvectors of sigma z and eigenvalues
and so I can immediately say sigma z times up
is equal to up plus one time's up
Why? Because the measured value
when we measure sigma z
is going to be plus one
That's eigenvalue and up is the eigenvector
because in the upstate sigma z is definite
What about sigma z on the down state
What should I write there?
Is sigma z definite in the down state?
Yes, it's always minus one
It's going to be minus one
and that means the eigenvalues minus one times down
It's not sigma z times down equals up
That wouldn't be an eigenvector
An eigenvector has a property
that when the operator acts on it
it gives the same direction back times the eigenvalue
So here is what we know about sigma z
Let's see if we can compute its matrix elements
and exhibited as a matrix
But when I say exhibited as a matrix I have picked
I must pick a basis
I'm going to pick the basis up and down
First of all, one thing
up and down are orthogonal to each other
They must be according to these principles
Because of sigma z is an observable
it corresponds to Hermitian matrix
If there are two different eigenvalues
The eigenvectors must be orthogonal for Hermitian matrix
and so up and down
we first of all learned that up and down are orthogonal
That's one fact
So it doesn't matter
whether we write up and down or down up we can write the opposite order
Let's see if we can compute the matrix elements
The matrix elements are just the array that we get
when we consider the four possibilities
It's going to be two by two matrices
and the four possibilities are going to be,
first of all, we take the inner product with this back with up
That will be the up up matrix element
the one one matrix element
What is that going to be
To find, let's, I'm not sure I want to
Let's do it over here
Let's calculate up, sigma z, up
That's equal
Sigma z acts to the right to give us up plus one
Or plus is just one, times up
Just inner product of up with itself
and since up is a basis vector, it's normalized
and this is just equal to one
Its magnitude is equal to one
I can choose it to be equal to one
Uh, it's positive, yeah, it's positive, it's real
and it's just plain one
So up here in the up up, or the one one place is just one
Now let's worry about the off diagonal element
The off diagonal element
That's off diagonal element there
That's going to be equal
to be inner of down with up
What's that? It's zero over here
I would get exactly the same thing
if I put down over here and up over here
That would use this equation over here
that sigma z act on down
and then take its overlap with up
and I will get zero again
And the last one is down, sigma z, down
What is that?
Well you're going to here
sigma z times downs is minus down
So this is just equal to minus down down
What's that?
Minus one
So this is the matrix
That's associated with sigma z
When it acts on a vector on a column vector
in particular when it acts,
What is the column vector that associated with up?
It's just one on the top and zero in the bottom
Alright, let's just try this, one zero
What do we get? we get one times one is one
zero times zero is zero
we just get the same vector back
That's good, ok, same thing
It's guaranteed that will get the right
The eigenvectors are what they're supposed to be
Namely just up and down
and the eigenvalue are plus one minus one in the right way
Alright, so we found one of the sigma matrices, sigma z
is of course, well not of course
they called the Pauli matrices
sigma x sigma y and sigma z
Let's see what we can find out about sigma x
Now I'm using if I use the x basis
or I use the basis of left and right
of course I would just find exactly the same thing
But I want to stick with the up down basis
I want to stick with the up down basis
But find out what the matrix elements of sigma x are
Now what is the property of sigma x?
The property of sigma x is
that its eigenvectors are left and right
So for example, sigma x on right that equals right
and what about sigma x on left?
Equals minus left
Those are the two possible values
that sigma x can take on
Left and right are the eigenvectors
and another words the states in which the sigma x has definite values
plus one and minus one
and this is what I know about sigma x
But I want to find its matrix elements in the up down basis
So what I really want then let's uh,
Let's come over to here
and see if we can compute in the same basis
What do we do with Pauli matrix? Did I erase it?
I work so hard to get it
Sigma z is equal to one minus one zero zero
Now we want to try to get sigma x
So the first step is, oh here it is, to erase the blackboard
Let's start one by one
There are four matrix elements
Let's do it one by one
Up, sigma x, up
What we have to know is
that up is equal to left plus right over the square root of two
Remember that?
We originally defined
left and right to be up plus or minus down
over the square root of two
But then we can solve for up and down
in terms of left and right
Down, down is, left, sorry, it's right minus left
with the notation we had last time was down
sorry, is right minus left over Root Two
So all we have to do is to plug them in
On the left here we have, left
You know I'm gonna abuse notation
and just write this as left plus right over squared root of two
This is a meaningless symbol
but I think you know what I mean
I mean the bra vector left
plus the bra vector right over the square root of two
But too many vertical strokes and I get confused
So let's write, let's put right over the square root of two
Sigma x, left plus right over squared root of two
First of all, I can take out
This is the, what is this thing?
This is sigma x up and up, there it is
This is up and up and one goes up in here
Alright first of all, there's a factor of true
that I can take out square root of two from here
and the square root two from here
That's altogether one-half
Now let's look at this
What happens when sigma x hits left?
It gives back left except with the minus sign
What happens when sigma x hits right?
It gives back right with a plus sign
So when sigma x acts on this
What ones giving you can take the sigma x away
and just remember what it does
It gives right minus left instead of right plus left
It hits the vector right and give plus one
It hits the vector left and gives minus one again
These are not things to be numerically added
These are vectors
The right vector minus the left vector
and now what we have to do is take the inner products
Well, the inner product of right with right is what?
One
The inner product of right with the left is?
Zero
The inner product of left with right is zero
and the inner product of left with left
Student: One or minus one?
Minus one when you account for this minus
The result is they cancel, right?
One minus one
Equivalently the inner product of uh, of uh, of uh
Well, ok, zero
So first of all those zero are over here
That's the up up matrix element
It's easy to get the down down matrix element
To get the down down matrix element
you would do exactly the same thing
you except you start with right minus left
right minus left, right minus left
sigma x
and then you would say when sigma x hits right
it's plus right
When it hits left, it gives minus left
When sigma x acts
it takes right minus left to right plus left
and what's the inner product of right plus left with my right minus left
Zero again
Right with right is one
Left left is minus one
The cross term is just zero
So this is zero over here
Now, we are going to get zeros, but that can't be right
So let's try, let's try up down
Alright, we try to up down
Let's put up down there
Up will be right plus left, will have sigma x
and then down was right minus left
What happens when sigma x is right plus left?
It makes right minus left
and now what's the inner product?
Inner product of right with the right is one
The inner product of minus left with minus left is also plus one
So they add, and again
The cross terms between right and left are zero
So we get two divided by two which is one
Is one up here and if we work it out
we will get another one over here
So now we've got sigma y
Let's just stop for a minute and say what is it that we have
We have a pair of linear operators, a pair of matrices
whose eigenvectors are
This fellow's eigenvectors here are up and down
This fellow's eigenvectors are right and left
They are exactly what we were talking about on the previous blackboard
The states in which the observables
have unambiguous results are the eigenvectors
That's what we are now
The last one is sigma y, Ok?
What do we know about sigma y? I am not
In and out are the eigenvectors
Student: So the one what we did is just sigma x, right?
The one we did is sigma x
Student: Yours is sigma y
Oh, sorry
Student: Yes
I don't think I wrote sigma y
I think I just failed to cross the x
I think, maybe I wrote sigma y
Alright, the next one is sigma y
and here I'm going to leave some of the words,
some of the algebras
It's very easy to you but let's see what the uh,
What the rules are
Oh, incidentally, no, I think we are Ok
Okay so there was in and out
I cannot remember which one was which
So I am going to fake it
and if the comes out wrong, it comes out wrong
Uh, I think in was up, plus, I think, i times down
and out was up minus i times down
and I left out a factor of square root of two
Incidentally you can check
that in and out are orthogonal to each other
Ok, these are in and out
Can we find a matrix
which in and out are eigenvectors
with eigenvalue plus one and minus one
It's getting late
It's very easy
leave it to you
I will simply tell you what that matrix is
It's unique
If you know the eigenvectors and if you know the eigenvalues
One way of doing it is to solve for up and down
in terms of in and out
Once you solved for up and down
in terms of in and out and you know how the matrix acts on in and out
you've finished
The last one in the multiple here
Now I am writing sigma y
Similar to this one
But it's all minus i and i
Alright, so a little exercise
You don't really need to go and prove this
You can do a different thing
You can take this matrix
and show that these are the eigenvectors of it
Just show that these are the eigenvectors of it
If you take this matrix
and show that if its eigenvectors
What is that mean?
It means its eigenvectors are one i and one minus i
The square root of two doesn't matter
Eigenvectors are eigenvectors
They don't care about the square root of two
These are the three Pauli matrices
They represent the components of the spin
in different directions
Uh, I think, uh, that's enough for tonight
What I was going to do
and I have in my notes was exactly this question
what happens if you have a component of spin
along an arbitrary direction
Can we show using what we know?
But the problem, I will do this next time
We will do this next time
If we have a component of spin along an arbitrary direction
and we want to calculate using the principles
We want to calculate what the probability is
for the measurement of sigma z in various, either plus or minus
We should be able to do it
We have enough information
I think it's probably more than
than what we can get handle for tonight
We did a lot for tonight
Probably more than reasonable
Student: Am I wrong to make the u be negative
Student: to solve the problem?
Student: Is one of the u is negative?
No, you know you're missing? You're missing to have to complex conjugate
If you want to inner product of in with out
you multiply one times one
and then add I, not times minus sign but i times plus i
Yeah, yeah, the only way is that somebody like me know so quickly
why what you're thinking
is having made the same mistake of course, (laugh)
Sometime in the past, Ok
Alright, we've finished with tonight I think
and I left these questions
For more, please visit us at stanford dot edu