Stanford University
Okay, let's, let's go on
Let's forget for the moment, the spin system
We will come back to it, probably tonight, definitely tonight
But let's remind ourselves of,
I think I wrote down four principles of quantum mechanics last time
And I wanna write them down again
And then move on to a fifth principle
In fact they are not all independent
It's easier for me to explain them one at a time
To deprive from the minimal, absolute minimal number of them
I don't think there is any particular advantage in doing that
So I just write down... all the principles that I wrote down
The first one is the observable, the observables are the things you measure
It could be called measurable, if I have, if it's up to me, I would call it measurable
But they are called observables
Observables are represented... I will just use the equal sign to indicate that
Observables are represented by Hermitian operators
I use the symbol L for the moment for the Hermitian operator
Not all operators, not all linear operators are Hermitian
And it will not always be the case that
the symbol L will stand for Hermitian operator
But right now, L stand for Hermitian operator, any Hermitian operator
Every observable is identified with a Hermitian operator
Then the question is whether every Hermitian operator
is a thing which can be measured, is a generally hard question,
you know, what can or can't be measured
depends on what the materials you have available, all kind of things
Generally, the abstract rule, or the full rule, let's call it,
Is it any Hermitian operator is identified with a observable and
Some day somebody will figure out how to measure it
Okay, but the other way that any observable
is identified with a Hermitian operator, that's for sure
The eigenvalue of a Hermitian operator, let's call them lambdas
Lambda is the eigenvalue of L
The eigenvalues represent the possible numerical values
that L can exhibit when it's measured
Okay so eigenvalues, eigenvalues of L which equal lambda
Now they represent the possible observe...
or the possible outcome of an experiment
Possible outcome of an experiment to measure L of L measurement
Okay I think we have a third one along the line here
Physically distinguishable state,
Now let's just see what physically distinguishable state means
Certainly up and down are physically distinguishable
And the meaning of saying two states are physically distinguishable
is that there exist a measurement of some kind that you can do
that can tell you the difference between a up state and a down state
Another words, somebody hands you a spin from out of their pocket
And they say I created the spin,
I prepared it in a state which is either up or down
Can you do an experiment to unambiguously tell me which one it is?
Yes you tilt your apparatus until it's pointing along the z axis
And you make the measurement
If the state was up you will get plus one
If the state was down you will get minus one
No ambiguity
The same is true for left and right
Different measurement, different thing that you will measure
You will measure the x component,
then you will tilt your apparatus along the x axis
but, same deal,
on the other hand, supposing somebody, that same person came along and said here
I'm gonna give you a spin, here it is, and that spin either prepared up
or I prepared it right
I'm not gonna tell you which way I prepared it
I'm not gonna tell you in which way I tilted the apparatus
when I did the preparation
I'm just tell you it's either left... I'm sorry it's either up or right
Can you do a experiment which will uniquely tell you the difference?
The answer is no, for example supposing you decide to measure the spin along the z axis
Well if it's up you will get plus one, if it's right,
with fifty percent probability you will get plus one
So you can't be sure whether you are up or right
>> forty five degrees
still you will have a probability for
Ya, ya, it would not be unambiguous, right, okay?
So the next postulate
>> excuse me, if in that statement you were assuming it was prepared along the z axis
>> If it have been prepared along the x axis
>> Then if you measure the x axis first, you get ...
If you measure the x axis first you will find something else
But you could have found out exactly the same answer if it was along the z axis
Either case, there was some probability
of getting the same answer whether it was up or right
There is no experiment you can do
which unambiguously will determine which it was
That leads to the notion, I am not going to give you a more precise definition of it
That leads to the notion of physically distinguishable states
by which it's meant that
their exist an experiment or a set of experiments
that can unambiguously determine which of the two states you are talking about
The next postulate is that physically distinct or physically distinguishable states
are represented by orthogonal vectors
Okay, so physically distinct, distinct, distinguishable, same thing
It's easier to write distinct
This physically distinct states imply orthogonality
I said that observables are Hermitian operators
I could have just said linear operators,
let's leave with linear operator for the moment
But let's add a postulate that the result of every experiments
Every simple primitive experiment it's a real number
If it's a real number... if it's a complex number
It really means that, two independent things are measured
The actual result come out of your apparatus, come out of, you know
The needle on your apparatus ,the real numbers
So I will let that as a postulate, the result of experiments are always real numbers
And therefore the eigenvalues of observables are real numbers
Now that does not prove that the operators are Hermitian, not enough
The other added thing is the various eigen vector with different eigen value
is physically distinguishable states, or orthogonal
Okay that's the third postulate
And that tells you the observables are Hermitian operators
It's the Hermitian operator whose eigen values are always real
And whose eigen vectors are orthogonal
That's necessary and sufficient
And this one like I said, they are not all completely independent to each other
One, two, three, and let's write number four now
I forgot what fourth is, oh,
Well, what was fourth? Ya
Ah, the probability, the probability principle, okay
The probability principle, it's also called Born's rule, that Max Born
But it's a rule for probabilities
So far, none of these have much content, the added content
You know, it has content, but the real bite here is for the prediction of the probability
for various experiments
And the Born rule is the rule for how to calculate the probabilities
The Born rule says, if your system has been prepared in state |A>
System in |A>
And you measure L, the observable L
Now I'm using interchangeably the physical idea
with observables with the operator which represent it
I'm not going to make a special language where
operator will always be called operator
And the observable of L, same thing
They come in pairs
Alright, if you, if the system has been prepared in state |A>
And you measure L, you measure L
The outcome is going to be one of the eigenvalues
So the only question you can ask is
what is the probability that you get the answer lambda
One of the specific eigenvalues
The answer is, the probability
The probability that you get result lambda
That's the probability you get out of the various eigenvalue you get lambda
Is equal to the square of inner product of the state vector
That the system was in
With the eigen vector corresponding the normalized eigenvector
or vector normalized now
The inner product of A with lambda squared
A with lambda, sometimes incidentally the inner product is called the overlap
It's a measure, if we say that orthogonality is complete distinguishability
Or unique in the complete distinguishability
Then a lack of orthogonality represent to some extend the inability
to make the clear distinction between two states
Ya, alright, so this is, question?
>> I'm surprised to see lambda is represented as a vector
>> because it's a value
No, no, alright the notation is every eigen value is associated with a eigen vector
I will just write E vector
The notation is the vector labeled by lambda
is the eigen vector associated with the eigen value lambda
That's a good point, you know, the problem we are trying to be a pure about notation
is that the notation get very complicated
It get so complicated, it get difficult to read,
too many indices, too many different letters you have to use
So, ya, sometimes we use slightly excuse the word bastardize notation
Or where we conflate a symbol for a vector, with the symbol in this case for a eigen value
Okay, so that's the probability principle or Born's rule
And just look at it for a minute
You ask why the square of the absolute value?
Well in general, this overlap is neither positive nor even real in general
Overlaps between two vectors are not necessarily real, in fact
They are generally not, we are talking about a complex vector space
And if the component of a vector is complex
In general in a product that would not even be real, let alone positive
On the other hand, the square of the absolute value of the square,
Square of the absolute value of the inner product, that is real
It's not only real, it's also positive
So this has a chance to be a candidate for the probability
Whereas the inner product itself doesn't
The inner product itself is called the probability amplitude
The probability amplitude is a thing that you square
in the sense of absolute value to compute a probability
Needless to say, the justification for this principle in the end
is experiment
On the other hand, you could ask how much can I bent them
And still make physical sense out of prediction
The answer is nobody has ever found a way
to change the rule of quantum mechanics
and still preserve a reasonably logical structure
So you eventually get familiar with these principles
>> Which of these principles took you from several possible outcomes
>> to one actual outcome?
Well, okay, if <A| is an eigenvector of L, if it is
If the state, starting state of a system happens to be an eigenvector of L
Then it would only have an inner product of one of the eigenvectors
Right, so that's again, it's a good question so
>> If you say that L lambda can't equal to...(inaudible)
Ya, ya, that's right
>> Excuse me, what if lambda is an eigenvalue for multiple eigenvectors?
Ya, still the rule is the same, but right
I will give you two answers
The first answer is don't worry about the case
with the eigenvalue maybe the same
Because it's very special, but that's not good enough, let me...
Let me say what the right answer is
The right answer is if you want the probability for a given value of lambda
and there's more than one eigenvector with the same value of lambda
Then you add them, you simply add the sum of the square
of the probability addition
The question, they are really good
>> What about the case <A| has overlap...
Yeah, yeah, then you take the sum of the square of them
You take the sum of the square of them
If there're several different eigenvectors all with the same eigenvalues
First of all you make them perpendicular to each other
You can always make them perpendicular to each other
No no, even if they are the with the same eigenvalues
The theorem, let's go back to the theorem
The theorem says that the eigenvectors with different eigenvalues
are orthogonal
It doesn't tell you anything about the eigenvectors to the same eigenvalue
That's supposing you have two eigenvectors with the same eigenvalue
Then it's also true that any linear combination of those two vectors
is also a eigenvector with the same eigenvalue
For example, let's suppose lambda, lambda 1 and lambda 2,
Now these are not two different values of lambda
These are the same value of lambda but two different eigenvector
Maybe we should write it like this
Lambda 1 and lambda 2, two different eigenvectors
Both exhibiting the same eigenvalue
Then you can take any... what that means is
L on lambda 1 equals lambda times lambda 1
L on lambda 2 equals lambda lambda 2
Multiply this by any complex number alpha
This one by any complex number beta
And add the two equations
What you find is that L on the linear combination
The linear sum of alpha lambda 1 plus beta lambda 2
is equal... on this side now you have lambda
times the same thing as in the bracket here
Another word if you have two eigenvectors with the same eigenvalues
You can add them with arbitrary coefficients and they remain eigenvectors
Now given two distinct vectors, given two distinct vectors
and all the possible linear combination of them
You can always find perpendicular combination
If you got this one, you got this one, now you can always add them
Or subtract them with coefficient to make them perpendicular
So the rest of the theorem is that if the two eigenvalues are the same
You have the freedom to choose two eigenvectors which are perpendicular
Which are orthogonal
In the end of the day, to summarize the theorem
It's that given the Hermitian operator, it's eigenvectors can be chosen
So that they form a base, so they are ortho-normal
perpendicular to each other and normalized
Okay, so where were we
That was an interruption, but I don't remember where it was
That's the problem with the interruption
>> we just finished Born's rule
Yeah, so we were talking about Born's rule
Right oh, good, okay, so now if you happen to have several eigenvector
Let's say lambda 1 and lambda 2
Both with the same eigenvalue,
then you construct the overlap of the state vector with lambda 1,
you construct the overlap of the state vector with lambda 2
you square this one, you square this one, and you add them
another words, you simply add the probabilities for the two possible ways
that you can get the same lambda
Just the sum of the probability, thank you Henry, way to late
I already got Oreos
But my wife would say this is probably healthier than Oreos
Right? You got Oreos?
Loud and clear
>> Can we say that the reason why those things are square regardless
>> whether they are complex or not is sort of the probability adds to one right?
Yes, uhm, we know it's the sum of the square of these things which add up to one
For normalized states, for normalized vectors, that's right
I'm not sure which one implies which, but clearly they fit together very nicely, good
Okay,
>> question? Is it possible to get an unambiguous result?
>> on an unprepared experiment?
I'm not sure what an unprepared experiment means
But I think what you are asking is, supposing somebody gives you a spin
And they don't tell you anything about how they prepare it
They just say here it is, I give it to you, I tell you nothing
Then it is not possible to find an experiment which has an unambiguous answer
Another good point
Okay, now, now we need to come to a new idea and a new question
In classical mechanics, all of these, the whole stories here
were summarized when I show you a heads and tails
Those are two possible state of a simple system
I didn't talk about measuring it, you know
It's also obvious that we didn't have to
Because we know that measuring is doesn't do very much to a system
You measure, but it doesn't change much to a system in any way
Here we come to much more complicated story
But the story up till now it's really the quantum mechanic analog just specifying
That you have a collection of state
The next question we ask was how to state change with time
That we call in the classical case dynamical laws of motion
Or dynamical laws of nature, whatever
The rules for how a state changes
If you remember there was an example the coin
The simple example would be put the coin down and rule is nothing happen
It just stay the same way, whatever it's attribute
Another possible law is, in each interval of time
We have a stroboscopic time we can imagine
And each individual time if flips
Heads, Up, heads tails heads tails
That's perfectly good law
We talked about the concept,
the same concept in the context of a die with six phases
Or any number of phases including continuous infinity
Same basic idea, the laws of physics are updating from instance to instance
Of a configuration, I will tell you what a configuration changes
And if you have a good law, in classical physics it's deterministic
It will tell you how the state changes, but also another rule
Another rule we call reversibility
Reversibility was basically just the idea that the state don't run into each other
The states which are distinguishable namely, different
Heads and tails are distinguishable,
two states which are different will evolve mathematically and stay different
That's the idea of reversibility
And when it comes down to, it's exactly that if you know the state at any instance
You not only will know what comes next
But you also will know what change before
Because there is no chance that the states run together
And two different states giving you the same outcome
Then you wouldn't be able to tell where you came from
So reversibility is the idea we also call the information conservation
And I suspect that I refer to it as minus first law
Minus first because it comes before everything else
Quantum mechanics also has a rule of reversibility and information conservation
You can call it the minus first law
But it comes down to the same thing, the state which are distinguishable
In the sense that I said, there exist an experiment that uniquely distinguish them
Stay, distinguishable
So now I wanna talk about how states evolve with time
We gonna come back and discuss this in the context of a spin
The simplest system of quantum mechanics
It's a good idea to get it all down for that, but let's talk about it more generally
Okay, here is the postulate, the postulate is that if you have a system
Add time, add some specific time let's call it a time zero
And I'm going to start changing my notation for states
Instead of calling them A and B, I'm going to start using a notation
Which is more or less the standard notation in quantum mechanics
Call them Psi, Psi is a Greek letter
And Psi is the commonly used letter to represent the state of a system
Now the state of systems do change with time
So you have to think of these, these vectors as being function of time that evolve
So let's put that in here in the following way,
The Psi of t simply represent a state which changes with time
Which state? It could be any state,
it's not the same after a certain time as it were to begin with
But we are following one specific state of the system which have been prepared
And then allowed to evolve, by whatever means things evolve
Alright, the postulate is, the Psi of t can be obtain from Psi of zero
This means time zero, by an operation on Psi of zero
A unique definite operation which is governed by the law
By the quantum mechanical laws for that system
So we have to do something to the vector so it doesn't stay the same
So let's represent what we do by the operation of some kind of operator
Now incidentally we didn't have to start with time of zero
We could have start with time of something else and evolve by an amount t
So this t here really represents that time of evolution from the initial state
To the final state, not necessarily final, but the state of some time
The basic postulate, two basic postulate, the first is that U is a linear operator
U is a linear operator and the same U for any state, whatever the initial state is
You put that here, and you hit it with the same U,
this is called a time development operator
It's a linear operator, and it evolve with the state from one instance to another
You could try to ask what would happen if you make a more general hypothesis
For example you might have a hypothesis that U depends on the initial state
Or you might have the hypothesis that
U was an operation but not a linear operator
Some other kind of operation, you can try it,
you will very shortly run into big troubles with all kind of things
It's been tried, I guarantee you it has been tried and again
repeatedly ever so often, some physicist will try to invent something
And then some other person would come along and say
Look , that has a trouble of locality, and the trouble with causality
It has trouble with probability interpretation
You are free to try, I've given up trying, I actually never tried
Right ,okay, so U is the linear operator
With all the rules for linear operators
But one other thing and that's this idea of conservation of information
Or conservation of distinguishability
That if you have two states, two different states of the same system
And you evolve them, let's call phi of t, alright capital Phi
That's given by the same U of t, the same operator times Phi at time zero
Then, if Phi to begin with, is orthogonal to Psi
Another words if they are physically distinguishable to begin with
Then they will remain orthogonal for all time
>> on the left and ...(inaudible)
say that again?
>> The Greek letters are upper case on the left and lower case on the right
>> is that just?
Because I'm sloppy
Alright so orthogonality breeds orthogonality
Physically distinct states evolve into physically distinct states
Distinguishability remains intact,
it's the immediate analog of the minus first law of classical mechanics
So let's see if we can find out what it says
Oh, incidentally it's very easy to prove from that
What does it say? It say if Psi and Phi were initially orthogonal
If they are initially orthogonal
If, then, don't ask me to use capital letter, it's much quicker to use lower case one
I mean capital here, I mean upper case
Then, this is true and it remains true for all time
It's an easy exercise I will leave it to you to prove that if orthogonality is preserved
That you can say a stronger thing
It's implied by this, you can say if you take any two vectors
which may or may not be orthogonal
The inner product between them stay constant with time
That' s a nice little trick, if you take any two vectors
You expand them in base vectors,
then you assume that base vector remains orthogonal with time
Then you can prove that
the inner product of any two vectors is time independent
So it follow from the orthogonality, the evolution of orthogonality
That the inner product between two states, remain
the overlap between them remains the same
It's essential that the overlap between two states
is of course a measure of their similarity
And what it says is the degree of similarity remains the same
Okay let's see if we can figure out what that means for you
What it says, let's rewrite this by plugging in Phi of t and Psi of t
The product U times Phi and U times Psi
But before we do, we have to remember that we have to flip this equation
oops, it's chocolate? Yeah this is chocolate
We have to flip it with a ket vector to a bra vector equation
So let's do so, this is Psi of t equals Psi of zero, not times U
But times what? U dagger, the Hermitian conjugate
Not the complex, it's related to the complex conjugate of the Hermitian conjugate
So now we plug this into this equations here, and what it says?
Let's write it out, a little bit of a eraser,
for arbitrary state don't have to be orthogonal
Whatever they are , they have some inner product that's equal to Psi of zero
U dagger of t, U of t, Phi of zero
All I've done is plug in, for Phi, U of t, Psi, U dagger of t
Now the product U dagger times U is another operator
What is the product of two operators
Because we didn't talk about this,
But the product of two operators are two very simple concept
You take a linearly operator, and you apply it to a vector
And then you take the result , and you apply another operator to it
The process of repeatedly applying two operators gives you an operation
Which is called the  product of the two operates, so that's what this is
First you hit Phi with U and then you hit the result with U dagger
And what this said that for any Phi and Psi
Any Phi and Psi at all, that when you plug in here
U dagger and U, the product of U dagger and U
You get something which is exactly the same as have you not evolve the state
The inner product stays the same, oops, I think I've make an mistake
One of these should be Phi right?
Alright so that's a principle of conservation of overlap if you like
Alright so here's the theorem we don't need this
This is again very very easily prove by going to a base
Very easily prove, if the matrix element, it's called the matrix element
So the product like this, if this equation is true for any pair of vectors
Here we go, I will write the theorem in general
If you have an operator, let's call it K, for U dagger U
For any pair of vectors Psi,  is equal to
For any pair of vectors, whatever
It follow that K is a unit operator
The unit operator is a operator which does nothing,
just gives you back the same vector
So what follow then, U dagger times U must be the unit operator
That's the content of conservation of overlap
U dagger of t for any t, times U of t, is equal to the unit operator
Reading, a unit operator that does nothing
Just gives you back the same vector
>> Questions? Can you say that one of the infer from the other
>> Is the Matrix (inaudible)
Yes you can, yes you can, indeed
I will examine these for a little bit now
In particular let's examine for a very very small time
A very small time, another words
if you only evolve the system by a tiny little incremental time
Let's call the incremental time epsilon right?
Let's write that U of epsilon, now first of all what is the U of zero?
No time evolution at all, just one ,just the unit operator
So for very small epsilon, U must be itself close to a unit operator
Plus a small deviation presumably have order epsilon
That would be right, it would be a order epsilon
so it will be something of order epsilon times another operator here
I'm going to make use of freedom with all that I have
I'm going to put a minus sign here, we are gonna put an operator over here
This minus sign has no content yet
I'm gonna say the operator over here, the minus sign
You know, just absorb in the definition
I'm also gonna put an i here,
Again there's no content yet, because I haven't told you anything about H
H is some operator, epsilon times H is just some operator
And i times epsilon and H is just an operator
So I have not really say anything other than a small epsilon
The operator U is close to the identity, how close? Of the order epsilon
And then there maybe additional things of order epsilon square epsilon cube
But we are gonna drop that, and study this equation
Or we should give a name to this equation here
Or more specifically we should give a name to the operator
which satisfy this rule
U dagger times U is equal to one
Or as we said that U dagger the Hermitian conjugate of U is the inverse of U
Such operators are called unitary
U is a unitary operator, so this is again
This is a restatement of the principle of conservation of overlap
Let's now apply this equation, this condition, to U of epsilon
See what we find out about H
So let's bring it over to this blackboard
U epsilon is equal to one minus i epsilon H
I will do it over here
What about U dagger? U dagger is the Hermitian conjugate
The Hermitian conjugate of 1 is just 1
But then we have complex conjugate plus i epsilon
And then we have Hermitian conjugate H
So here is U dagger, and here is U
And now let's multiply them together, and set the result equal to one
To order epsilon, to order epsilon
Okay, so what do we have, we have U dagger is one plus i epsilon times H dagger
Times one minus i epsilon H that has to equal 1
And now just expand it out to all the epsilon one
Plus i epsilon H dagger minus H equals one
As I said, the approximation the epsilon is so small
that the square can be completely ignore compare to order epsilon
Okay, so the ones canceled
And basically what we find is H dagger minus H has to be zero
It cancel out the ones, we get zero on the right hand side
And so to order epsilon, H has to equal H dagger
This is the condition that H be Hermitian
Now I didn't call H to be Hermitian
I call the H for something else, I call the H for Hamiltonian
What it has to do with the Hamiltonian of classical mechanics
will eventually become clear
The Hamiltonian for classical mechanics also introduced
to the equations of how system evolves from one instance to the next
But of course that's not a good enough reason to call this Hamiltonian
We will have to see the introduce equation of a way
very very similar to the way of Hamiltonian in classical mechanics
It is also to think, this is Hermitian right?
That means that if it's an observable
It could be an observable
Is it the Hamiltonian operator? It could be an observerble, an Hermitian observable
It's the Hamiltonian, it's the energy
Hamiltonian and energy are the same, this is what the energy of a system is
It's the Hamiltonian which generate the evolution of the state vector
According to this rule here, ya
It could be any Hermitian operator at the moment
Now what determine what Hermitian operator you put there?
Well it can be, it can be any Hermitian operator
associate with a system you study
For studying a system with one spin, we want to make it up out of
a operator associate with a spin
So it can be any operator
But it's either experiment, it's the same thing which
govern how you choose Hamiltonian or Lagrangians in classical mechanics
Either experiment, some prejudice about the way things works
Some symmetry principle, whatever you have that might give you a clue
to what H is
At the end of the day you may have to resort to experiment
to find out whatever it is
Okay, so that's right
So now, let's rewrite our equation, let's rewrite, question?
>> So when you do that expandsion of the, normally the H is a constant
>> You don't do that on first quarter, so this H would be...
H is not a constant
>> I mean it's not a function of time in that case
Okay, the situation with possible explicit time dependence with H
is the same as in classical physics
In classical physics, H can depend on time
For example, if you have a particle moving in a magnetic field
And the strength of the magnet has been vary with time
by changing the current to the electric magnet
Then the Hamiltonian for the particle moving in the magnetic field is time dependent
Otherwise if you have the parameter of the problem are not vary with time
Then you say the Hamiltonian is not time dependent
This is exactly the same, exact
>>(inaudible)
Ya, ya, that's right, that's right
In principle, H could be a function of time
Let's take the case where it's not, what that correspond to
is the situation with parameters of the problem are not time dependent
Whereas in classical physics we call time translation invariance
Remember classical physics, so time translation invariance
Which means like every time is the same as every other time
Okay, you do the experiment, the same experiment at a later time
will have the same output as the identical experiment in a earlier time
The statement of that principle, time translation invariance
It's that H does not have explicit dependence on time
Just an operator which doesn't depend on time
As I said, you can imagine a situation where you ramping up current
in a electro magnet, or the universe is expanding, or god knows what
There are some explicit time dependent, then H can be time dependent
Now do you know what happen with time energy conservation
if the Hamiltonian is time dependent?
Down the drink, same thing here
If the Hamiltonian is time dependent,
we haven't yet seen why there might be a conservation of energy,
we will come to that, but
Alright, so let's come back then, to this equation over here
>> What happens to the lon thing?
>> This is the lon for certain
Say that again?
>> This is for the infinitely small thing?
Yeah, we will come to that, basically we just multiply them together
We will come to that, okay, or you can think of it another way
If you updated by a small amount of time,
you just do it again and again and again
You just do it repeatedly, but we can use this to derive
a differential equation for the way state change with time, let's do that
Let's do that, okay, let's look at the state of a system at a time epsilon
And this time epsilon could be thought of
as time epsilon right after some arbitrary time
which I'm gonna call zero, but it doesn't matter
Psi epsilon is equal to one minus i H epsilon
minus i H epsilon times Psi, let's say it times zero
Another way to say it, it's that Psi of epsilon minus Psi of zero
This is a small incremental change in the state vector
That's equal to minus i epsilon operation by H on Psi
Now as I said, this zero here doesn't have to be zero
It could be any time as long as epsilon is an epsilon unit after the starting time
Okay, let's divide this equation by epsilon
You are allowed to do this because you can multiply vectors by numbers
So we just multiply both side by one over epsilon
One over epsilon times this whole thing
Okay, so what's this thing on the left hand side?
One over epsilon times the difference of two things
which, by which, at two slightly different times
That's just the time derivative of this vector
We haven't talked very much about taking derivatives of vectors
But it's clear you could do that
You can take the difference between two vectors
that's perfectly well defined
They would be close to each other if epsilon is small
If you divide by the small epsilon,
you would get something which is on the right hand side
It's just the time derivative of Psi
The time derivative of Psi equals minus i H Psi
At any given time, it doesn't, as I said, it doesn't have to be at time zero
At any given time, if you want to find out how the state of the system
changes over a incremental time interval, this is your equation
Completely analogous to the way you update classical systems
But because knowing the state vector is not the same as
knowing the values of the experimental outputs of the experiment
You can know the states but still there could be ambiguity or uncertainty
on the value of the experiment
This tells you how states change but it doesn't tell you
how the result of experiment change
The experiment were also experiment as still statistical
but with a continuously updating state vector
Okay this is, this equation have a name
Name of this equation is the generalized time dependent Schrodinger equation
This is the general form, this is the Schrodinger equation
Specific version which Schrodinger wrote down
was a very specific version of this
We are gonna come to that later, and of course
But this is the general idea, the rate of...
I don't need to say it again, this is what it is
But of course in order to use it, you have to know what H is
>>Question? So all of this depends on the irreversibility of the system
>>Is that right?
Yeah, or the conservation of the inner product, ya
>> How is that rationalized when you take the up vector with the down vector
>> you measure them along the horizontal axis
>> this sort of end up ...(inaudible)
Alright, that's a good question
You have to remember when you do that, you intervening with an apparatus
In order to follow the system, under those circumstances,
you have to include the apparatus as part of the system
You can not interact to a system and not include the things
which are interacting with it in the system
Classically, it's not such a bad sin
But quantum mechanically of something
interacting with the system strongly enough to affect it,
or strong enough to measure it
You have to include it as part of the system
Now this is the way a system evolve
If it's isolated and completely not in contact with anything else
We will have to come back to ask how it evolves
What happens when you put it in contact with a measuring apparatus
We will have to have a model for how measurement take place
But this is the way the system behave if nobody disturb it
during the course of the evolution from time zero to time t
We will have to come back to that
It's an important question
Oh boy, yeah, really just two assumptions
Well, maybe three,
First is the time evolution takes place by a linear operator call U
And the operator is independent of the state that it's acting on
Okay? With me?
That's the first statement,
and the next statement is that inner products are conserve with time
And that tells you U is unitary
From that ,we went over to here, and discover that
for a small little incremental change is governed by a Hermitian operator
So we get to the idea of the Hamiltonian
And then we just rewrote that, and say that, look
The small little incremental change could be thought of as
one over epsilon times the time derivative of the state vector
Okay so, this is the Schrodinger equation
How do you solve the problem
if it's a long time interval not a short time interval?
You basically solve this equation
I will talk about how you solve this equation, we will do so
There are lots of example, but okay
Alright, to go on, and explain what this has to do with classical mechanics
What it has to do with the corresponding concept in classical mechanics
We need a couple of ideas of,
by how you relate classical ideas to quantum mechanical ideas
We need the idea of what it's called the expectation value of an observable
It's a bad name, it's a bad name because the expectation value was defined
may have very little to do with what you expect the experiment to give
This doesn't have much to do with quantum mechanics,
this just have to do with the probability theory
I think I've talked about it before
But I will just remind you, if you have a probability distribution which looks like this
Then the least likely answer that you can possibly get is right over here
It's also the expectation value, so it's a poorly chosen terminology
The right terminology should have sometime, some fancy people
I won't name, Mary Youman, but some fancy people
like to call the expected value was even less the expected value then it is the expectation value
It's the average value, this is average value, and
the average value is something could be a value the thing can't even pick on
The possible value it could not even have
The average value for example, if you assign head to plus one
and tails to minus one, and you flip the coin, what's the average?
Zero, but you can't get zero,
so it's got nothing to do with the expected value of an experiment
But nevertheless, it's called the expectation value
And we will call the expectation value, what's the average value?
Let's talk about the average value of a observable giving a particular state
So our state is A, I said I was gonna change the sign but
sometimes I will sometimes I won't
>> expectation value
>> I think I just have to clear my head of statistic
>> but with that picture you draw, I assume it's a frequency distribution
>> So to me, the middle is not the average
>> but really is the expectation value is the value occur most frequently
No, no, definitely not, this one here?
It never occurs, never, ever ,ever
Let's even make it worse
>>Okay, what do the x and y axis represent?
>>I keep seeing
P is the probability and x is some variable
Something that you measure, this could be a probability of finding a particle
with different location, okay?
Alright, it could be, after some particular state
The probability, let's make it symmetric about the origin
It could be the probability distribution looks like this
I meant to make this symmetric
And it's really very very zero in the neighborhood of the origin here
There's no sense in which x equal zero is 'expected'
You can do the experiment for ever and ever and ever again
and you will not get x equal zero
You will either get an x somewhere around here, or here
So to call it the expected or the expectation value
It's a sort or misnomer
It is the average value, defining average in a very particular way
Now, for many many smooth probability distributions
And particular probability distribution don't have big holes in them
Something like this I would like to say
It can very often be the case and very often is the case
That the probability, that the average value is the most likely value to get
>> Is this the (inaudible), what is the peak?
The peak there is the most likely value
Yes, by definition the top of the peak is
And in many many cases, if you have nice simple probability
Gaussian probability, you know , bell shaped curve and so forth
Then the expectation value or the average value
is usually quite close to the average and peak value
because they are usually close to each other
But certainly there could be violent exceptions
The coin or the spin which can only be plus one or minus one and never zero
The expectation value and the average value are quite different
Okay, that's just a little sermon to give me a chance to beat my friend Mary Youman
>> Question, if you think the spin were the apparatus perpendicular
>> then in 70 percent if you are very unlucky, you get a million up-s in a roll
>> the average would be up, but that's not accurate
Ya, well, it depend on what you mean by an average
There's a notion of average which is strictly mathematical
I'm gonna write it down in a minute
There is a unwritten law which I think, is safe to say nobody really understands
It's the law of the large numbers
That if you do a thing enough time, how many times? I don't know
If you do a thing enough time, you do an experiment enough time
The average gotten by averaging the result of your experiment
will be equal to the average defined mathematically to within what?
To within the margin of error
What is the margin of error? It's a specific number
Does it really mean every time you do it, the answer would come out
within the margin of error? No
Alright, so, we are assuming standard probability theory
That if you do a thing enough
Plus this extra little ingredient
This extra physical assumption
I don't even know what to call it
That if you repeat an experiment enough times
The average of your data would be the mathematical average
Can anybody prove that? No
That's a law of large numbers
No, no, no, there's nothing you could do to prove it
The reason you can't prove it, is because sooner or latter some where in the multiverse
Somewhere there's gonna be an exception to it
No matter how many time you do it, a zillion time, a zillion numbers
It's not infinity, a zillion is one with the logarithms with a zillion of zero after
Or something like that
If you do an experiment, and opt for repetition of it
Eventually somewhere some place there is gonna be a violation of it
It is closely connected to the second law of thermo dynamics
You know there was a principle, a second law of thermo dynamics says
That the entropy never decreases
Boltzmann was never able to prove that and finally realize the right law is
the entropy probably never decreases, except when it does
Which is rarely, except when it does
So I'm not going to try to give you an explanation of
why probability theory works
This is to me very puzzling, but we will assume probability theory works
The statement that it works is the same as the statement that
the average of your data will be, for big enough experiment,
would be the mathematical average
Alright, let's come over to this side here
First just say, supposing we have a collection of a,
we have a probability distribution for some variables
Let's say for lambda, lambda, one of the eigenvalue
By measuring the eigenvalue of L
Supposing we have a probability for lambda, here it is
The other thing I call prob of lambda, Probability for lambda
Lambda can take on a whole bunch of different values
Lambda sub ii, let's call them
So this becomes the probability for lambda sub i
Then the average, the definition for the average is the sum over i
Of lambda i times the probability for lambda i
That's the definition of the average
And we will represent the average by the symbol, the bracket symbol
Why it's labeled by a bracket symbol, we will come to it
Okay, but that's the definition, the standard probability theory definition
of the average of a quantity
The quantity times the probability the quantity takes on that particular value
Sum over i, as I said this is the standard definition of average
Okay, what is the average in a state A of the observable lambda
So let's say A is expanded in a bases, which bases?
The bases of eigenvectors of L, alright?
Remember L is the Hermitian operator
It's eigenvectors form a bases
It could expand vectors in ortho-normal bases
So let's write this in the form alpha sub i summed over i
lambda sub i, remember the lambdas are orthonormal bases
What is the probability lambda in the state i?
Probability for lambda i is equal to alpha star i alpha i
Alright ? I maintain, this is the probability and the average of lambda
Let's call the average of lambda is summed over i
Lambda sub i alpha i star alpha i
All I've done is plugged in
Let me prove that this is the same thing as taking the vector A
bra vector A and sandwiching between the bra vector A and the ket vector A
The operator L, the operator L is the operator whose eigenvalues are lambda
Let's see if we can prove that, it's actually quite easy
All we do is, let's just plug in
Let's come to another blackboard and plug in
And let's see if we can prove that
Alright, so let's calculate this creature over here
A is the summation, and let's use also the bra vector A is
the summation over i of lambda sub i alpha star i
Alright so make a sandwich
The sandwich is the sum over i and j, why there are two sums?
One for the bra and one for the ket
Lambda sub j, alpha star j, this is the bra vector A
And then we put L there, and then we put the ket vector alpha i lambda i
It's pure plug in-ology
Now, what is L when it act on lambda sub i?
Lambda sub i are the eigenvectors of L
So when L act on lambda sub i
This left sum ij, lambda j, alpha star j alpha i
And now L has lambda i and it gives us lambda sub i times lambda i
Now all this junk in here is just number, for each i and j
For each i and j this is just the number
So that means we approach the point to take the inner product
of lambda i with lambda j, what is that?
Right ,it's one or zero, depending on whether i equals j or not
Given that, this sum, this double sum collapses to a single sum
In which lambda i and lambda j are identified
And it just become sum of i, lambda i, well, okay
Let's cut through some of the steps
If j is not equal to i, you got nothing
If j is equal to i, the inner product is just one
So this just becomes the sum over i, alpha star i alpha i lambda i
Which is exactly what we have over here
So we've prove the relationship here
That the average of any observable is just the sandwich bra-ket
A bra-ket, a bra-ket may sandwiching L, the observable between the bracket
The same bra and ket, the bra and ket associated with the state of the system
That's where this notation of a bracket comes from
Okay that's a good thing to know, if you want the average of a quantity
Just sandwich it between the bracket, the bra-ket representing the state
Any questions about that?
Okay, I'm gonna tell you what I'm gonna do
What we are going to do is we are going to try to find the equations
governing the time evolution of this average values
The idea is under suitable reasonable circumstances
If the probability distribution are nicely shape
That they have a bell shape curve
that by calculating the time evolution of averages
You are doing something pretty close to what classical physics
would instruct you to do, about calculating the equations of motion
of classical systems, the way average tend to evolve with time
as I said, under suitable circumstances,
follows equations which will
very very much like the corresponding classical equations
So our next goal is to try to find the rules
for the time evolution of these average values, expectation values
That's not so hard, we have all the equipment we need to do that
And let's see if we can do it
Fine, so at any given time, at any given time, the average of lambda
is given by Psi of t, the state vector at the time t
The operator L representing the observables times Psi of t
Another word, I just plug in the A, the actual time dependent state of the system
This is the average of L as function of time
I don't know, what should we call it
Let's call it, the average of L as a function of time
Again this is kind of a wrong notation, it's not the average of L of t
Is the average of L as function of time
We could, we could put the t outside the bracket
That's none standard, sub t
But why don't we just go with standard notations, standard notations
And remember, okay, I'm not gonna do it
I will just call it average L as a function of time, okay
As a function of time
It is a function of time, that's the main thing, function of time
We do something else, we could call that L bar
Another notation for average is just to put a bar on top of something
That's another notation for average, standard notation
Or we can just call it L bar of t
It means the average as a function of time
Let's do it that way, what would we like to do with this
We would like to find the equations of motions for it
Another words we would like to find how it changes with time
by differentiating with respect to time
I want to take this quantity and differentiate it with respect to time
So let's call it L dot, now we have bars with dots on top of them
L dar of t is the time derivative of this
Now L of t, that's just some fix operator
It's a fix definite operator, All the time dependence is in the state vector
The state vectors change with time, the operators, those are fix
Those are definite operators,
so let's see if we can take the time derivative of this here
The time derivative act on the side of t,
when you take the time derivative of a product
and this can be a product of vectors, it can be a product of numbers
It can be a product of functions, well functions
The rules are always the same, it's the time derivative of one times the other
Plus the time derivative of the other time the one
That's very general, so this is going to equal d Psi by d t, bra vector
L Psi plus Psi L d Psi d t
Oops, I've raise the very important equation, or else I bury it under the blackboard
And I write it over here, d Psi d t, is equal to minus i H Psi
That's what I was gonna stick in right over here
So we begin to see that the Hamiltonian is gonna tell us something
about how average values change with time
The Hamiltonians of classical physics tells us
how the correspondent quantities change with time
The Hamiltonian of quantum mechanics will tell us
how the average change with time
We are going to also need the bra version of this
So let's write the bra version of this
The bra version of it is d by d t of the bra vector Psi of t
is equal to plus i, plus i Psi H
H is Hermitian, so we don't have to Hermitian conjugate it
But we do have to change the sign of i, when we goes from bras to kets
And so now we are just gonna plug in
We are just gonna plug in and we will get L dot
L dot, okay, let's first do this one over here
This one is gonna be plus Psi, there's a minus sign
minus sign here, minus i Psi, L H, Psi
That's what we get from here, what about the other one
The other one is plus i Psi H L Psi
Or i times the expectation value, we have the Psi here
we have Psi here Psi here i times HL minus LH Psi
How about HL minus LH? Is that zero?
Why not? HL? Who cares about which way we order them?
Operators don't necessarily commute
Commute means that you can freely interchange the order of them
In general, this is true for matrices,
products of matrices don't necessarily commute
Sometime they do, and in particular an operator commutes with itself
L times L minus L time L that's okay, you can do it there
L times L minus L times L is zero, okay?
So is H times H minus H times H, but in general,
L times H is not equal to H times L
Maybe, but typically not
What is this animal called? H times L minus L times H?
It's call a commutator, so this is the definition, given two operators
Well, they could be just H now, the combination HL minus LH
is written with a square bracket, H comma L, and it's call a commutator
Commuting has something to do with passing freely between each other
Exactly what has to do with taking the subway of New York, I don't know
Let's call the commutator, and so what we have here
is the equation that the average of L at any given time
Sorry, the average of time derivative of the average
is equal to Psi, commutator HL, Psi
But this object over here is just the expectation value of commutator of H with L
So we can think of this as an equation relating
the time derivative of certain average to the average of another quantity
We could, I did, it's plus i, plus i
Or we can write L dot of t is equal to i, average,
times the average of the commutator HL
and I will indicate that by a bar on top of it
So we have a equation of motion now
The average in terms of averages,
if the probability distribution for everything are nice and peaked
Then we really can just say approximate nice and peaked
so the average is close to the highest point on the curve
And the curve is reasonably narrow, so the reason of amount of certainty
Then this basically says the time derivative of the classical
Or the time derivative of the approximate L of t
is equal to the approximate average of the commutator of H with L
So one writes, this of course is not quite right
but I will write it anyway, L dot is equal to i times commutator H L
Now this has to be taken with a little rain of salt
What it means is a equation among the averages
It means a equation among the averages
But it's often just written in this form
L dot is equal to H time L
Okay, now before we finish I want to remind you
of a classical mechanics equation of motion
It's the equation of motion represented in terms of Poisson brackets
Do you remember Poisson brackets? Good old Poisson brackets?
What was the Poisson equation of motion
Do you remember? And if you write d by dt of a classical function
And this could be a classical function of q-s and p-s
In classical mechanics there are q-s and p-s
L incidentally is the standard notation for angular momentum
This could be the angular momentum, but right now I'm just using it
to represent any observables
d by dt of L is equal to certain Poisson bracket
and the Poisson bracket is a Poisson bracket of L with the Hamiltonian
Remember that? Probably, some of you don't
As far as you could go, it's in the, this could be the electrical classical mechanics
the Poisson brackets, I will not introduce it here, I just remind you of it
And I want you to notice the similarity, where is it?
I think I erased it, the similarity of this with dL by dt
Average value i, minus i or plus i, Psi i times the commutator of H with L
Now incidentally, okay, let's just point out one thing
Poisson brackets have the property that if you interchange the two expressions
What happens to the Poisson brackets?
It just change sign, so do commutators
H L minus L H, if you interchange the order of them change sign
So we can also write this as minus L with H
Commutator of L with H, as a remarkable similarities
and it suggest that we identify the Poisson bracket with minus sign
times a commutator, now I've left out a discussion or something
I just realized it, just now, I completely forgot what happen to H bar?
What happen to H bar?
We've been working in units in which H bar is one
I've been working in units in which H bar plus constant is one
The question is if we were to reinstate Planck's constant and make it not equal to one
Where would it go in these equations?
And, what's it?
Yes it goes into Schrodinger's Equation, that's correct
But how do we trace it, let's see, how do we trace it?
Here's the equation, I told you H has significance as a Hamiltonian
Therefore it has a unit of energy
So let's look at this equation, sign cancels out on both sides
Just as far as unit goes
Unit of this side is the same as unit of this side
So the right hand side of the equation, apart from the sign has a unit of energy
The left hand side of the equation has a unit of inversed time
Inversed time and energy don't have the same units
Inversed time is inversed seconds, and energy is joule, so whatever
So we have an equation here which doesn't make good dimensional sense
We need a constant in here and the constant we have to put the constant in here
let's see where does the constant goes?
Does it go to the right hand side or left hand side?
Where does the Planck's constant go? Right hand side or left hand side?
What? >> Either
Well, if it goes in one place with one thing
it would go to inverse in the other place
So, here is all you have to know is that
Planck's constant has a unit of energy times time
So, let's see so energy times time, so we want to put Planck's constant here
Energy time times over time is equal to energy
That's where Planck's constant goes into these equations
I apologize for having completely forgotten about it
But that's where it goes, and if we follow through the equation
No doubt it appears over here
I think it appears in the denominator here
Let's see, I got everything right except when I have H I should have H over h bar
Let's rewrite it this way, H over h bar
So in all my equations, wherever we wrote H, the Hamiltonian
We really should have, if we want to keep the unit straight,
H over Planck's constant, and that goes straight to here
So really the right equation including the constants
is D L dt is one over h bar here
One over Planck's constant
Planck's constant is a small number
So this looks like it was very big
But in the other hand, this is L times H minus H times L
In classical physics, that would be zero
So whatever this is, classically zero, in quantum mechanics,
it must be a small correction to the classical physics
To extend that quantum mechanics is a small correction to the classical physics
And so the commutator is itself something which is typically small in the order of h bar
So that allows us then, to guess,
to guess an identification between commutators and Poisson brackets
Now I'm, this is none intuitive at the moment
It's just looking at the two equations, and say
Look is there going to be any connection
between quantum mechanics and classical mechanics?
Then there must be a connection between the Poisson brackets
And between the Poisson brackets and the commutators
Namely Poisson brackets must be equal to minus i over h bar times commutator
Or it's usually written in the other way,
commutator is i h bar times Poisson brackets
Commutator is a small thing because there is a h bar there
Poisson brackets in classical physics is not a small thing
It's a number, I mean it's some characteristic quantities
which is neither small nor big
And in the same unit, the unit that you do classical physics
Standard units, meters, seconds, whatever
Commutators are very small, that's because they are almost zero
A times B minus B times A is almost zero
Okay, no I don't think so, we have a minus i on this side
Minus i over h bar multiply by h bar
And now multiply both side by i
And use that minus sign, times plus i is one
It was Dirac who recognized the connections
and built his quantum mechanics out of it
He built his quantum mechanics out of making an identification of Poisson bracket
with commutators, but of course the foundation of the subject
quantum mechanics is a consistent subject
without having to make any reference to classical physics,
the right way to think about things is
quantum mechanics comes before classical mechanics
Commutators before Poisson brackets
You have to derive classical physics is an approximation to quantum mechanics
So here we see some formal similarities, at this point here
We have no idea why this commutator should have features
in common with a Poisson bracket
Before we go, let me just say, let me just write down
some of the features of commutators and of Poisson brackets
To remind you
And again all of this should be at this stage should be a little mysterious
Why is this funny connection between Poisson brackets?
But let's pursuit it anyway
Okay, I remind you about Poisson brackets
First of all if I have two quantities, I will call them A and B now
Or A and B that I used, what the hell?
I will just call them L and H,
it doesn't have to be the Hamiltonian and anything special
They are just L and H
Alright the first thing is, the Poisson brackets of L with H is equal to
minus of Poisson bracket of H with L
The commutator of L with H is minus the commutator of H with L
So that's a parallelism that we could begin with
Now let's take some other properties of Poisson brackets
There's a lot of properties of Poisson brackets
But let me just write one or two more
If I have two operators, or two of not operators
But two quantities, let's call them L and M, okay,
L times M is itself a classical quantity,
and I can compute it's Poisson bracket with H
Does anybody remember the answer?
I will remind you and tell you, look it up, this is important
L is a Poisson bracket of L with H times M
Plus L times a Poisson bracket of M with H
Now in classical physics the order multiplication doesn't matter
So you could bring the M on the left on the right it doesn't matter
You can bring the L on the left or right it doesn't matter
But this is the relationship for the product of two variables
The Poisson bracket, go back, go back to the last quarter lecture
And check this out, this is one of the defining
Not one of the defining, one of the properties of Poisson bracket
You can do the same, you can ask the same question over here
Supposing you have LM and you take it's commutator with H
What do you get? This is an exercise, this is an exercise
All you do is you write, that this is equal to LMH minus HLM
And now you start just juggling and
adding same term, subtracting the same term
And eventually you will discover that this is the same as this
Same relationship, this is equal to L times a commutator of M with H
Plus commutator of L with H times M
The way to do this is just write LMH minus HLM
And then write out this guys over here
This is L, MH, minus LH, M
Plus LH, M minus HL, M
Four terms here, two cancel in pairs, and you will just get this back
It's two one step thing , very easy thing
Okay, so you begin to see some pattern that Poisson bracket and commutator
must somehow be closely related
The last thing I'm gonna show you tonight is about energy conservation
Now we are not going to consider
the most general concept of energy conservation
We're simply going to ask, is the average of the energy conserve with time?
We have not even really got into
what it would mean for energy itself to be conserve in any deeper way
But we can ask we have all the ingredients now
Which would allows us to ask how is the average of
How is the average of any quantity changes with time
No, here it is over here, we can now specifically ask
how the average of the energy change with time?
Let's do it, the energy I claimed is Hamiltonian, or it's definition if you like
What is energy? It's Hamiltonian
So let's check and ask whether the energy is conserve
if energy is the Hamiltonian
This equation would read, the time derivative of the average of the Hamiltonian
is equal to minus i over h bar,
times the commutator of the Hamiltonian with itself
The Hamiltonian with itself is H times H minus H times H
H times H is the same as H times H
Quantum mechanics is not that weird, you know it's weird
But H times H is the same as H times H, so this is zero
Whatever the Hamiltonian is
It's average, it's average, it's expectation value with time is always zero
So it's conserve in that sense, at minimal that sense
There is stronger sense in which it's conserve, which we will come to it
But even in this weaker sense, it's kind of interesting and it tells us
on some kind of right track would be able to
compare quantum mechanics and classical mechanics
# Okay, I'm gonna stop now and take a few questions
>> the bar notation (inaudible)
Up here?
>> Is the bar notation mean average?
Probably, I just mean the average, I mean it's the average that define
define the summation of probability of lambda times lambda, okay
So I don't know what's the standard symbol in statistic or average in that sense
>> The first moment of the distribution you knew that
The first moment of the distribution, ya, okay,
I used to just calling it lambda
>> including brackets?
E bracket of lambda, that stands for what?
>> the average of expected value?
The expected value even though it's not the expected value
You never see the expected value as a bar on top of it?
>> I mean (inaudible)
Okay, ya, when I use the term average I will mean this
It's also call the expectation value,
and I will freely interchange the Dirac notation
for the average with the bar notation
And that's not, if that's not standard according to statistic books, too bad
>> So here you wrote down the Schrodinger equation
>> and then you wrote down the ...
>> How did you go to left hand equation to right hand equation?
>> Is that complex conjugation or Hermitian conjugation?
Hermitian conjugation, but remember H is Hermitian, we proved that
That was the condition of unitarity, that H is Hermitian
>> But how can you interchange the order of Psi H
>> but not d/dt with Psi?
Where, where, where, where, where?
>>On the left side of the equation you got d/dt with Psi
>>d/dt is the operator
This one here? >> Yeah
The time derivative of a bra vector is a bra vector
Look the time derivative is just another way of talking about difference
The difference of two bra vectors is a bra vector
The difference of tow ket vectors is a ket vector
And the limit difference becomes the time derivative
So the derivative of a bra vector is a bar vector
The derivative of a ket vector is a ket vector
If you want to take this ket equation
What is that bra that goes with this ket?
The bra, the dual of this ket is
the time derivative of the corresponding bra vector
It's just the think of this as taking the difference of two vectors
It's just the difference of two vectors
Alright, exactly
And again, quantum mechanics is weird,
but taking the difference of two vectors
and replace it by a derivative
when the difference is small, that's perfectly legitimate
>> (inaudible) energy conservation
Well, yeah
>>so we ignore this so far?
No
>> So why it is that energy
How come we getting to what ?
>> Energy conservation is, how do you know the energy is conserved?
Well, we don't know it's correspond with energy until we do a lot more
We don't know, we can find it to be energy Hamiltonian,
but that's not satisfying, we want to see in cases
where we understand the classical physics
And we understand what energy is
We are gonna want to see that the quantum mechanics of the same system
classical system is an approximation to the quantum mechanical system
Physics is really quantum mechanical
Under certain condition, such as the system is heavy
Basically heavy is big, large masses
Then the system behaves approximately classicaly
which means that the average values move in ways
which are consistent to what classical equations of motion
We are gonna want to see when we study such big heavy systems
That the thing we call quantum mechanical Hamiltonian
is essentially closely connected with the thing what we call classical Hamiltonian
But we will come to that, but we can't do all thing all in one night
At the moment, I'm just showing you similarities
And if you wanna do better than that
Whether we will actually get to do better than that I don't know
We can't do everything, but that's the logic
>> way back to the electron spin, I think you left off in the last lecture
>> You want to show the probability (inaudible)
Well, yeah, right, I've save some time to do that
but I think we've done enough for tonight
Who was it that send in this solution to the...
Yeah, well done, we will do it, but I just run out of steam
Right we will come back to that, we are gonna come back to that
>> So how can your postulate work with that without a collapsed postulate?
>> How can your postulate work without a collapsed postulate?
Well we really want to derive a collapsed postulate
The derivation is deeply connected with something else we have not come to yet
I think we will come to it next time, entanglement
The measurement process is really a process of
establishing entanglement between system and the apparatus
And until we talk about that, the entanglement process
I think until we do, we simply have to adopt the language of collapsed
But next time, next time, next time, remind me about collapsed
And course to collapsed, Okay
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu