Stanford University
Okay, tonight we are going to do a number of things
We are going to talk about uncertainty
We are going to talk more about the Schrodinger equation
The various version of the Schrodinger equation
We are gonna talk about how things evolve with time
We've talk about that some already
Let's see what else we have here, ya
We are gonna apply the Schrodinger equation idea to the evolution of systems
to our favorite little system of one spin,
but then if we have time, and I hope we will
I would like to move past the single spin
We have a general theory of quantum mechanics for which
I announced to what the basic rules were and the basic principles
Hermitian operators, observables, vectors are states, and so forth and so on
Orthogonal vectors means distinguishable
are very very general sets of principles
And So far we have applied it to one simple system
The simplest possible system in the world
We are not finished with it yet
But hopefully tonight or next time we would move on to the next simplest
Well no, it's the next to next simplest system
There is a simpler one in between, but two spins
Two spins is the next to next simplest system
Why do you think the two spins is the next to next simplest system?
As opposed to the next simplest
A spin has two states, how many states do two spins have
Two orthogonal states, four
So what happened to the state with three states
This is the number three state
You can imagine a system with three states that's the next simplest
So two spin is the next to next simplest, alright
Let's get on, first of all the concept,
I'm not going to do the mathematical uncertainty principal tonight,
but we should just talk a little bit about the fact that
there are observables, pairs of observables
which can not simultaneously be measured
The basic principal is that if you measure something
Then by the definition of a good measurement
you leave the system with the same value that you measured
Otherwise you couldn't confirm in the next round
You couldn't confirm what you have measured
So it's important that you leave the system at least
momentarily or instantaneously having the same value that you measured
The measurable quantities of a system
are the eigenvalues of the observables operators
The observed, the operators represent the observables
And the state in which the observables are definite
another words in which there is no ambiguities about them
The thing that you get after you've done a measurement of a certain quantity
is an eigenvector or the eigenvectors of the observables
Now supposing we have two observables
which could be simultaneously measured
if you measure, you could measure one
And it will leave it in the state with the same value
But you could also measure two things simultaneously
It doesn't matter, it could be one after the other
But let's just call it simultaneously, you made two measurements simultaneously
of two different things and you leave both of them in eigenvectors
of the quantities that were measured
Two distinct quantities, that must mean the state that you leave things in
are simultaneous eigenvectors of two, of the two distinct things
If you can measure things simultaneously,
it means basically that they have the same eigenvectors
Or that there exist a complete set of basis
basis are incidentally the term, somebody pointed out that the term basis
That I have been misusing it a little bit, that's probably true
I use the term basis to mean a complete set of orthonormal vectors
You need to say the word orthogonal
Quantum physicist tend to use it that way
I think in mathematics the notion of the basis
does not requires the vectors be orthogonal
It just requires them to be linearly independent
Alright that's not a big deal, I just point it out for you
I will use the term basis to mean
a complete set of orthogonal normalized vectors
The eigenvectors of an observable can be made
to be complete orthonormal basis
when I see It can be make to be, you do have ambiguity
What happens if there are two eigenvalues with exactly the same value
Then you have the ambiguity, you have to choose eigenvectors
But you can't choose them perpendicular
And if you have two distinct operators which can be simultaneously measured
and therefore simultaneously left an eigenvector of those quantities
It must mean that there is a basis,
a basis of vectors which are simultaneous eigenvectors of both quantities
Another words, there exist a basis if,
Let's call the two observables L and M
These are Hermitian operators, L and M
And it means that if L and M are to be simultaneously measurable
It must mean that there is a complete basis
basis of states, which are both simultaneously eigenvectors of L
and eigenvector of M
So that must mean that L on |i> equals
Let's use the notation for eigenvalues of L
Let's use the notation little l, little l sub i, instead of lambda
l sub i times |i>, that's the condition that |i> be an eigenvector of L
with eigenvalue l sub i
and at the same time the same set of state
must be eigenvectors of the m observable
so this must be true for a complete set of states
Now let's apply L and M in sequence
First L and then M, and then try the other way
And see what we get
So first, let's start on L on |i>, here we have it
But now let's take M multiplied by L and then hit the eigenvector |i>
Well from the first relationship here this is equal to M times l sub i times |i>
All I've down is plug in the first equation
But now l sub i, that's just number, that's a number
That's not even a matrix, it's just good old number, an eigenvalue
And that means we can write it as l sub i M times |i>
But now we know that M times |i> is just a little m
So what does this give, so this give us l sub i, m sub i times |i>
A product, okay that's not too surprising
|i> is a thing which can be measured, oh sorry
M and L are things can both be measured simultaneously
And if we multiply the two of them together as matrices, or as operators
They become another observable whose eigenvalues are just a product
But if we did it in exactly in the opposite order
LM on |i> we will get exactly the same thing
The order, these are just numbers,
so that the order you write them down doesn't matter,
l sub i times m sub i is the same as m sub i times l sub i
and so this is equal to the same thing, same thing
Now supposing you have two operators
which have exactly the same action on every member of a basis
That means they would have the same action on any superposition of vectors
Formed out of the superposition of base vectors
Another words, they would have the same action on any vectors
M times L and L times M have exactly the same action on any vector
And therefore M times L is equal to L times M, it's operators
So we prove the following theorems
That if two things are simultaneously measureable
The two observables or the
two operators representing those observables commute
L times M and M times L are the same
Or L time M minus M times L which is the commutator
Which is the commutator [L,M] must be equal to zero
You can prove a stronger form of this theorem
And it just go the other way
If you have two operators, I will leave these to you
If you have two operators which commute
Remember if you have two operators which commute
It means that you can find a complete basis of state
in which both of them simultaneously
in which the complete basis of state
are simultaneous eigenvectors of the two operators
As it goes, both ways, given that you have two things
which can simultaneously be measured
If follows that they commute, and if two things commute
It follows that they can simultaneously measure
They have complete set of common eigenvectors
So the condition then for things to be simultaneously measurable
is that they commute,
What if they don't commute?
In fact we already have some examples that things don't commute
Sigma x and sigma y and sigma z, no two of them commute
No two of them commute with each other
And therefore they do not have simultaneous eigenvectors
That's no surprise, we know that the eigenvector of sigma z are up and down
The eigenvector of sigma x or left and right they are the same thing
They are different, they don't, they are not proportional to each other
So there are examples of operators which don't commute
In fact we are gonna work out the commutation relation for them
They don't commute, in fact they don't commute
And that's an indication that you can not measure them simultaneously
That's the idea of uncertainty, the idea of uncertainty is
when you have two objects, two observables
Each of which you could decide to measure
And get the answer, you may not know what the answer is gonna be
It's statistical, but you can't measure them
After you measure them, be certain you can repeat the measurement
and find the consistency, each of them, but not both of them
In classical physics there is no such thing
If you can measure A and you can measure B
Then you can measure both A and B
And you can be certain about both of them
If you can be certain about either of them
So that's just, and we will come back to that uncertainty
And quantify it, um, there maybe states where although you,
Alright, we will come back to it
We want to quantitate a measure of the necessary degree of uncertainty
In measuring two things simultaneously, that's the uncertainty principle
But for the moment we have the idea and an explanation of
why there are uncertainties between observables in the first place
>> (inaudible) why they have to share
Well if you measure them, and you get answers for both of them
You have to leave the system in a state which an eigenvector
Either one of them, both of them
That's the rule, and when you measure something
It leaves it in a state of definite wetness
whatever that happens to be, which means an eigenvector
If you measure two things, if you can measure two things simultaneously
It must mean the state you leave it in is an eigenvector of both of them
Okay
Alright, let's come back now to the evolution of systems
As I said last time, I went back and look at the classical mechanics notes
And I realized that, and I have something like a fifty pages of quantum notes
The equivalent classically was how many pages in classical mechanics
A half, about a quarter of pages, just the statement
that states of a set of things you can write on the blackboard
So fifty pages to get to where classical mechanics
After about thirty seconds, and it is just the way it is
The next thing we did when we talk about classical mechanics
We talk about the state change with time
That took another page
Arrows going from one to the next so forth
Here is not so bad, it ain't gonna take us another 50 pages fortunately
In fact we have already lay it out
It took basically, I would say something like about five pages
Something in my notes, I think four or five pages, maybe a little more
So we are beginning to compress, and things are
Once you get the idea of state, the next is a little bit easier
Okay, so let's remind ourselves what we said about the time evolution
The Schrodinger equation,
the Schrodinger equation is the equation that governs the time evolution of systems
We began with the idea of conservation of distinction
Or conservation of distinguishability of states
The implications was the state which are orthogonal remain orthogonal
It was easy to prove from that, and I hope you've proved it
You should be able to prove it, that the U operator
I should have brought my own pens
The U operator, remember what the U operator is
If you want to know what a state is at a later time from a value at time zero
It stands for time zero
Then you apply a certain operation
It's more than just an operation, it's a linear operator
A linear operator U, and you get Psi at time t
U of course is a function of t
At later or the earlier if you want to project the vector forward
You put in different t-s here
And that was the basic equation
But then we require another ingredient
Another ingredient is that orthogonal states stay orthogonal
So for example if we have two orthogonal states
Let's call them for the moment i and j instead of Psi
i and j are orthogonal
In fact i and j might be members of an orthonormal basis
Let's take them to be members of an orthonormal basis
And then you allow |i> to evolve for a time
And you allow <j| to evolve for a time
The ket vector |i> becomes U, let's say U of t, times |i>
If you start with |i>, after a time it's U of t of |i>
<j| evolves with the Hermitian conjugate of U, <j
|245
And the assumption is that if |i> and <j| were orthonormal
U times |i> and U star times <j| are also orthonormal
So the way to say this is if  is equal to a Kronecker delta
Then this is also equal to a Kronecker delta
Another words, putting U and U dagger,
sandwiching them between orthonormal basis here
does not change the inner product, and from that you can conclude
Since this is true for any member of the basis
That U dagger U is just a unit operator
We did this last time, I know, unit operator
It does nothing, U dagger times U
Then we went on to another step
You said, aye, let's consider the evolution from time zero
to an infinitesimally short time later
So we are interested in let's call it U of epsilon
Where epsilon is a small time
And we argue, well first of all if epsilon was zero nothing happens
And say that nothing happens means that U is the unit operator
Alright so U of zero is just a unit operator, it does nothing
Just leave it to stay the same
We added one more thing, and that was a kind of continuity
I may not have spell it out
A kind of continuity and that was that U of a small time is close to the identity
Another words in a very small period of time
And the state doesn't change much
So that's the same as saying that U is equal to the unit operator
plus something small of order epsilon
And I used my freedom of definition
Just choosing definitions to write this as minus i epsilon times H
There was no content in that minus i times epsilon
I can just absorb it into H
I put it there in fact, had I really wanted to keep track of
all the interesting constants
I would have put an h bar over here
But this is all a matter of convention
Whether or not we include H bar, whether or not we include an i
Whether or not we include an epsilon
Is simply a definition of how, of H
We could have call this the whole thing K
And then said K is equal to i epsilon H, you know what I mean
I don't have to say it any more
Alright let's take away the H, and h bar and forget it anyway
It's unit, it's simply unit
We fit this, let's write another one U dagger of epsilon
is equal to one plus i epsilon H dagger
Dagger meaning Hermitian conjugate
Then we feed these two into the unitarity condition
And what do we find? We found that H minus H dagger must be equal to zero
That's what happen if you feed these two into the unitarity condition
Or another way to say it, is H is equal to H dagger
Or H is Hermitian
Now that's big news, why is that big news?
It means that H is an observable
It's something that we can measure
And we should be interested in it
What it is?
And of course the answer is, it's the not of course
But as I said last time, it's essentially
It is apart from the fact that Planck's constant
It is the Hamiltonian, what's it got to do with classical Hamiltonian?
We've talked about it a little bit, I will come back to it
But for the moment, it's just called the quantum mechanically Hamiltonian
It's a thing which in some way or another, not in a very clear way
generates time evolution
Incidentally you might think of this, alright, let's go on
We've run a little bit another step
It's okay let's write the equation, Psi of epsilon as purely viewed
Psi of epsilon is equal to Psi of zero minus i epsilon H Psi of zero
I just plug in for what U is
And then let's transpose the left hand side and divided by epsilon
Transposing to the left hand side make this the minus
Makes an equal sign here, and then divided by epsilon
It's the obvious thing to do
And what do we get on the left?
We get the time derivative of the state vector of the system
The time derivative of the state vector of the system
D Psi by D t is equal to minus i H Psi
So what H is, it's a rule for how you update the state of a system
If you know it at an instance of time then in the next instance of time
It's you make an incremental change in the state of a system
proportional to minus i H which times |Psi>
It's a little machine for telling you how you update the state of system
That sounds awfully deterministic,
it sounds awfully much like classical determinism
Classical determinism is also a set of rule for updating the state of the system
So in what sense the thing is not deterministic?
If you know how to change the state from one instance of time to another
We are not deterministic in the sense that
even if you know the state of the system
You simply don't know the result of every measurement
The knowledge of the state of a system in quantum mechanics
is not equivalent to the knowledge of the outcome of every experiment
What does it tell you the state of the system?
It tells you the probabilities
So this is basically a rule for updating probabilities
It's not a rule for updating knowledge, complete knowledge of the state of the
set of the experiment you could do
But in some sense or another, the state vector evolves
I don't want to call it deterministically
Because deterministically carries a package with it
But it evolves in a known and definite way
Now this is true but only if you don't interfere with the system
In classical mechanics you can interfere with a system arbitrarily gently
And not cause the, cause any changes in the way it is evolving
In quantum mechanics when you make a measurement
You necessarily disturb a system
So this is the evolution of the system of an undisturbed system that is not
in the process of being measure
>> What if the system happens to be
>> in eigen state when the measurement is made
Sorry, so what?
>> And you would not disturb a system
Well that's a special case, ya
You are right, you are right, that is if you, that's right
If it's in a special case of an eigen state of a system when you measure it
It doesn't disturb it
So right, so that is an exception to what I said
But generally speaking, the generic situation is when you measure something
You disturb something else about the system
This equation is the Schrodinger equation
Now it's sometimes call the generalized Schrodinger equation
The actual equation Schrodinger wrote down was a particular kind of a system
The motion of a particle
But has exactly this form
This first became known as the generalized Schrodinger equation
And people drop the generalized,
we now think of this as a form of the Schrodinger equation
And what it is? It's an equation which tell us how state change with time
It can be applied to the simplest system of a single spin
It can be applied to the second simplest and the third simplest system
And to system with arbitrarily complexity
This is the form that it has
Alright, that's, that's where we more or less work last time
Okay, let's erase everything but the Schrodinger equation
Actually this is called the time dependent Schrodinger equation
The time dependent Schrodinger equation is an equation
for how things change with time
There is also another equation
which is called the time independent Schrodinger equation
H is an observable, it correspond to the Hamiltonian, but
Hamiltonian is nothing but an energy, at least in classical mechanics
So in my respect that H is the operator
representing the observable energy of a system
Okay now we are gonna make a measurement of the energy of some system
How do we do it? Let's not worry about that
There is one way we can do it
With E equals mc squared and then we weight the system carefully
Really really carefully, and in that way determine it's mass, and it's energy
That is not a very efficient way to do it because the change of energy of a system
when you heat it up or something, it's so negligible but that's one way
There are many ways to measure energy
But one of the possible outcomes of the measurement of the energy of the system
That of course depends on the system,
it's not something you can ask and answer in general
But depending on the system, for example if you measure the energies of an atom
You get one of a, denumerable family of the possible answers
Namely the energy levels of the atom
If you measure the energies of a harmonic oscillator
Again you get a denumerable collection of possible answers
If you measure the energy of a particle moving in a none-closed orbit
Then in fact you get a continuous possible family of possible answers
So the question of what the energy are depends on the system
And it depends on the choice, of course it's not a choice
The system has a Hamiltonian, it's just not up to you
to dictate to a system of what a Hamiltonian is
It may be up to you to try to discover what a Hamiltonian is
But let's use the terminology you get to chose the Hamiltonian
Needless to say you get to study different possibilities
And depending on the choice of the operator that you put here
That you call H, you can get different energy levels
How do you describe, sorry, how do you calculate
and determine what the possible outcome of the energy measurement are
And use the statement that
the values of the energy can take on are the eigenvalues of the Hamiltonian
Like any other observables
So you write another equation, H on, let's call it the |i>
|i> now represent an eigen state of the energy
It doesn't represent any old basis
It represent in particular the fact, maybe we should indicate that
I'm writing in here the energy, the ith possible energy level
H on E sub i is equal to the eigenvalue E sub i
times the eigenvector associated with that energy
The notation is putting the E sub i inside the ket vector
Just means nothing more than this is a ket vector
which happens to be the eigenvector of H with eigenvalue E sub i
And how many such E sub i-s are there?
Well there is a complete basis of them
Whatever the dimensionality of a system is
Whatever the dimensionality of the space of state is
It's that many eigenvectors of the energy
And your job is a physicist of trying to find them
So that's the time independent Schrodinger equation
Next thing we did, a lot of review tonight
Next thing we did was to talk about the evolution,
time evolution of expectation values, average values
I complained bitterly about the terminology expectation values
But many many years ago I have given up on this
So it's become expectation value, but really it should be average
It's okay, I'm okay with expectation value
I will use expectation value, but it really should be average
And here is what we found
What we said is the thing that change with time is a state vector
So we are interested in calculating Psi of t
Remember the expectation value
I will just remind you the expectation value you get
By sandwiching the observable in a sandwich
between the bra version of the state vector and the ket version
We've proved this, we've proved this
This is the same as the average, the statistical average
And I won't go back over that now
This is the average value of L, the observable L
And we can ask how it changes with time
It change with time because Psi can change with time
And here we know how Psi change with time
This two factor of Psi here
So when we gonna differentiate this with respect to time
There will be two terms
One coming from differentiating this
And one coming from differentiating that
If you remember, if you flip from bra to ket you have to complex conjugate it
And a complex conjugating change the sign of i
You will come to the conclusion that this is equal to
Now I was getting the sign wrong
Let me try to get the sign right
I think it's minus sign, times L H minus H L
Average value of that, Psi, Psi
We work that out
We use the L on Psi gives you H on Psi
That's this piece over here
Now we use that L when it acts to the left
gives you a term with H acting to the left with a minus sign
Okay so here is what we find then
We find that the time derivative of the average of L
Let's write it this way
d by dt of the average of L
I will use that notation for the average of L as a function of time
is equal to minus i times
the average of the commutator of L with the Hamiltonian
If you know what the Hamiltonian is as an operator or as an matrix
And you know what L is as an operator or as an matrix
You can compute the expect... the commutator
Now if you compute the commutator you compute it's average value
Just use this rule, this sandwich rule, let's call it the sandwich rule
And it tells you the right hand side tells you what the left hand side
How it changes with time
If you find it odd it has an i there
Well I did it the first time I saw this
First time I saw this, I said wait a minute wait a minute
Time derivative of a real thing can't be imaginary
We are gonna find out that the commutator of real things are always imaginary
So imaginary will go away, we will give you some example and you'll see
this is not hard to prove, but we will do it by example
Sometimes this is written in short hand
The short hand is just the dL/dt
is equal to minus i times the commutator of L with H
But at least at this stage of our knowledge
What this means is it should always be sandwiched
and thought of as equation for the average value of things
So there we have what we call the Heisenberg equations of motion for the system
That brings us to the study of commutators
The study of commutators and I wanna go through that just again for a little bit
Commutators have some rule associated with them
The rules are very very reminiscent
of the rules of Poisson brackets
So go back and read about Poisson brackets
I will write down what the rules are,
general rules, algebraic rule of Poisson brackets in commutators
And I will just check, are they really true for both of them
Well the rules for Poisson brackets we did last quarter
Poisson brackets are written this way, A B,
I'm not gonna write them out
in terms of p-s and q-s in terms of classical mechanics
But there was a few simple rules associate with them
First of all there is some linearity rules
That if you add two operators, oh sorry
If you add two things and then take the Poisson bracket with a third
And so forth, this is certainly true for a commutator
But there is a couple of non-trivial rule
Well first of all the Poisson bracket is odd
Which means if you interchange with two entries it changes sign
Minus B A, that was one property
This is certainly shared by the commutator
If you interchange L and H you interchange these two terms
And you change the sign of the commutator
So that's true the commutator also
If A and B are now quantum variables, this is also equal to minus B times A
There's really only other one important relationship
It's a product rule, the product of A and B Poisson with C
The operation of Poisson-ing
If you remember the Poisson bracket was a combination of derivatives
Derivatives of various things, if you go and use that definition of Poisson bracket
Use the rule for derivatives of products
What you find out is this is equal to Poisson bracket side
is equal to A times Poisson bracket of B with C
Plus the Poisson bracket of B with C times
Sorry Poisson bracket of A with C times B
Now the order that you write down A and the Poisson bracket
That's not important, these are just numbers
These are just ordinary functions or numbers
And it doesn't matter which order you multiply them
But I wrote them in an order which I know
that the commutator would also satisfy
Operators the order does matter
So I wrote these in a specific order namely I put A on the left over here
And then I put B on the right over here
Maybe it's not too surprising, A up here on the left of this factor
And B appears on the right, so I kept the order intact
So let's see if this is true for commutators
What would it say? It would say, well let's write it out
A times commutator BC, sorry, go back
It would say that commutator of AB with C is equal to
I put a question mark here, I don't know if it's equal yet
A times a commutator of B with C plus A with C
Ya, A with C times B, let's check if that's true
This is very easy to do, we don't have to do any derivatives
So what we have to do is write out the meaning of this
Commutator of AB with C is the same as AB times C minus C times AB
Everybody see why?
First you put AB on the left time C, and then you put C on the left
and AB on the right, then you take the difference
Definition of the commutator
Let's see what we get on the right hand side
On the right hand side, we get A times BC minus CB
That's this term, and then from here we get plus AC minus CA
Times B, these are operators now
And these calculations are operators, the order matters
Okay let's see what we have
We have ABC, here is ABC that's good
We have, so this is a friend
We have minus CAB, that's this one over here, CAB
That's also a friend
Our enemy are ACB, but they both occur the same way
ABC, no no ACB, that's a bad one
But here we have also ACB, one with a minus sign
One with the plus sign, it was ACB minus ACB, and we're finished
The commutator satisfy the same algebraic rule as the Poisson bracket
Is it an accident? No of course it's not an accident
But we will get to the deeper reason for it eventually
which comes first and which is more basic
Certainly the commutator is more basic
Quantum mechanics is more basic than classical mechanics
Classical mechanics is an approximation of quantum mechanics
So it stands to reason
there ought to be a classical approximation to the notion of commutators
And there is, it's a
That leads us to speculate, if you like,
I will take it, it's not a speculation, I will take it as something would discover
Or we are able to prove later
That when we go from quantum mechanics to classical mechanics
The Poisson bracket let's see,
The Poisson bracket becomes I think minus i
Now this equality doesn't quite make sense
This is something classical on the right hand side
We should put arrows there, Commutator A with B
>> In that last equation, it seem
>> It seems that the right side is twice as the left side is
Well I don't think so
ABC, ABC, CAB, CAB with a minus sign
And then we have a couple of extra terms
The extra terms are minus ACB plus ACB, ya
Allow me to make this quick
That's good, slow me down
Now nothing in what I've done so far tells you
this should be identify exactly with that
It might be identify with this times a numerical multiple
The Poisson bracket might be seven times a commutator
Or a quarter of the commutator if they are all still make sense
If fact there is a dimensional difference between these
Poisson brackets are derivatives of A with respect to X
Derivatives of B with respect to p
They have units which are different than just AB
The difference of unit is actually soak up in Planck's constant
If we work with Planck's constant equal to one
Then Poisson brackets are just minus i times commutators
But for dimensional reason there is an h bar
Let's write it another way, let's put the h bar on the left hand side
Certainly classically, we think of commutator is very small
In fact we think of it as essentially zero
AB minus BA, so in the classical limit
The commutator is something which is zero
How does that happen? Well, it's the h bar here
And h bar is very very small in units
And h bar is very very small
which are just ordinary units, units like meters seconds kilograms
h bar is incredibly small in numbers, ten to the minus thirty
It's a very small number, so in a classical approximation
Commutators are negligibly small
But when keeping track of real quantum mechanics
The commutator is not zero
So that's the meaning or the notion of the commutator
And the nice property now is that this relationship here
is simply the quantum analog of an equation we studied last quarter
dL by dt is equal to the Poisson bracket of L with the Hamiltonian
which matches quite well with this
That is the essential reason at this stage for identifying H with a Hamiltonian
Classical mechanics when packaged in this fishy way called Poisson formulation
Fishy Poisson formulation capture, you know,
organize everything into relations involving Poisson brackets and
in particular it said dL by dt, L could be anything
Incidentally L here is not the angular momentum, it's anything
dL by dt was equal to the Poisson bracket of L with H
and in quantum mechanics, in the sense of average value
We found that dL by dt is minus i times the commutator
So that's the essence of the connection
between the Hamiltonian of classical mechanics and quantum mechanics
>> (inaudible)
L is any observable, any observable,
I used L for linear operator, but of course it should be Hermitian operator
So I might have used H, but then I would have got caught and found that H
Oh H is Hermitian, and so is L
But I use L for a generic observable
So I assume that L is Hermitian
Originally I used it for linear
But now I'm using it to mean linear and Hermitian
Alright L could be H, L could be H
That's we could study the equation of motion of how H changes with time
Or better yet, how average of H changes with time
Let's do so, here we are, dH by dt is equal to
minus i times the commutator of H with H
But the commutator of anything with itself is zero
And so incidentally as the Poisson bracket of anything with itself
Because Poisson brackets are odd,
they change sign when you interchanging two objects
That means the Poisson bracket of a thing with itself is zero
So from the classical point of view,
we could have derive the conservation of energy from the principle
That the time derivative of energy is the Poisson bracket of the energy with itself
Here we find in quantum mechanics are very similar things
The time derivative of the, again the Hamiltonian is the Poisson bracket
It's the commutator of the Hamiltonian with itself
And therefore it's zero
Energy is conserved in quantum mechanics,
so at least the average of the energy is conserve
Now it's better than that,
there is very definite sense in which energy is exactly conserved
But not for tonight
>> In the introductory example where you talk about two operators
>>physical example of that should include two object of particles?
We have two spins, ya, absolutely
In fact whenever we built a system out of two systems
In general the observables of one of the system
and the observables of the other system commutes to each other
That's why you can measure the position of me and Samuel J simultaneously
Because we are two, because our position commutes
So do our spins, I think that is the question you are asking?
But we haven't come to yet
As well as I gonna go latter, we will get to it
To the question of composing systems
Taking systems and making bigger systems out of composing them
That would bring us to the issue of entanglement
I have a feeling we probably won't quite get there
But maybe we will partly get there
Alright the next thing we wanna do is to solve Schrodinger equation
I don't mean the one for the eigenvalues and the eigenvectors
That we solve by standard methods
if we happened to know what the Hamiltonian is
Particularly if we happen to know some matrix form
Then we are just calculating the eigenvectors or eigenvalues of some matrix
Let's suppose that's done
We have the eigenvectors, we have the eigenvalues
Let's now find the general solution of Schrodinger's equation
Another words how things evolve with time
You know I realize that all of these are abstract that
the only system that we have to apply these all to is
the world's simplest system once again
And that's very not much
So at this stage, you probably saying to yourselves
when are we going to be thinking about real things
Objects systems, we will, we will, by all means
But I think having all these apparatus
abstract formulation of quantum mechanics
Will make it very easy and quick to start applying it to a lot of things
>> We didn't know the H for this spin system yet
Well, okay, so let me answer that right now
That depends on what we do with the spin
If we have a spin in three-space far from anything else
Then it's energy or it's Hamiltonian is just basically zero
Incidentally adding a constant to a Hamiltonian doesn't do anything
And the reason is because the constant commutes with everything
So apart from possible added to the constant
The spin which is not around anything else
It's just, the Hamiltonian is zero
And that means it doesn't change with time
If you put it in a magnetic field, if it happens to be a real spin of electron
You put in a magnetic field
The magnetic field induces Hamiltonian which helps we will get to it tonight
And it causes the spin to do things, to have a time-dependence
And then what the Hamiltonian would be would have to do with
which direction the magnetic field was in
So Hamiltonians can be changed, I mean you can change the Hamiltonian
by changing the direction of a magnetic field
But we will come, I hope we can get to the example tonight
But let's just first write down the general solution of the Schrodinger equation
To do that, we start by saying let there be a basis for eigenvectors
I guess we call it, this is the same as E sub i
If I don't want to write E sub i, I will just write down the ith eigenvector
But it means the eigenvector with the energy E sub i
Alright we can take any states since i or E sub i are basis of states
We can take any state, let's call it A
Or should we call it Psi, let's see what should I call it in my notes
No I think I called it Psi, I did, I called it Psi
And let's think of Psi at time zero
Well no, let's leave the time arbitrary
Psi is a sum of all the eigenstates, so all the eigenvalues
of some set of coefficients, alpha sub i
I've used the term alpha in the past
to denote the coefficients of states of basis vectors
So any states whatever can be written as
a superposition of eigenvectors of the energy
Since the eigenvectors of a Hermitian operator are a complete basis
Alright so this is Psi, let's say the time is equal to zero
Now how does the state change with time
What's changing here? Well the state |i> is just a fix set of states
It's the alpha which changed, the coefficients here which change with time
Alright so the coefficient in the expansion of an arbitrary state
are typically time dependent coefficients
That's what gives rise to the time dependence
In expectation values and other things
Now let's write the Schrodinger equation
So we have i Psi dot, sorry we have Psi dot which can now write,
Let's take Psi dot, d by dt of Psi
d Psi d t, that's equal from here
sum of i, d alpha sub i of t with respect to t, times |i>,
to differentiate the states, all we do is to differentiate the individual coefficients
now Schrodinger's equation tells us to set that equals to minus i
Oh, different i, holy smoke
Okay, j, j,
set that equals to minus i times H acting on this
But H can be brought in through the summation here
And this can just be written as summation of i
The coefficient numbers, alpha j, sum over j
Alpha j of t, H on |j>
Now what is H on |j>?
Somebody said zero?
No no no no no
|i> and E sub i are the same vectors
Go up to the top equation,
H on the ith eigenvector is the energy E sub i on the ith eigenvector
Okay? So this just becomes E sub j
Here we have on the left hand side a sum of basis vectors
With coefficients alpha j, sorry
Where are we? Did I make a mistake here?
Oh sorry, this should have gone down here
This is wrong, here, this should have gone down here
This is sum on j, d by dt of alpha j, and then
>> the i should be j
I'm lost
this is correct up to here
Let's, okay, let's go back to here
And now let's calculate the time derivative of this
What do we do? We put in minus i times H on |j>
Here is where I used H on j, is equal to E j on |j>
I think that's what I have a moment ago anyway, isn't it?
It's exactly what I have, minus I to get the minus i
Alright this thing and this thing are the same
So this sum must be exactly the same as this sum
If you have two sums, or basis vectors
The coefficients must be the same
If you have two sets of basis vectors, sorry
If you have two linear superposition of the same set of basis vectors
And they are equal to each other,
then the individual coefficient have to be equal to each other
So it follows that d alpha by d t is equal to minus i times d alpha j by dt
E j alpha j, all I've done is set d alpha dt
equal to the coefficient in this equation over here
And that's the whole upshot, it tells you how the alphas change with time
For each j, this is the differentially equation
Just think of this as the differential equation of alpha
What's the solution of differential equation?
We've done this kind of equation over and over again
The time derivative of something is proportional to the same thing
To the thing itself, exponential solutions right?
So the solution of this equation is alpha j equals alpha j at time zero
times e to the minus i E j t
If we differentiate alpha j with respect to t
It will bring down this factor minus i E sub j times the same thing
So we can now write the general solution of the Schrodinger equation
We solve it for each individual eigenvector
This is the way individual eigenvector
The individual coefficient alpha change with time
But now we can go back, let's go back
To the original equation, that the state vector is a summed over the eigenvectors
And let's plug in what we now know about alpha
Now we solve for alpha and here we can write the general state vector time t
If you know it at time zero
Let's suppose we know it at time zero
At time zero, it was just alpha j of time zero times j
All it happens is each alpha j picks up a time dependence
and the time dependence is just governed by the energy of the state
Too quick?
That's all you do to find the general solution is you take the state
you break it up into eigenvectors of a Hamiltonian
And then whenever was it time zero
The only thing that happens is that of each entries here change with time
with an e to the minus i, times the energy of the state
Where would the h bar go in this formula? Anybody know?
Underneath the i, underneath the energy, or underneath the time
It doesn't matter, but it goes into the denominator here
This is the connection between energy and oscillations okay?
This is the oscillations of the wave function
Not oscillations of real things,
but oscillations of the coefficients of the state vectors
While we are at it, let's do one more thing
Let's use our general solution of the Schrodinger equation
To calculate how the average of L changes with time
We have an equation for it, but now we actually know how Psi changes with time
And this is just a little bit of, not a gymnastic,
just a little bit of a fiddling around with equations
Some of you may recognize the equation we are about to get
But whether we recognize it or not
It's just explaining how the symbols are used if you like
Okay, let's calculate, given that the state change like so
Let's ask how the expectation value of an arbitrary observable changes
What do you have to know to know
how the average of the expectation value of L changes
L is some operator, I haven't told you what operator
Of course you need to know what operator in order to say how it changes
Of course you do, but still, we can go a little ways
Let's plug in this formula for Psi of t
This is sum of j, alpha sub j, e to the minus i E j t times |j>
Now we have L, put L over here
And now we are gonna do the same thing to this bra vector over here
But what happen when we do a bra vector?
Let's do the bra vector, the bra vector is Psi of t
is a summation, we better use a different summation variable k
And then we will have alpha star sub k of zero
And you go from bras to kets you have to complex conjugate
We will also have to change this to e to the plus i E sub k t,
times the bra vector <k
|874
I've changed the summation index here so I don't confuse it with this one
I've complex conjugate it, complex conjugate it here
And flip from kets to bras
Alright so I can put this over here
Summation of a k, <k| alpha star <k|, at time zero
This is at time zero, times E to the plus i E k t
So it's a double sum, it's a double sum over k
And j that's not terribly illuminating
But that's just for fun, let's work it out
What's the inner product of ?
Oh no, not sorry, it's not the inner product of
What we see here is L sandwiched between |j> and <k
|886
L sandwiched between |j> and
And then you project it onto <k
|888
Let's give that a name, let's call that L kj
That's exactly the kind of matrix element we compute it
when we talk about the matrix representation of the observables
The inner product of alpha, sorry, of L on j with k
That's what we call L kj, just the matrix representation of the observable
And then we have alpha star k of zero, alpha j of zero
I will say we talk about that in a moment
And then we have a phase e to the i (E sub k minus E sub j) times t
Summed over j and k
You know the main reason we did this was just to illustrate the machinery
I did not do this because this is a formula of any importance right now
But some of you may nevertheless recognize it
It is Heisenberg matrix formulations of quantum mechanics
Heisenberg formulations of the way averages change with time
If you go back to Heisenberg's first paper on quantum mechanics
He guessed this formula, basically just guessed this formula
Every observables have two frequencies associate with it
That was weird, it was common for people to understand that
An observable might be an oscillating observable
It might be something that oscillate, we have a frequency that oscillate with it
But Heisenberg said
there are two frequencies associates with every matrix element of an observable
This is where it came from, no, this came out of Heisenberg's head
But this is the way Dirac explained what
This is the way Dirac understood what Heisenberg was saying to this machinery
First just the pieces, this represent just the observable
Whatever the observable is
It's just the matrix representation
These things have to do with the initial state
The state at time equal to zero
And these things here have to do with things change with time
Everything change with time with two separate frequencies
And then you sum it all together
And that tells you how L changes with time
How the average of L changes with time
So we are putting together, a bunch of machinery that we will use
Are there any questions?
>> While I reading the case,
>> Is the magnitude of the alphas stay the same over time?
The alphas are fixed, the alphas are just the time equals to zero, period
Yes, I think you are going back here
Yes and that's correct, the magnitudes of alphas stay fixed
It's the relative phases between them
So all the time evolution has to do with these relative phases
>> So the equation is partial?
Is what?
>> partial?
Oh, it actually doesn't matters
This just mean the whole derivative with respect to time
It's usually written as a partial derivative
It just means, it could be written as total derivative, same thing
Psi only depends on time
>> Is Psi function of position?
It's, ya, okay, that's right
We will eventually thinking Psi as a function of time and position
And that's why, that's why, for the moment it doesn't matter what do we use
Partial derivative or total derivative, it just mean the change in Psi in a small time
And it doesn't matter which
>>When you directed time depend on Schrodinger equation
>> You used the fact that the state stays orthogonal all the time ?
>> I think that is an empirical fact
Well, it is an empirical fact, but in fact I think it's much more than that
The evidence is much more than that
It's also an empirical fact
It's a curious empirical fact
People are trying to change quantum mechanics
It seems to be just as hard to change quantum mechanics as it is
to change arithmetic or logic
As you start fooling around with it and try to change the rules
You will very quickly find something really bad happens
The probability is not conserved
The probability is not positive
Terrible non-localities happens when you can communicate infinite distances
And so quantum mechanics is not a thing can be easily changed
In fact there was no known changes that can be made in it
Of course there is one known change you can make
You can just replace it by classical mechanics
That's a consistent theory
The reason it's a consistent theory is there is a good limit of quantum mechanics
But there is no way to change it, you know to deform it a little bit
A friend David Finkelstein who is very wise, is a very wise man
Great scientist,
once explained to me that there are two kinds of revolutions in physics
He call one the plastic flow and the other a brittle cracking
What he meant by that,
he consider for example general relativity to be plastic flow
You can change it a little bit, you can deform it a little bit
You can change the Einstein's equation by changing variables
It's not something that you can not change at all
You can change it a little way and deform it
Special relativity is very hard to change
Once you change special relativity, it's very brittle
The whole structure of it goes down the drain
But you probably, but nevertheless, you cloud change it a little bit
It's hard to change it in general relativity, things go wrong
But quantum mechanics is absolutely brittle
And by that he meant, not the theory is endangered of being broken by anything
But that if you try to change it, you will get broken
So quantum mechanics is very hard to change
And I think the evidence for that is just
all of the years which people are trying to change it
>> So the (inaudible)
>> Is the reason we know that the real number because the eigen states
>> that we chose the eigen state of the
Yes, we derive from unitarity,
unitarity is the condition that U dagger U is equal to one or I,
it's called unitary, from that we derive that the Hamiltonian is Hermitian
And from that we can derive that it's eigenvalues are real
Of what? Syntax?
>> (inaudible) H or the ket vector E sub i
>> the first E sub i on the right hand side of the equation is an eigenvalue?
No, no, okay, it's, this whole thing is a eigenvalue, eigenvector
But it's an eigenvector with eigenvalue E sub i
So you can, you are labeling the eigenvector by their eigenvalues
Here is just the eigenvalue, right
And incidentally, this is a case where repeated indices do not get summed over
This is a case of the non-summation convention
Let's apply some of these apparatus to the problem of a single spin
The spin in a magnetic field
Let's see if we can calculate,
and in particular how the average of the components of the spins change
As we do this, depending on your memory for classical physics
You may start to find some of them familiar
If not, I will remind you
>> It's not as bad as finger on the old plate
No no it's not, no, it is not
That wasn't terribly bad, it just remind me of my cat in the middle of the night
Okay we have a single spin
Let's put the spin into a magnetic field
If we put a spin into magnetic field along
Let's take the z axis, it's very simple
Let's take the z axis put the spin in
Put the magnetic field along the z axis
A spin in particular, a spin of a charged particle
is a little electro magnet
Charged particles spins around, if it spin around
There was a current of flow and it creates a little magnet
Put a magnet in a magnetic field
And you get an energy, and basically the energy is proportional
to the misalignment of the magnet field with the spin
With the axis of the spin
And the simple formula is that the energy is proportional to the dot product
of the spin with the magnetic field
That's all we are gonna start
We are gonna start with an energy which is proportional to the magnetic field
And the magnetic field is along the z axis
So what is the dot product of the spin with an magnetic field?
It's going to be proportional to the z component of spin?
The dot product to the spin with the magnetic field
would be the component of the spin along the axis of the magnetic field
That's a guess, okay, I could take that as a guess
Which we could then study and ask if the experiment on the spin agree with it
Okay so we have a spin, we have a magnetic field along z axis
Let's call it B sub z
And we have a spin, and the spin has components sigma x sigma y and sigma z
People ask me incidentally
why in the book I'm writing about quantum mechanics has few figures,
there are lots of figures in classical mechanics book
The reason is very simple, I mean the real reason
You can't draw a quantum mechanical system
Quantum mechanical system are the very nature not things that you could draw
If you could draw then you will always be trying to draw a thing
Which can not simultaneously make sense
In particular if I try to draw the components of the spin
Try to draw the components of a spin which don't commute with each other
And it doesn't make sense to draw them
Nevertheless there it is
Magnetic field and the spin
And we are just going to write now
We are going to take this as a guess, or as a postulate
The Hamiltonian is just going to be proportional to the component of the spin
along the z axis times something proportional to the magnetic field
I'm not going to write out, it contains electric charge
It contains a magnetic moment, it contains magnetic field
But let's just call the coefficient here
Let's call it omega over two
That's a definition of omega if you like
Whatever the right combination of magnetic field, charge, magnetic moment
Make the particular charge, magnetic field
would lump them up and call it sigma over two
Sorry omega over two
The reason for the omega would become clear shortly
Sorry the reason for the two,
both the omega and the two will be conclude shortly
Okay now what I want to calculate
What I want to calculate, I want to calculate
the time derivative of the averages of all the components of the spin
Here we have the z component in the Hamiltonian
But I want to find out how all the components
Sigma x sigma y and sigma z, how they vary with time
So in particular I want to calculate the time derivative
Dot for time derivative of sigma x sigma y and sigma z
What was the rule? I'm afraid the rule is erased
But I think you probably remember it
The time, by definition now, this means the average of sigma x right
I'm not going to bother writing the bra-ket angular bracket there
We are now talking about the averages of sigma x sigma y and sigma z
And the time derivatives of the averages
Alright if you remember, this is equal to minus i times the commutator of sigma x
with the Hamiltonian right?
So the Hamiltonian is sigma z, and we get another factor of omega over two
Ya, that's correct
Likewise here, sigma y with sigma z times omega over two
And likewise here, sigma z sigma z
Now one of these is very easy
Which is the easy one?
The bottom one, everything commutes with itself right?
Everything commutes with itself
So this is zero and what does it tells us?
It tells us the component of the spin along the magnetic field
The average of it does not change with time
That also tells us, if we are doing classical physics, which we are not
If we are doing classical physics, it will tell us the angle of the little vector here
With the magnetic field stay the same
But we are not
We just take this for what it says
It says that z component doesn't change with time, the average
So that's the first thing we discovered
Now to go beyond this, we have to know what the commutation relations are
Of the sigmas
Let's work them out, I think we have enough time
Let's work out the commutation relation of the sigma-s
All pairs of them, see what we can get, and then plug it into here
I'm gonna start with sigma x sigma z
But instead I'm gonna do the opposite way
I'm gonna calculate sigma z sigma x
It's the same thing except with the minus sign
If you interchange with two of them
So you have to remember
I'm calculating sigma z sigma x
We will have to remember the change of sign
Okay so what is this? This is the product,
now anybody remember what sigma z is as a matrix?
We are going to do it now as matrices
and say the way to calculate this is to remember
the sigma z and sigma x are matrices
or at least they have a matrix representation
and we just have to multiply the matrices
sigma z, what was that? That was one zero
one, sorry, one, minus one
And what about sigma x?
That's zero one one zero
That's the first term in the commutator, sigma z times sigma x
And then the other term is just to put them in the opposite order
Zero one, one zero, times one zero, zero minus one
>> These operations would not (inaudible)?
No, we just take the commutators of the matrices as what it comes down to
We could do it without the matrices, just by applying the operators to the vectors
The vectors up and down and
we know enough to actually do that without actually using the matrices
But the matrices are very convenient tool for manipulating operators
Operator product is the same as matrix product
So everybody knows how to do a matrix product? I hope so
Let's do this one over here
The upper left hand corner is the product of this row with this column
One time zero, zero time one is zero
The upper right corner is the product of this row with this column
One times one zero, zero one
The lower left corner is the product of this row with this column
That's minus one and then the last one is this row
Sorry this column times this row, zero times one and sorry no
Zero to this one, this one is still zero
Okay now let's do the other one over here
Minus, zero times one, this one times this one is zero
This one times this one, minus one
This one times this one, one, zero
Uh, I think I missed the sign somewhere
No no, that's right, that's right
This is plus, minus, okay so this we just gave the same thing
But with a minus sign sorry
This minus this gave two term which add
So the commutator is just equal to the commutator itself
It's just equal to zero one, no, it's equal to twice minus one zero
Now do you recognize this thing over here
If I put an i, an i over here, you might recognize it as being related to sigma y
Let me write down sigma y
Sigma y is equal to minus i, i zero zero
Then what happens if we multiply sigma i by i
i times minus i is one, and i times i is minus one
So what this is, it's just twice i sigma y
Two i sigma y
That's kind of neat, it's closing up on itself
Commutator of sigma with sigma is sigma, that's good
Because it's going to allow me to write equations for the time derivative of sigma
Which is just gonna be sigma-s again
Okay so let's see what we have, we have commutator sigma z with sigma x
is equal to twice i sigma y, and now I will write down the rest of them
Incidentally, as I said, if you want to get the opposite order
you just change the sign
Sigma z sigma x with sigma y is equal to two i sigma z
And z, x, y sigma y, x, y, z sigma z
It's equal to two i sigma x
These are the three commutations
Does this remind you of anything?
Do you remember the Poisson brackets for angular momentum?
The Poisson brackets of angular momentum were L z L x equals L y
L x L y equals to L z
And L y L z is equal to L x
So apart from the fact there is two i
Remember there is an i in the connection
between Poisson brackets and commutators
These are essentially apart from the fact of two, which can be absorbed
Then essentially angular momentums are Poisson brackets
That's an important clue there for the meaning of angular momentum
But we are not gonna dwell on it for the moment
These are the commutation relations of the component of the spin
And they just give back the component of the spin again
With this funny ordering, z x y, x y z, y z x
I just permute it secretly
Okay so let's go over to here now
This now becomes minus i omega over two
And what's the commutator of sigma x with sigma z
It's minus two i sigma y
So we get another minus two i sigma y
With two-s cancelled,
that was the reason that I put a two in the denominator here in the first place
cause I knew it's gonna cancelled
So let's cancel the two, and we have minus i times minus i which is minus one
So what we get is minus omega sigma y
Notice that the i went away, the i went away
I was worried about it, about half an hour ago
Oh my goddess, time derivatives of real things are gonna get imaginary
But they didn't, they didn't
because the commutators themselves has imaginary coefficients
And that's general, that's general, okay
So there we are, we have sigma x dot is equal to minus omega sigma y
And sigma y dot, here we have the relationship for some sigma y
And it involves twice sigma x
The correct relationship we've worked it out is that
This is equal to plus omega sigma x
Okay so sigma z dot is zero, but what's happening to sigma x and sigma y
Can you see what's happening with sigma x and sigma y?
Do you recognize this, these equations?
These are the equations for a thing moving in circular motion right?
What's happening is simple, the x in the sense of expectation values
Expectation values are real numbers
And the sense of expectation values
The spin vector is processing around the z axis
It's processing around the z axis
Sigma x dot is minus omega sigma y
Sigma y is plus omega sigma x
This is the same kind of formula that we discovered in classical mechanics
That we talked about a roller
We also put the roader in the magnetic field, the angular momentum
Executed exactly the same, and it's also the gyroscope procession
It's basically gyroscopic procession
The spin, the quantum mechanical spin in the sense of expectation values
It doesn't make any sense to say that the quantum mechanical operators
themselves are processed, that doesn't mean anything
Quantum mechanical operators are just these matrices
They don't do anything
But because the state vector change with time
The expectation value or the average value of the spin
Executed motion which is basically the same as a classical roader
Processing a magnetic field, okay?
So we have now solve the problem of a spin in the magnetic field
We solved the hardest possible problem associated with a single spin
There is no Hamiltonian which is more complicated than this for a single spin
It's the more general, of course you could put the magnetic field in the x direction
That's a little, yes you could solve a harder problem
You could put the spin along some peculiar axis
But what you would find after you work the whole thing out
is it just process around a peculiar axis of the magnetic field
Same thing it just rotated
so that the magnetic field is pointing at different direction
What's that?
>> any () can be described by Hamiltonian?
There really aren't many operators
Okay so let's just, here's a general, you could work this out yourself
This is not hard to prove
The most general Hermitian operator in two dimensions
is a linear combination of the unit operator
sigma x sigma y and sigma z, the most general Hermitian operator
is a linear combination of these
Putting a unit operator into a Hamiltonian
That's like adding a constant to the energy
Unit operators commute with everything
So putting a unit operator in is not interesting
It does nothing, so we get rid of this
The next possibility is a general combination
A linear combination add them up, of coefficient times sigma x
another coefficient times sigma y and another coefficient times sigma z
That just correspond to putting the magnetic field of some angle
It just, the simple case where we only took one of these
It's the magnetic field along the z axis
If we took a general linearly combination
Let's say n sub x sigma x plus n sub y sigma y, plus n sub z sigma z
This will just correspond to the component of the spin along the n axis
And you would do exactly the same calculation
except you might work instead in the basis of eigenvectors of sigma dot n
So it really is the general Hamiltonian that you can write down
And that just because a two-dimensional space is so simple
It's just on very independent operators in it
It just does nothing else
>> The two-dimensional space is the space of states
>> but sort of things in three-dimensional space in the procession
Right, but we work, ya, but remember for every direction you can think of
There is a state for which that component of the spin is definite
But that's secondary here, we are not
That didn't play very much a role here, which just follow the rules
And yes, I mean there are two things going on here
And this is a good place to focus on those two things
There are the three-vectors, the vectors in real space
Those are the components of the average of sigma
And there is a two-dimensional space of state and they're quite different things
Although they are related
>> Does it make a represented
omega is basically the magnetic field times the magnetic moment of the little spin
Maybe of two I have to remember, but no I don't think
Ya, there is a two, ya
Omega over two is the product of magnetic moment with the magnetic field
>> Our original technique for creating a sigma z was to
>> put it in a magnetic field and have a (full timer)?
That was, that was last year, you are right
>> I mean if we pursuit this and couple it to a field
>> we will see that
Ya, right, if we couple the spin, now forget the procession
If we couple a spin to a magnetic field
Then there will be two energy states
For example if the magnetic field this is along the z axis
Then the energy of the up state and the down state would be different
They will different by amount omega
Up will have an energy omega over two
Down would have the energy minus omega over two
And there will be an energy difference of omega
Alright so one of them has higher energy
One of them has lower energy
What happens to a real spin if you wait long enough?
If you put it in a magnetic field
The answer is eventually the higher energy state will emit a photon
And what will be the energy of the photon? Omega
Just a difference between the upper energy and the lower energy
And in the process of emitting the photon it will flip
So these things are all certainly connected
But alright we solved a real genuine quantum mechanic problem
>> So why is the B not in the operators
>> Why is the magnetic field not in the operators?
If you are to think of the magnet as a part of quantum mechanical system
Whenever you are facing the problem of a real quantum system
which is being an interaction with a heavy system
With a system like a magnet or other kinds of detector
Almost classical system, you don't bother
trying to think of the heavy system quantum mechanically
That has to be justified, this is not obvious to justify
Why don't we have to think of the magnet
is a part of the quantum mechanical system?
It's another way of asking the same question
And the answer is it's so big and so heavy that it doesn't fluctuate much
But eventually we will want to address that problem
For the moment we just think of the magnet as a part of a heavy apparatus
which is sort of fixed and it's there
Nothing that the electron can do is gonna cause that magnetic field to change
It's just stuck there, and we get to think of it deterministically
When do we get to think of other thing deterministically?
We get to think of the thing deterministically when it's so heavy
And so many degrees of freedom
That when we calculate the quantum mechanics of it
We find that the fluctuation is really small
But that's nothing established yet
So far we divided the world into the quantum and the apparatuses
The heavy apparatus we don't have to deal with quantum mechanically
That of course is a temporary thing
Real apparatus is made of the same thing as the system we study
And at some point we have to come back and say
What was the justification for saying the apparatus was allowed to be consider
just classically, you just point it in some direction
And that's the way it is
And the spin dealt with quantum mechanically
We will have to come back and answer that
But you know my usual statement at this point is not tonight
>> sigma x, sigma y, those are average values?
>> if we repeat the experiment a zillion time, would it
>> if we repeat the experiment a zillion time, would it change or fail?
No unpredictable manner
Yes the answer is yes, it will occasionally fail
But that has little to do with quantum mechanics
Well it has to do with quantum mechanics
But it has to do with the use of statistics and probability
Why is probability work?
We make a basic postulate, and that's if you do an experiment over enough time
The average value that you get in a laboratory will agree with in small precision
With the mathematical averages
that you calculate from a probability distribution
I am not going to try to justify that
The reason is I don't know what is true
And why does probability work?
Why, if I tell you, if you flip a coin a thousand times
Does it come up heads of five hundred times? No
There is no such prediction
Certainly I mean it might come up five hundred times heads
But there is not prediction that says it does
Will it come up five hundred times plus or minus?
Square root of a thousand? Plus or minus thirty?
That's the margin of error, not every time, no
So there is no such prediction
What can you say? You could probably come up
You know we are getting into a cycle
How about if I do a million times, it will certainly come up
five hundred thousand plus or minus square root of them?
No, no matter how many times you do it
There is no hard and fast prediction from probability that
any particular thing will happen
Why does it work? Jesus, that beats me
But it does
You know I'm not the only one that have been puzzled by this
I mean, you know, I used to like to joke that
This is probably the reason that Einstein didn't like quantum mechanics
>>
Say that again
>> on the floor the Psi, x, y and z
>>  reflected in the magnet right?
Now we could have done the same calculation
by instead of putting an sigma z here putting sigma dot n
Sigma dot n is the matrix in the notation that we've been using up till now
With the sigma matrices that are the things that wrote down
It will be the matrix and there is a unit vector
n sub z minus n sub z, n x minus i n y
and n x plus i n y, it's just taking a component of n
and multiplying them with the corresponding component of sigma
and then you could start with this and say
This is, put an omega over two
And take this to be the Hamiltonian
And then recalculate what happens to the different components of spin
Well the component of spin along the n axis, what would we do then?
We will have to calculate commutators of the various components of the spin
With sigma dot n, sigma dot n
What about the component along the n axis?
What happens to it? The commutator zero right?
Sigma dot n commutes to sigma dot n
So we will find out that the component to the spin along the n axis
Would be the thing that doesn't change
How about the component of spin perpendicular to that axis?
We can work that out, and we will discover that the spin process about the n axis
That's a good exercise to try to do
>>  reflected the orientation
If you want to, say that again?
>> I was asking what the reflected the orientation of the spin
>> the omega and then to dot n
Omega is just a number
>> because you flip it to dot n, if you move to dot n
>>(inaudible)
My orientation you mean Poisson minus one?
Or you mean direction?
No no no no no, omega doesn't have to do with the direction
Omega is just the magnitude of a magnetic field
Magnitude of a magnetic field times the magnitude of the magnetic moment
>> the dot?
No dotted in they are just numbers
Numbers, the dot product is between sigma and n
Omega is just a spectator, a number, it's just a number
It's just a number, or you can if you like,
you can take this omega and put it with a n if you want to
>> (inaudible)
>> depends on the orientation of the spin
What depends on the orientation of the spin?
>> The energy eigenvalue H
One of those is confused, I'm not sure which
>> The confusion is we can see there the magnetic field is in the z direction?
Here the magnetic field is in the z direction
>> omega z
Omega z, where do we have the omega z?
>> H equals omega two, sorry, sigma z
sigma z, yes sigma z
>> Where is the spatial vector of the spin vector
Omega (sigma) dot n means dot product
>> you said whenever you are talking spin
>> you are talking with one over two
I think I read that too, I think it was Newt Gingrich last book?
I don't know, sigma dot n stands for sigma x n x plus sigma y n y plus sigma z n z
Exactly as if sigma was a classical vector
But of course it's not, it's just a collection of three matrices
So this stands for matrix
This stands for a single matrix which happens to be
the sum of three particular matrices
But that's definition of sigma dot n if you like
These are the components of n
and they determine the direction of the magnetic field
We multiply that by omega over two which is just a number
Just a number, nothing more complicated than a number
And this is what sigma dot n means
If the magnetic field is along the z axis
Then the only component of n which is none zero would be n sub z
Okay? If the magnetic field was along the z axis then
We would say only n sub z
If you like, would you like me to write down
the relationship between n and the magnetic field?
The relationship between n and the magnetic field
is that the magnetic field vector is equal to the magnitude of the magnetic field
times the unit vector n
The magnetic field as a vector was a magnitude to the magnetic field
times the vecotor n, and that stands for magnetic field
It's pointing along the n axis with magnitude B
Once we know that, then we could basically identify the magnetic field with n
Apart from a numerical coefficient
Numerical coefficient is buried into omega here
Once we know that we could write this as the spin dotted into B
So I'm not sure what the questions are
There is something which is bothering some of you I'm not sure what it is
>>  is frequency you get always the same or
It depends on the magnitude of the magnetic field nothing more
>>
You are talking about the frequency of the photon?
Now the frequency of the photon is always just the difference of
the energy of the upper energy level and the lower energy level
And it's always just omega
It doesn't depend on the, right
If you take sigma dot n and ask what it's eigenvalues are
The eigenvalues don't depend on n
They are plus or minus one in any direction
>> (inaudible) eigenvector?
The eigenvalues, let's write out, sigma dot n
Alright here is an exercise for you should be done
Sigma dot n is n sub z times sigma sub z
That's n z minus n z, plus n x times sigma x, that's that
Minus n y sigma y, that's n dot sigma
Question: what are the eigenvalues of these matrices?
Somebody worked them out,
I know somebody in this room has worked them out
But who was it?
The eigenvalues for these matrices here for any n, as long as it's the unit vectors
If n is the component of a unit vector
Another words, n x squared plus n y squared plus n z squared is equal to one
You will find that the eigenvalues of these matrices are always plus or minus one
This is simply the statement that
no matter what direction you point your detector, your apparatus
When the apparatus acts, it gives you plus or minus ones, okay?
So whatever direction you take here
The eigenvalues of these matrices are plus or minus one
If you know a little bit about matrices
For those who know a little bit about matrices, let's prove it
The trace of the matrix is the sum of it's eigenvalues
The trace means sum of the diagonal elements
First step, there are two eigenvalues, let's call them lambda one and lambda two
And the trace of the matrix is zero
This one plus this one, and that tells us that lambda one plus lambda two is zero
Or lambda one is equal to minus lambda two
So there are two eigenvalues and they are equal in opposite
What about the determinant of the matrix?
It's the product of the eigenvalues
So we now know they come in equal and opposite pairs
What's the product? What's the determinant?
The determinant of this matrix is equal to minus n z squared
This times this, minus this times this, and that's minus n x squared
Minus n y squared, right?
n x plus i n y times n x minus i ny is n x squared plus n y squared
Here it is, now what is n x squared plus ny squared plus n z squared?
One, so the determinant which is the product of the eigenvalues
is equal to minus one
There is only one solution, lambda one plus lambda two is equal to zero
That's lambda one equals to minus lambda two
And the product is equal to minus one
There is only one such pair, it's plus one and minus one
So all such matrices of these form have eigenvalues which are plus or minus one
And therefore the energy levels are always plus or minus omega over two
One of them plus omega over two, the other minus omega over two
When you flip from one to the other you get omega worth of energy
Always so it doesn't matter which way it was pointing in
Ya , I think it's time to go but
>> the electron is  in the extra
>> and you put it in a magnetic field and review that
>> and suddenly it has y and z direction
Ya ya, in studying, yes, I should have say
In studying the procession we ignore the possibility that it can radiate a photon
Now the probability to radiate a photon per unit time
Can be pretty small, can be very very small
Particularly the energy difference is very very small,
as they would be in a magnetic field
It will process many many times before emits a photon
>> So, my question is, if it does it will emit a photon
>> Since it's not flipping in a whole 180 degree
No, go from up to down
Remember the two eigenvectors, the two eigenvectors up and down
left and right or in and out, correspond to opposite orientation of the spin
Even though the state vectors are orthogonal
The directions in space are 180 degrees apart
>> So this imaginary situation that
>> What is was doing to orthogonal
Well okay, there is a probability for the electron to decay
And emit a photon, and that probability per unit time is typically small
So you could be unlucky and after a quarter of evolution
It might emit a photon
But that's extremely unlikely, you can estimate,
Am I answering your question, I'm not sure
>> No I really is  would it be either in the direction
>> it was going to a flipped opposite and suddenly goes other way
>> like from x y to z
>>I think the question is
>> It appears that if the electron is not perfectly fit into the magnetic field
No, no no, it's in a superposition of being up and down
It's one or two of those
It's only the average which is sort of in that direction
It's in a superposition of being up and down
If it's down and down is the lower energy state it wont radiate
If it's up it will radiate, so you put the electron to some other direction
There will be some probability for it to radiate
And the probability for it to not radiate
The probability for it to radiate is the probability that it was up, ya
Very confusing, very confusing, alright
Okay now I knew what was bothering you
If the magnetic field is that way
And the spin is aligned that way
You might have thought that when it jumps
you only emit half the energy of the photon
Half the energy, no,
what's correct is that the probability for it to emit a photon is one half
Why? Because it has half a probability this is actually down
And half a probability that is up
If you are to measure the up-ness and down-ness of it
So that means the average energy that it emits is half
But it either emits omega or it doesn't emit at all okay
For more ,please visit us at Stanford.edu