Stanford University
There was an issue that came up last time
I didn't understand the question
There was a question that kept coming up
And I didn't understand what it was until the very end of the class
It was an interesting and a good question
So I wanna go over it because it is important
It had to do with a spin in a magnetic field emitting a photon
And I maintained that if it emits a photon
Remember the, the way we set things up
We set let's take the Hamiltonian to be omega over two
Let's say sigma z
That has two eigenvalues, plus omega over two and minus omega over two
So the two eigenvalues let's call it E_1 the energy
The lower of the two eigenvalues is minus omega over two
And the upper on is, let's call it E minus and E plus
This is plus omega over two
So there was two energy levels, if we draw an energy level diagram
Energy, we will have two eigenvalues, it would be zero over here
But that would not be one of them
But then we would have one over here, omega over two
And minus omega over two
Alright what could happen under such
We have not studied this process here yet
But let's talk about it for a moment
Given two states like this, it is possible for an atom or a spin
Or a system with energy levels like this to emit a photon
Emit a photon and go from the upper one to the lower one
If it's in the upper, if it's in the lower state obviously it cannot emit a photon
Doesn't have the energy to do it
But if it's in an upper state it can emit a photon
And that photon will have the energy difference
between the upper and the lower state
So we will have an energy, of frequency, of energy omega
Sorry not frequency, it will be frequency
But more important, it will have energy of omega
There is an h bar missing, I have been setting h bar equals to zero
No, h bar equals one
I've been setting h bar equals to one
It's really h bar omega, but I will continue to set h bar equals to one
Because we all grown up, we are not afraid to set h bar equals to one right
What?
>> It was zero last quarter
it was zero last quarter, yeah, it was zero last quarter that's correct
Okay so we draw a picture of the photon transition and a photon being emitted
Now somebody said what if the spin was not pointed up or down
What if it pointed, here is the z axis
What if it pointed, let's say in this way along the x axis
And then it emitted a photon
Would it not emit the photon of half the energy namely omega over two
The answer is no if would not emit a photon of a energy omega over two
Let's discuss first what we are having classically
Classically if we have a roller, a spinning roller in a magnetic field
That had an energy, which it was the typical energy would be the co..
The cosine of the angle between the axis of the spin
Here's the axis of the spin, here's the magnetic field
The energy of that rotating object would depend on the orientation of the spin
Relative to the magnetic field
The energy would be minimum down
And it will gradually increase until it was up
That's number one, number two classically and quantum mechanically
Classically the actual value,
and quantum mechanically the expectation value of the spin
processes around the B axis with frequency omega
That also happens classically
It's in the classical mechanics notes in the Poisson brackets section
Where we study exactly that question
It wasn't called spin, it was called angular momentum, the spinning top
Does exactly the same thing
And that spinning top if it really is a little electro magnet
A little magnetic system rotating, it will radiate
In the process of going around with frequency omega
It will emit radiation, at what frequency? Omega
It will emit, radiation at the
And how much radiation would it emit?
Now it's classical it's not emitting photon
Emitting classical radiation, and it will gradually, as it emit radiation
Fall over until it gets down and then no more radiation
How much energy would it emit all together?
And the answer depend on the angle that it started at
If it starts up it would emit all together an amount of energy that is proportional
essentially omega, if it's pointing down it will emit no energy
If it's pointing horizontally, it would emit, let's say omega over two
So it would be a continuously possible value of emission of radiation at the same frequency
Quantum mechanically it can only emit a photon with
whatever that energy the photon has
And the answer is, it's related but different answer
If it emits, it will emit a photon of energy omega
On the other hand the probability of whatever it emits is not one necessarily
And in fact let's suppose the initial state is some alpha up plus beta down
If alpha and beta are equal, that corresponds to oriented along the x axis
If alpha is one and beta is zero, that's pointing up
If alpha is zero and beta is one, that's pointing down
And up electron, or an up spin, will emit a photon of frequency omega
Of energy omega, so if was just the up state, yes indeed
It will emit omega
If it was a down state, it emits nothing
If it starts at the superposition of the states
Then with probability alpha star alpha it emits
And with probability beta star beta it doesn't emit
What is the average energy, given that it's a probability alpha star alpha
that emits with a photon of frequency omega, energy omega
And beta star beta that it emits nothing
What is the average energy, and the average energy
is the same as the classical energy
The average energy is the same as the classical energy
But each individual event emits a photon of either
Either it emits no photon or it emits a photon of energy omega
So that was, who asked the question?
Somebody here asked a question
So that's the upshot
And this is sort of the internal consistency of quantum mechanics
And of course to really, ya?
>> If the electron will emit a photon when it's in the down energy
>> presumably could avert the photon?
Yes, that's correct
>> How precise of the photon after B to omega
That depends on the life time of the state
And which in terms depend on how strongly coupled
the depends on the dipole moment, the stronger the dipole moment
The magnetic moment, the faster it would emit
The faster it would emit, it's another way the sort of life time
the excited state will be
It's the inversed life time which set this scale of exactly what you are asking
The precision with which you will have to be exactly
There is a spread in the energy level
The spread in the energy level are uncertainty in the energy level
And the uncertainty of the energy level is the inversed to the life time of the state
So right, so you are absolutely right, it was a spread
It's governed by the energy-time uncertainty principle
But we are not there yet, whether we will get there I don't know
Okay
>> Is this phenomenon of photon emission which use
>> to create an apparatus to detect it?
What apparatus
>> to create an apparatus that detects the spin of an electron
You could, that's one way to do it, that's one way to do it
I decided to not think about that as an apparatus
I didn't like it, because it didn't satisfied the rule that
If you measure a component of a spin you leave the system with exactly that
After thinking about it, I decided not qualified as a genuine measuring apparatus
So we are gonna come to measurement
and the meaning of measurement in a little while
But we will soon move, half an hour gone already
#Okay if there are no more questions,
I'm gonna move on to the subject of entanglement
I have a few words to say about the collapse of a wave function
Let's just talk about for a moment the idea of collapse of the wave function
We've talked about how the quantum states evolve
According to the Schrodinger equation and that is the way they evolve
But that's the way they evolve between events
where somebody or something are detectors or
an apparatus or just some other systems, an external system
interact with the original quantum system
So we have a quantum system, we have other thing in the world
Including observers, including apparatuses, and just including other things
If we take away all the other things
The system might be left in some state, and then the system will evolve
according to the Schrodinger equation
And then we maybe bring back the other things
The other things might be an apparatus
Where did the apparatus go? The apparatus is hiding
But it could be an apparatus or something else
But let's say it's an apparatus, and the apparatus measures some specific thing
That were happened during the course of the interaction with the apparatus
If a measurement takes place, and the system is left in an eigen state
corresponding to the particular outcome
So for example we might start, let's suppose we want to measure L
And our system after a while might be in a state
Some summation over i, a bunch of complex number alpha sub i
Times eigenvectors of L, eigenvectors of L with eigenvalues lambda sub i
Okay what's the probability for the outcome of the experiment?
The system got here by evolving using the Schrodinger equation
We started it out, we evolve it according to Schrodinger equation
Here is what we got, at the end of the day
And now we make a measurement of L
And we get some specific value of lambda
Random, we don't know what it's gonna be?
But it's gonna be something
Let's say it's lambda seven, we measured lambda seven
There after, or right after that, the system is in state lambda seven
The course of the operation of measurement
is not governed by the Schrodinger equation for the system
It's governed by the nature of the measuring process
And it simply tells you that you come out with one of the eigenvalues
as the measured value, and the state vector will be just one of these
Which one? Random
Random depending on the measure, now that's funny
because you might think, look, well first of all
let's give it a terminology,
the terminology is the way the function collapse around one point
It is collapse around one single eigenvalue
You can't predict which one
But all of the structure here with all the other one becomes irrelevant
And only one state pops into existence so to speak
Alright now what's wrong with this?
What's wrong with this? There is absolutely nothing wrong with it
It's correct description of the measurement process
But what is very unsatisfying about this
is after all, apparatus is just quantum systems
Why do we have two rules for the wave systems evolve?
One is Schrodinger equation, and one is arbitrary collapsed wave function
The answer is that we,
if we want to think quantum mechanically about the whole system
A system plus apparatus, that's fine we can do it,
and I hope we could get to it tonight
And then it's pure Schrodinger equation
but we cannot separate the system into just system and apparatus
We have to think about the whole quantum system as being
system plus apparatus, that raise the question immediately right now
How do you combine systems together?
If you have more than one system, it could be an electron spin and the apparatus
We have two systems now,
imagine we had a good quantum theory of the apparatus
The apparatus is a physical system quantum theories governs it
How do we describe the combined system where we take two components
One spin, one apparatus, put them together
How do we make it into a single quantum system?
And then how with that single quantum system
do we describe this process of measurement?
That is a very, confused a generation of physicists
Partly because Bohr was very stubborn about this
He didn't quite had it right
And he was a nice man, a very nice man, very glad, I never met him
Though he was a nice man, but thing is he is also a very stubborn man
And this particular thing, he was mostly right
But here and there, he was wrong,
It was apparently very tough to be around him where he was
People tried to explained to him over and over again
You have to think of the combined system
and you have to think of the combined quantum system
If you want to understand the quantum mechanics of measurement
And he said no, he didn't believed that, anyway
Combined systems, we have two systems now
Let's just not worry about what they are
They are two systems, we will get more specific in the moment
But let's give them names, let's call one of the systems A
and A does not stand, it could stand for apparatus
But it doesn't have to, it's just A
System A, I will call the space of states of system A, S sub A
S sub A could stand for system A
but now I had it to mean the space of quantum state of the system A
And we have another system, I'm gonna call I
It's another system with it's own space of state I
This system A has state which are labeled by a basis of states
You chose a basis of states in the system A
And you can label them |a>,
|a> can go from one to whatever the number of state of the system A is
Whatever the dimensions of the space of state A is
And system I has state |i>
Any state of system A, if you didn't have I,
would be a superposition of this basis states
Any state of system I would be a superposition of these space of states
How do we put the systems together and make a single quantum system?
Well, I'm gonna tell you what the rule is
I will give you a quick book rule but it's pretty compelling
And it is the way real things work, okay
You built a space of state of the system A I
Which means A and I together, both of them
That space of state is called mathematically,
it is what is called the tensor product
I will tell you what it means in detail
but it's the tensor product of the two space of states S A
And this is the symbol of the tensor product S I
Now what does a tensor product mean?
Well, it mean something very simple
It means you construct a new space
New mathematical space whose vectors are labeled
by a value of |a> and value of |i>
Another words, you pair off the basis vectors and all possible pairings
One from A, one from I, and you construct a basis which is labeled |a i>
If this, let's suppose the dimensionality of this space is D sub a
And the dimensionality of this space is D sub i, or D sub
I guess it's capital A I want here, D sub capital A and D sub capital I
Another words the number of orthogonal states of each one of these separately
Then what's the, what's the dimensionality of the tensor product?
D_A times D_I, you get to pick one from A and one from I
Like in a Chinese restaurant, one from A and one from I, Okay?
And how many are there all together?
D_A times D_I, that's why it's called a product,
because the dimensionality is a product
So this is D_A times D_I in dimensionality
These are the base of states for the tensor product, okay
They are labeled with two indices
Now you think of them as orthonormal basis
Orthonormal in the following sense
If you take two such vectors |a i> and let's say |b j>
Where b is another one of the basis vector of A
And j is another one of the this
What's the inner product between these
Let's take these to be, let's take these to be normalized vectors
What is the inner product between them?
And the rule for a tensor product is the inner product between this and this
Of course we have to make a bra vector out of it
In order to, in order to take it's inner product
But if we make a bra vector out of this until it's inner product with this one
The rule is that the inner product is zero unless a is equal to b
And i is equals to j, another words, unless they matched
If they don't match, these might be observably different
For example if this b is the same as this a
But i was not the same as j
Then one half of the system here would be, would be observable difference
associated with the observable difference in the sub system I
So in order for them to have an overlap
b must equal a and j must equal i
and then they are observably the same vector
>> Excuse me, are these arbitrary vectors? a, and
These are basis vectors
>> Part of the orthonormal basis?
Yes you could pick any orthonormal basis from this one
And any orthonormal basis from this one
Ya, but you could pick any orthonormal basis from this one
And put them together in this way, you will get the same result
Doesn't matter which basis you pick, but let's pick a basis to be concrete
Let's pick a basis, if a and i are not the same as both b and j
The inner product is zero
I can write an equation for that
is equal to delta, kronecker delta ab kronecker delta ij
If i is not equal to j, or a is not equal to b, this is zero
It's only none-zero if i is equal to j and a is equal to b
So these vectors formally by construction, by construction
Which means you simply assigning values to things now
But in a way that it's useful
These vectors form by definition or by construction,
an orthonormal basis for the combined system
And this makes sense
>> And you've defined this depend upon the basis, but
It does, but actually, defined it, let's put it this way
It were depend on the basis
That construction in the end doesn't
The construction in the end doesn't, and that's not hard to show
This is, however, keep in mind that
these basis vector are not all of the vectors in a tensor products
You can then take any linear combination of these basis vectors
And they are also a vector in the tensor product, so
So the general vector in the tensor product is of the form
Sum over i and a, alpha, let's call it sum i a, |i a>
A general linear combination of the coefficient
that depend on what's inside here times the vector
times the basis vectors
Now the answer is, if you have chosen another basis
Another set of basis, you could have gotten exactly the same vectors
Except they would have been written differently
They would have just been written in a different basis of a combined system
Changing basis for the individual systems
corresponds to the basis changes for combined systems
Okay, so that's good, we now have the idea of a tensor product
And I'm gonna give you a concrete example now
The concrete example is the next most complicated quantum system
Namely two spins
Well it's debatable whether it's the next most complicated
or the next to next most complicated
And the reason I say that, is because two spins have four basis vectors
You could imagine a system with only three basis vectors
And such system exist
But since we are trying to learn how to combine systems
Let's take two systems and combine them
Each of them being a spin
So what do we have, we have an electron nail down at this position over here
And it has a spin, which we are gonna call sigma
And it has three components, sigma x y and z
So sigma x y and z, and we have another one over here
We need a name for it, now I've toy it for a while
We are calling this sigma one, this one sigma two
But there are too many indices,
but then I have sigma one x and sigma one y, but they are bad
So I decided to give this one another name
And the Greek letter that comes after sigma is tau
I don't know if it's the next letter, the next one in the English alphabet
That's t, ya, so the next one I think in the alphabet is tau
And I simply call this one tau
How many component does tau have?
Oh tau is also a spin
So it also has three components x y and z
Supposing I chose for the basis vectors for each of these
The up and down basis vectors
Another words, the state in which sigma z is up or down
And the state in which tau z are up or down
Then our basis vector for sigma are up> and down>
Our basis vectors for tau are exactly the same
Up> and down>, and maybe in order to indicate that
These are the vectors for the system tau
And these are the vectors for system sigma
Let's use a slightly different kind of bracket notation here
Let's use a curly bracket, I'm gonna give that very shortly
I just want to point out to you that these are different in meanings...and down
And down}, so what is the basis vectors for the combined system
If we put the system together,
what are the basis vectors for the combined system?
There are four of them, two times two is four
And what are they? They are states in which both spins are up
It's one of them, one spin
And I always take the first entry here correspond to sigma
And the second entry to correspond to tau
Up down>, down up> and down down>
That's the four basis vectors, each basis vectors carrying two labels now
A sigma label and a tau label
That's the idea, that's you know, it's very reasonable idea
Yes?
>> Supposedly these two component systems interact
>> Does that .. or not?
No, the basis vectors stay the same, but the linear combination of basis vectors
That they are describing the system would change, ya
So any state in this space can be written as alpha up, times up up>
Plus an alpha up down |up down> plus an alpha down up |down up>
Plus an alpha down down |down down>
That's the most general thing we can write
Let's call it |Psi>
The answer to your question is
if you started out with a particular linear combination
Let's say for example just alpha up up |up up>
Both spin's up and you let them interact
Then in general what happen to these coefficients would change
In fact it could even happen that after a time alpha up up
might go to alpha down down
In other words, two spin up might interact in such a way
It's just wind up down,
that would not be a change in what the basis vectors are
It would be a change in what the alphas are
Alright another several questions we can ask
Incidentally, one of the criteria for doing this correctly
is that if we take a combined system but then we only do experiments
on one of the halves of it
The other one doing whatever it's doing
And they are well separated from each other
Let's suppose they are well separated from each other
And we do an experiment on only one of them
The answer that we get should be the same answer that we got
When we even not think of it as a combined system
If we have a theory of sigma
Which we talked about now for five weeks I think
And we know all about it
We know how to do experiments on it
And now we think of it as half a system composed of sigma and tau
But sigma and tau are far from each other let's say
They are not interacting with each other substantially
And we do exactly the same experiment so we've been talking about up till now
We should give the same answers
So we should put these things together in a way
Which make sure that the earlier issues
The earlier description of either sub system is still correct
Now I'm not gonna bother proving that
I think you will get the idea and you will see how it works
And the way we are putting things together does guarantee that
Okay now we can go into two directions from here
We can talk about the space of states
Or we can talk about the observables
So we are gonna do both
But I will take a vote, how many of you want to talk about the space of states?
How many want to talk about the observables?
We will talk about the space of states first
You know I was gonna do that, you know, come on
Alright , ya
>> .. left and right for that again?
What's that?
Oh yeah yeah yeah, sure ,there are ya
Supposing we wanted, supposing we wanted a state
Which was left for sigma and up for tau, alright?
So this would be a state which would be prepared
We have two apparatuses now,
I'm always uncomfortable with the word apparatuses
I always thinking it would be apparati, I don't think that's right
We have two apparatuses, one that we apply to sigma
The other we apply to tau, and we now take our apparatus
One apparatus, sigma apparatus, we point it in the, let's say, the x y axis
Not the x y, along the x axis, and the other one and we point along the z axis
And we are wind up discovering that sigma was along the x axis with plus one
And tau was along the z axis also with plus one
So that means that sigma was up but tau was right
How do we make a state which is
So the answer is, I will tell you what to do,
but then we will eventually have a mathematic for this
Sigma is definitely up, but tau is a linear superposition of up with down
Easy, you just take up up plus> up down>
Square root of two, one over square root of two
You can think of this another way
You can say think of it as a product
A product of up> for sigma and right} for tau
Now what is right}?
Right} is up> plus down> right? Right
Right is up> plus down>
So this can also be written as up> times another,
I will put a big square bracket around it
Up}, curly bracket, plus down}
But if I want to normalize it I should put a square root of two downstairs
So we just think of it as a product of sigma up and tau in the,
along the right direction
But that's the same thing here
We have one over square root of two up up> as this one
And one over square root of two up down>, that's this one
I'm not sure this answer your questions or not
But I think it probably partly did, ya, okay
This kind of state is called the product state
It's a product state in which you know exactly what's going on with sigma
Namely it's in the up direction and you know exactly what's going along with tau
It's in the y direction, it's product state
It's simply two separate things which are prepared independently
And here it is, a product state is by definition a product
Let's write the most general product state
The most general, this is not the most general product state
The most general product state can be written as follows
Alpha up  up> plus alpha down  down>
That's for sigma and then for tau let's call it beta
Let's call the coefficient for tau, let's call it beta
Beta up up} squiggly plus beta down down}
What does this mean?
This means that sigma was prepared in this particular linear combination here
It might have been holding the detector in some funny angle
And this one is the respond to holding tau detector at some other angle
And you had only one of these not the other
You would just have written this down
And the other one you would have written this down
Together you write down the product, that's the rule
Okay, of course you know, ultimately these rules are the rules
Because they agree with experiment but
It's pretty plausible rule
This is a product, we can also write it alpha up beta up times up up>
Plus alpha up beta down up down>, do I need to write the rest of it?
Well I will, plus alpha down beta up down up>,
Plus alpha down beta down down down>
Alright of course, this is of the form of the general vector
But there is something special about the coefficients here
The coefficients factorized into
And therefore this is in a certain sense special to some extend
Let's see if we can quantify how special
>> What kind of vector product is that?
That's a tensor product, this is the element of a tensor product
And it's a tensor product of this vector with that vector
It's a vector drawn in a composite system as a tensor product of
vector described in one system and a vector described in other system
So strictly speaking the tensor product is usually used for the whole space
But then you would say this is a product state within the tensor product space
And I will just call it tensor product state or product state
It's not general and to see how none general it is
We can count parameters, given a general system or a general state vector
How many parameters?
How many independent parameters does it take to describe it?
And the answer is four complex numbers
Alpha up up, alpha up down, alpha down up, alpha down down
I am not assuming that it has this special form
Just general four numbers, four complex numbers is eight real numbers
But that's a little too much
Because we should assume the state is normalized
So that's one constrain, and we also know over all phase is not important
So when you count parameters, you always subtracts two
One for the normalization, one for the phase
Eight minus two is six, six real parameters describing a general state of two spins
How many here? Well the state describing the sigma particle
That has two real parameters
Four real parameters for alpha up and alpha down
But then we subtract two, same thing here
This is a normalized state, and it's overall phase doesn't matter
This is a normalized state, it's overall phase doesn't matter
All together four real parameters
It's the same four real parameters that you might have guess
if you set ahead just two spins
Each spin has two parameters necessary to write down it's state
two real parameters,
two real parameters could have been the polarization direction of the spin
The axis along which the spin is oriented or
So there are four parameters but six parameters here
That simply proves that not all states are product states
In fact most states are not product states
We are gonna talk about some none product state soon enough
But this is the notion of the product state
And the product state, we can really think of separate states
for each of the particles for each of the sub systems
But for more general state you can't really divide it
into a state for one subsystem and the state for the other sub system
They are entangled, they are entangled and they are more elaborate
They are more um, I don't know what the right word is
Entangled, they are entangled in a more entangle way
We are gonna discuss that, entanglement
That's very important concept of course
Okay that's two spins, how many parameters six versus four
They are entangled, alright, we talked about product state
And that's what we know about the space of state of the system
It takes six parameters to describe it
While only four parameters of it's product state
Product state is the one
which you can separately say there is the state for one system
And the state for the other system, end of story
Okay let's talk about observables, now we come to observables
What are the observables for this composite system?
Well they must be the same observables
as for the separate systems by themselves
Another words, sigma x y and z and tau x y and z
They are the things you could measure with two apparatuses of the same kind
As we used in our experiments on one spin
We now have two of them, so we now have sigma x and sigma y and sigma z
And tau x tau y and tau z
Let's see if we can figure out how these operators what it operates on
the state of the combined systems
Alright you can sort of guess I will spell it out
But here is the rule, let's take sigma x
And let's apply it to the state of these sigma systems
Obviously it belong to the sigma systems
If it applies to up>, it gives down>
If it applies to down>, it gives up>
You can check that, that's a fact with sigma x, it's equal to zero one one zero
This off diagonal character means it takes up> to down> and down> to up>
This is what sigma x does
Ordinarily if we only have one sub system
Here is what it does on a combined system
Sigma x on any vector which begins with up and has anything
Let's see, which one was a and which one was i?
Second one was i? Tau went with i or Tau went with?
Tau was i, okay
So sigma x when it acts on up i, all it sees is the up>
All it sees is the first thing here, and it's completely passive
with respect to the second index
Another words, it doesn't even notice the second index
And leaves it the same, it doesn't change it
But it does whatever it should do on the first entry
Likewise, sigma x on down i> equals up i>
You just take what it did for the single spin space
And you just think of the other index as a kind of spectator
It just goes along for the ride, doesn't do anything
On the other hand, let's do one more sigma
Sigma z on up i> now what does sigma z do when it acts on up>?
Sigma z is one minus one zero zero, it just gives back up with value one
So that's just up i>, and what about sigma z on down i>?
And what happens when sigma z hits down?
Minus down, so this gives minus down i>
How about sigma y? What does sigma y (do)?
Sigma y does something very much the same as sigma x
Except it throws an i, not this i>, but numerical complex number i
It throws it around because what is it, sigma x?
This is sigma z, sigma x was one minus one
And sigma y was equal to minus i, i, zero zero
Sigma y also flips up> to down> and down> to up>
But it throws in a .. i here
Okay so that's what sigma does
Now how about tau?
Well tau does exactly the same thing except that
the first entry becomes the spectator
And only the second entry gets acted on
So let's, let's do this one
Tau let's say x on a up>, a could be anything, a could be up> or down>
Doesn't matter, tau x on a up> is equal to a times down>
And tau x on a down> is equal to a up>
Alright let's do tau z on a up> equals a up>
And tau z on a down> is equal to minus a down>
And you could figure out the action of the y component of the spin
It's straightforward
With this definition, it's quite clear that if you are talking about an observable
associated with sigma, that the tau degrees of freedom are completely passive
Nothing happens to them, the eigenvectors of the components of sigma
Are simply product state of the eigenvector of sigma times any vector for tau
Another words for example the eigenvectors
the eigenvectors, the eigenvectors of, let's take sigma y
Ordinarily the eigenvector of sigma y are one i or one minus i
I can't remember which one has eigenvalues plus one or minus one
But one way or the other
But that means, that means the linear combination up plus i down>
That's an eigenvector of sigma y
If you want the eigenvector of sigma y
when we are talking about the composite system
It's exactly the same except you put an i in here I guess
An i in here and an i in here, same i, same i
So for example, it could be up up plus i down up
Or up down> plus i down down>
The i is a spectator, it just goes along for the ride
Anything which was an eigenvectors for the single system
Remains the eigenvectors for the single system
except you have to add in the index for the other particle,
for the other subsystem
And that's all there is to it, with this definition as I said
It's pretty clear that the separate subsystem
Behaves independently, quite independently
As long as you don't let them interact and feel each other
Or do something interesting with each other
As long as they are kept separated
Okay, um, other questions?
>> The equation sigma x acting on |u> and gives down>
>> Shouldn't it, you have sigma x acting on
>> the superposition of state?
No no, sigma x
>> in terms of the eigen states of the sigma x
Well, let's just do it by matrices
sigma x is one one zero zero, up is one zero, okay?
up> is one zero, what happens? This times this is zero
This times this is one
So up> has gone to down>, okay?
Likewise, if we put a zero here and a one here
This would become one zero
So it just takes one zero and flips it to zero one
And back and forth like that
In general of course you would be right
But for this particular case, I just gives you back
>> I see what the ones and zeros work out
>> but in the physical situation where
>> you were making the measurement to get the state
Well this doesn't say, this doesn't say, let's see
This doesn't say one zero and zero one are eigenvectors of sigma x
Far from it, it's as far from an eigenvector you can get
When you acted sigma x on this one you get a completely orthogonal state
So this is not the rule that says, this is not the equation
that says zero one or one zero are eigenvectors
An eigenvector is a vector which is kept in the same direction
by action of the operator
This is as far as you can get from that
The operator acts and gives you something orthogonal
And that's okay? Alright you have to work that out
>> up> is a linear superposition of left and right
Indeed it is
Right that's correct
>> my question before class is,
>> Is there a physical meaning to applying operator to a none-eigen vector
>>What is that operation equates to?
Most of the times, that's just auxiliary operation in some calculation or other
Well, it doesn't have any particular special physical meaning
But in this particular case, it tells you is the zero one one zero
It's about as far from eigenvalues as you can get
And what it tells you is that if you measure sigma x
In an eigen state of sigma z, it's as random as it can be
It's as random as it can be
Alright we are going along good
>> (inaudible)
>> What happens if I have sigma x tau x
say that again
>> (inaudible)
>> What happens if I have sigma x tau x operating on
Sigma x times tau x? Okay we could work that out
It's a little bit later, five minutes in the note
But let's do it right now since we are at it
Let's take sigma x tau x and tell me what vector you would like to apply it to?
How about up up>? Let's do up up>
What does tau x do? I keep forgetting
The one in the left is sigma right? This one is sigma and this one is tau right?
Okay, alright so we saw the tau and we hit this
What does tau x do? It operates on this one and let this one alone
So this gives us, do I have it wrong? Ya
Ya it operates on this one and let this one alone, right
So it gives sigma x, I have not acted on that yet
Times, now tau x flips this one
So it was up down>
Okay now what does sigma x do?
It flips this one, so it just gives down down>, kind of boring
But that's what it does
Let's do it in an opposite order
Let's take tau x times sigma x on up up> what does it do?
It does exactly the same thing
Sigma x hits one of these and flips them
And then tau x comes and hits the other one and flips them
So when tau x times sigma x acts,
it gives exactly the same thing as sigma x times tau x
Commutator of sigma x with tau x equals zero
No difference between the order of operations
Let's try it for sigma x times tau z
Okay let's do it for sigma x times tau z and see what we get
Oh I have not proved this because I only exhibit for one particular state
In order to argue that sigma x times tau x equals tau x times sigma x
Oops, you would have to show that they give the same thing
when acting on any basis vectors
It's enough to show that they gives the same thing on basis vectors
Alright but that's pretty easy, not hard to do
You can do it on any basis vectors
And you will find out the order of operation doesn't matter
In fact the same is true if you take sigma x times, let's say, tau z
Let's do it again, shall I take a different vector?
Let's take some other vector, instead of up down>, let's take down up>
And see what it does, and then we will do it in the opposite order
Alright what does tau z do when it hits this vector here?
It only acts on the second entry
And it's the z component so it just gives plus one on up> right?
So this just gives sigma x times down up>
Tau z on up> gives up>
So that just goes right through
And what does sigma x do when it hits down up>?
This gets a little bit gobbly look, at this point my tongue starts rebelling
What does sigma x do when it hits tau? When it hits this guy
It just flips down> to up>, it gives up up> right
Let's do it in the opposite order tau z sigma x on down up
Alright first sigma x, that flips down to up
So it gives us tau z times up up>
And then tau z just gives us one when it gives it up here
So it gives the same thing again, so you can sort of see why
They are acting on separate indices here,
it doesn't matter which way you order them
This is very general, it doesn't matter which state you take,
It doesn't matter which component you take
Any component of sigma commutes with any components of tau
You can check that, just by knowing how they act
Alright so we can say sigma anything, I'm not sure how to call the index here
Sigma, I don't wanna call it i, I already used i for something
But sigma n and sigma tau n for any m and n they commute
The meaning of that, is that if you have two separate sub systems
Which are combined in this way, the observable for one and
the observable for the other can be simultaneously measured
In particular if you took the system from far apart to each other
And you treat them as a single quantum system
You would expect that measuring one of them
doesn't interfere with any measurement with the other one
And that's what this says,
that measuring a sigma does not preclude measuring a tau
And vise versa, for any components of them
So in that sense, they behave like independent systems
You can make any measurement on sigma
And any measurement on tau, ya?
>>
>> So these observables are each independent parts
>> you knows it fit into the system
>> and you could think about that observables one
>>
It's as happy as it was when you added the other sub system
Yes, that's a good question, are there observables which are some how
more intermittently connected with having both of them?
The answer is yes, for example sigma times tau
Sigma times tau, sigma x times tau x or sigma y times tau y
That sort of things are observables that
somehow no more intermittently about the combination of both of them
And they know in particular about entanglement
>> If you started with independent
>> You just said ..
>> Now how are you making them so they dependent on each other?
We haven't yet, we haven't yet, what we've done up till now
is to all the ingredients which tell you that
as long as you do separate experiments, separate operations
On the two sub systems, that they will behave exactly as they would have
Had the other system not been there
But now you can ask what about, are there more in particular
In particular, if the system, if the combined system, if it's in a product state
If it's in a product state so that each component has it's own state vector
Then the quantum mechanics of each one of them is separate from the other
They don't interfere with each other
They don't know about each other in any way
That's what this prescription ensures
No, they are not entangled yet
Not if they are product states
Now what we found out is that the product states are four parameters set
We found that also that the full space of state has six parameters
So there are apparently state which are not product states
Those are the state which would have to varying degrees
A degree of entanglement
#I'm gonna write down the most entangled state
and I'm gonna examine it a little bit
and see in what way it's odd
up down>, there are many highly entangled states, maximally entangled state
I'm writing one, one particular one, minus
I'm putting a minus here just because I happen to know that it's a particular
It has a particular property which is not so important at this stage
But let's put the minus state, minus down up>
One over square root of two of course
One over square root of two times the whole thing
Now this state is interesting
It has the property that if you, well, it has a correlation
If you know that tau was down, then sigma must be up
On the other hand if you know that tau is up, then sigma must be down
Now what does that mean mathematically?
We are going to find out what exactly that mean mathematically
This is not a product state
There is no way that this can be written as a product of one state
It's a sum or difference in this case for two product states
But it's not a product state
How can we tell, how can we tell, so let's consider the expectation value
In a state of the components of sigma
Let's go back to the one subsystem, to the one system quantum mechanics
One spin, and let's say what do we know about that?
In particular I'm interested in expectation values of, in any state
Take a state, and take the expectation value of all three components
This is the average value, I'm not multiplying anything
I'm just considering them individually
Can they all be zero?
Can they all simultaneously be zero for an ordinary state of a
For the ordinary two parameters family of states for the single system?
Should we take a vote or should I just tell you
The answer is no, they can not all be zero
Here's the reason, well, the reason is given any state
There was always a direction in space, in three-dimensional space
A direction for which, sigma in that direction,
the component of sigma in that direction is definite and equals to plus one
Given any Psi, this is what I told you in the very beginning of the lecture
Or maybe even before the lecture
Given any state, there are some linear combination of sigmas
which is definitely equal to plus one
In that case if I find that particular combination of sigmas
Sigma n x, you know, dot sigma into n, that particular linear combination
It's expectation value can't be zero
Because it's definitely up along that direction
So the answer is, given any state there was always some direction
Let's call it sigma dot n, that depends on Psi
That depend on Psi, sigma dot n, for which this is not only not zero
But it's equal to plus one
The average of sigma dot n is of course
If sigma dot n is definite, if it's known and there is no ambiguity about it
Then the average is just equal to the value that it's known to be
So there is always some n, alright,
for any Psi, there exists an n, such that, this is true
Therefore it can not be true that all of these can simultaneously be zero
For a state of a single spin
You can't measure them all simultaneously
But if I give you a state I tell you the state
Then I can then, you can tell me what direction of space
should you orient your detector
so that the answer comes out plus one, okay?
For example I mean, I can just give you up
Okay so what direction if I gave you up?
What direction should you orient your detector? along the z axis
What if I gave you up plus down, with square root of two?
What direction should you orient your detector to make sure
you get plus one? Along the x axis right?
What if I gave you up> plus i down> ?
I know, the sum, it's either plus i or minus i, okay? I forget which one
Given any combination there are enough direction that you can find the direction
For which sigma in that direction is definitely plus one
And therefore it can not be that all of these expectation values are all zero
Why? Because you know that sigma dot n is equal to plus one
And that of course is just a linear combination of these
Okay so as I said, it's impossible if we have just a state of one spin
Isolated by itself, it's been prepared somehow
However it's prepared, there exists a direction in which the spin is definite
And not equal to zero, okay
What about the state? What about the state now?
Let's take sigma and ask whether any of the components of sigma
have a non zero expectation value in this state?
What I'm gonna show, I will tell you the answer right now
We are gonna show that all three component of sigma
have zero expectation value in this state
That means the state cannot possibly be a product state
A product state is one in which each component behaves
as if they were just a state of subsystem by itself
This state is gonna behave in a way that
no simple product state could possibly behave
We are going to find, so let's do it, let's do it
Okay let's put, the square root of two here is not important
That's not the important thing
We have up down> minus down up>
We are gonna take the expectation value
So that mean we have to make a sandwich
The sandwich would have up down> minus down up>
In the middle here we are gonna put a sigma
We could do with sigma tau, and get the same answer
So let's put sigma z first
Let's put sigma z here and see what we get
First we act with sigma z, and what does sigma z gives when it hits up down>
It just gives up down> right?
Alright? So this just gives up down>,
but what does it give when it hits this guy over here?
Minus down up>, but there is already a minus down up>
So there is a plus, already a minus, the minus gets killed
It's over here, so that's the inner product
Let's put some brackets around it
It's the inner product with <up down minu <down up
Okay let's calculate it
What's ? Zero
What's ? One
So we get a one, what's ?
Wowo, I got something wrong here
What did I do here? This should be <up down| right?
Okay so let's go back
is one
is zero
what about ? Zero
What about ? One, but there's a minus sign here
So this is orthogonal to this, the inner product to zero
And it says that the expectation value of sigma z is equal to zero
Sigma z in this state, not any state but in this state is zero
Let's try sigma x, let's try sigma x next and see what we get
So we have sigma x here, alright, let's spill out sandwich again
And the minus sign here, and what happens when sigma x equals |up down>?
It hits |up down>?
It flips up to down, sigma x is the flipper
And it flips the first entry here
So it flips the first entry to down
And flips this entry to up
We are taking the inner product with this vector over here
So let's see is there anything in common over here
with something in common here?
No, so there is no way to get an inner product
is zero etc. etc.
again this is zero
so sigma x is equal to zero, expectation value
okay what about sigma y, let's put sigma y there
sigma y is also a flip flop operator
It flips up to down and down to up but with an i
I don't remember which, where the i goes
It either goes here, here, something like that
But whatever it does, it flips this up to down
So we get a |down down>, and it flips this down to up
So we get a |up up>
Again, no inner product is zero
So there we are, all three components have zero expectation value
But that's funny because we proved, well we didn't prove
But I told you, that if I take any state of the single spin
It's never the case that all three sigma-s have zero expectation value
What's the lesson? The lesson is there is a state of the composite system
That in no way ever be thought of as separate states for the two subsystems
That's what entanglement is
That's an example of entanglement
>> So what .. obvious that if you do that with product state
>> then it will satisfy the same property that one of them will be ..
Yes, that's correct, that's correct
Well if you show it for the single spin by itself
Remember the other index that just goes along for the ride
So however you derive it for a one spin with itself
You will do the same derivation
except put a sort of spectator index to ride along with it
So it's obvious that if it's true for a one subsystem by itself that
It will be true for the composite
What's not obvious is that it's true for one subsystem
So ya, so that's an exercise, that's an exercise to show that
all three components of the spin cannot,
or the expectation value cannot be zero
There is always a direction in which it's maximum
>> Question? So how do you put a system in this strange state?
Ya, it's very natural state to have
I will tell you, if you have two spins
and the two spins are interacting with each other
They will have a, in particular if there are little magnetic moments
Then they will have an interaction with each other
which will prefer to make them anti-align
Now this is anti-align, |up down>
This is anti-align, |down up>
And in fact this combination here has the lowest energy
This combination has the lowest energy
It has less energy than |up down> plus |down up>
So if you bring these two spins together and you wait awhile
They will irradiate a photon then eventually come to the state
So it's actually not at all hard to get this kind of state
It's kind of easy to get this kind of state
And we will discuss that when we talk about interactions
But it's a typical situation that this is what result
If you take two spins put them together and
let them come to equilibrium by radiating a photon
A long time, first of all I have to close them to bring them together
Second of all, how big the magnetic dipole of the spins are
And that has to do with the strength of the coupling to the magnetic field
So in ordinary laboratory situation,
in an atom the electrons are close enough together
That they will radiate the photon at not too long a time to achieve this
so called singlet state, this is called the singlet state, singlet
I'm not gonna tell you why right now
There are four basis vectors all together
The reason this is called the singlet
because there are three other which are called the triplet, okay?
>> Can you get the over all up down plus down up ..
Ya, well not at the moment by eventually
I will tell you the answer though
If you think of these as little angular momenta
And you put them in |up down> minus |down up>
The total angular momentum is zero
If you put then |down up> plus |down up>
The total angular momentum is one
And energy is often proportional to angular momentum
So, but, we will come to that, eventually we will come to that
It's a fair question but let's not try to answer it right this minute
>> If you take it in general state of two systems
>> Is it possible to change the basis
>> such that one basis create a sub space of product space, of product state?
>> the other is entirely pure product space
You are asking whether the notion of entanglement is an invariant notion
The answer is yes
The answer is yes, there is very definite quantity that you can calculate
called the entanglement entropy which measures the strength of entanglement
Which is not dependent on any particular basis
Now I might tell you right now, this state okay,
this state does have a special feature that
up down> plus down up> wouldn't have
Supposing you took this state, and this is good, homework assignment
Up and down individually for both sigma and tau
can be rewritten in terms of left and right
For example, up is left plus right and down is left minus right
Or whatever, there's a square root of two there but you know what I mean
Okay supposing I write this state
I plug in every place I see down, left minus right
And every place I see up, left plus right
What do I get out of this, the answer is very simple
I get |left right> minus |right left>
Supposing I rewrite it in terms of in and out, what do I get?
|in out> minus |out in>
So the structure that the state has and the nature of it
is actually the same in every basis
Every basis it looks the same
And that would not be true for |up down> plus |down up>
|down up> and.. they would.. um
They would get mixed up with other states
There are three other states, this is one, there are three others
Three others, obviously there are three others
The name mixed up with each other when you change the basis
But this is not obvious, this is not obvious at all
Alright let's do one last thing, I'm not sure it's last thing or not
I think it's probably last thing for tonight
#Let's ask about one of these observables which is not an observable
that can be identified with either sub system
but which are some how got to do with both
And let's look at that expectation value, very simple example
Let's take, let's take the expectation value of the product of sigma z times tau z
We will do that one, we will do sigma x times tau x
And maybe we will do sigma x times tau y, we will do, we will try some examples
Let's take the expectation value of this
Now to do this we again make a sandwich
And let's do it
|up down>, oops, sorry
Now I should put the square root of two in
The reason I should put the square root of two in now
is I'm not gonna get zero, so if I really want to get the numerical number
I wanna put the square root of two in
And here we have <up down| minus <down up
|1100
Also over square root of two, so in fact I could take the square roots of twos
And put them all into the factor one half here
This is the expectation value in the singlet state
So we take a singlet state, and we take sigma z times tau z
Let's see what we get
First of all, when sigma z, when tau z acts what does it do?
Do you remember? I don't, oh yes
tau z doesn't flip, it just gives you a sign which is plus for this one
and minus for this one
So we can remove the tau z just by putting the minus sign here alright
Did I do that right?
Let's see tau z, tau z acts on down to get minus down
It acts on up to give up, so it has no effect on this term
And it changes the sign of this term
I think I get it right, No? Ya, minus
Now what about sigma z what does it do?
It flips the sign, no it doesn't flip, it gives plus on this one and minus on this one
So it changes the sign of this one
Okay now we have to put it together
We have  with a minus sign, it's a minus one
We have , minus one
Cross terms give nothing,  gives nothing
gives nothing
There are two terms, you get the two over two
Hum, minus two over two equals minus one
What does is say? This is kind of interesting
The expectation value of sigma x by itself was zero
The expectation value of tau x by itself was zero
The expectation value of sigma x times tau x is minus one
Let's see if we can see why
Look at the state here, in this component over here
Obviously, sorry, this was sigma z, sigma z we were talking about
Sigma z are opposite in both contributions here
Sigma z time this z for this piece is minus one, why is that?
This one's up, this one's down
If sigma z is plus for this one, sigma z is minus for this one
The product is negative, the product is negative one for this one also
In fact if you think about it, this state is an eigenvector of sigma z times tau z
What's the eigenvalue? Minus one
So in fact this state is the state in which you measure the product sigma z tau z
We get minus one every single time
So the expectation value is minus one
Nevertheless the expectation value of the individual sigma x,
sorry sigma z and tau z is zero
Alright so this is, this is beginning to get some of the flavor
of what entangled state is
It simply doesn't behave like you might expect like two separate systems
which are just independent, it has always been independent as they behave
Let's try, this is undoubtedly gonna get boring now
But let's do it anyway
This is plus minus, you go back to the original sandwich
But instead of sigma z, let's do, let's do sigma x tau x
Alright so sigma x times tau x, it's easy to figure that out
Tau x flips the second entry, sigma x flips the first entry
Alright so this object here simply flips both entry
without changing any signs, it flips no entries at all
Well, it, what did I say,
So what does it do? It looks like it interchanges these two, alright?
Interchanges these two, this one minus and this one plus
Now what's the inner product?
, minus one
, minus one again
Again minus two over two, equals minus one
Same exact thing as
And what would you guess about sigma y tau y?
There was nothing special about the y axis, same thing
Also has an expectation value equals to minus one
So alright, this again this is telling you very clearly this can't be a product state
For a product state, the expectation value of a product like this
would just be the product of expectation values
And that's not what is going on here
So this is a highly entangled state, about as entangled as you can get
>> .. for two observables?
>> Sorry, two operators, excuse me
>> So how I can figure that physics
>> If follows back the operations?
In this case you, in this case remember
No you don't, not, in general no
In general it's just another operator, if it's Hermitian
It's another observable, it can be measured
But in this case, since all sigma commutes with all taus
You can think about measuring them both simultaneously
And in fact if you measure them both simultaneously you will simply discover
The obvious fact that they are oppositely oriented
Let's do one more, let's do, since I haven't work it out
I've never work it out, and I will work it out right now
Let's do tau, sigma x times tau z
Let's do sigma x, oops what do I write here sigma x tau x alright
Let's do sigma x times tau z and see what we get
I don't know the answers so let's do it
I have a suspicion, I have a suspicion, but okay we will find out
What happens when tau z acts on this guy here?
Tau z it just changes the sign right?
Tau z, if it's down you get minus one, if it's up you get plus one
So you get, alright flip them around, yes you are right, good
Okay so tau z sees the down> here and makes it minus down>
And sees the up> here and leaves it alone
Okay now what does sigma x do?
Sigma x flips the first entry
And so it gives minus |down down>, minus
Now let's see it flips, minus |up up> right?
Now we have to take the inner product with this right over here
Well nothing over here matches anything over here
So we see the answer in this case is zero
We see the answer is zero
The expectation value of sigma x times tau z or any unequal one
that's equal to zero
What does it say? Well I don't know
The main reason I did it is because I was curious about what the answer was
But I also did it just as a illustration of
the machinery of calculating expectation value
But these ones tell you clear things
What they tell you is that in a very definite sense
The any given component of sigma and tau
The x component or the y component or the z component
are oppositely oriented
It's obvious here for the z component they are oppositely oriented huh
This is opposite to this, this is opposite to this
So in any of the component, state vectors here
They are oppositely oriented
But we also found something else out
We found that they are oppositely oriented in the x basis or in the y basis
And one of the basis if you measure any one of the spins
Any component of the up spin
Basically it automatically tells you what the other one is
Well this is telling you,
since it's been telling you the product is always equal to minus one
In fact this is an eigenvector of the product, or any of these products
It tells you if you measure any of the component for one of them
That you will get exactly the opposite if you measure the other one
It's a correlation, it's a correlation and statistical correlation
That if you measure one of the component of spin of sigma
and also the same component for the other one, they will be opposite
Of course it doesn't tell you much
If you measure the x component of this spin and the y component of that spin
That it doesn't tell you much,
but it does tell you if you measure the same component of either of them
They would come out opposite
>> Bell (inaudible)
>> dealing with these systems of two spin oriented in opposite direction
>> isn't it will be a up down kind of state
>> Is that right or is that so?
No the kind of state Bell dealt with was
entangled state |up down> minus |down up>
It's exactly what he dealt with
>>Is there any interaction with two of the state like this?
This, almost any interaction between the spin that we do a state like that
>> Did you say that it's a statistical correlation?
Yes it's just the statistical correlation that
Look, at this, to some extend, it's similar to a trivial observation
The way I like to phrase it is I have a penny and a dime in my pocket
I put my hand into my pocket I take them out I don't look at them
Without looking at them I give one to Alice and one to Bob
And then I take Alice and Bob to take off and
They will go to moon or whatever you want to go
And it's gonna be the case that if Alice looks at her coin
She instantly knows what Bob's coin is alright?
She sees, if I got a dime he's got a penny
If I got a penny he's got a dime
That in itself is not surprising, there is nothing
In the past they work together some correlation is established
Now what was the correlation?
The correlation was a correlation that if Alice has a dime
Then Bob has a penny and vice versa
No other possibilities were possible
So there is a correlation between Alice's coin and Bob's coin
And there wasn't any anti-correlation
If we call heads and tails plus one and minus one
Then if Alice is plus one Bob is minus one
But the opposite is also possible, I don't know it advents
And yet when Alice's far away and Bob is far awy
Alice look at the coin, and she instantly knows what Bob's is
I assure you that does not violate the special theory of relativity
And this kind of correlation is a,
this is called the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen correlation, or entanglement
It's the quantum version of that same nickel and dime story
Penny and dime story
>> You use nickel for real properties
There are certainly a difference
That's just statistical correlation, it's tremendously common things in physics
But just the idea that by looking at something at one place
You instantly know something you didn't know with regard to other place
There's nothing special about it
The question is what is it that special and different about this entanglement?
And that's where John Bell found something interesting
He didn't find non-locality,
we are gonna talk next time about what non-locality means in physics
And what is it exactly that John Bell found?
But I'm gonna tell you right now it was not non-locality
It looks like non-locality and the reason is
because you are trying to apply classical reasoning
What John Bell said is you can't apply classical reasoning to quantum systems
That's what it came down to
Quantum systems are quantum mechanical that
if you try to apply classical reasoning
You are going to find inconsistency
I can say in another way, I will tell you another way
There is a way to say it
Imagine you have a computer and you try to simulate on that computer
The quantum mechanics of a single spin
Here's the way that you simulated
You would be able to instruct the computer to orient it's apparatus
in an arbitrary direction,
in other words you would put in coordinates for a direction
And when you put in the coordinates for a direction
That computer would do some calculation appeal to random number generator
And spit out a plus one or a minus one
There will be an algorithm that would say that
if you do it over again immediately
It will spit out the same number again
That if you do it again, it will spit out the same number again
But you might then say, alright now let me make it more interesting
By adding in a mathematical magnetic field
Which allows the spin to process
What would you do? The computer would solve the Schrodinger equation
Find out what the state was after a little bit of time
Calculate the probability for up and down
Or whatever you decide to measure
Calculate the probabilities appeal to the random number generator
And spit out a number that was statistically exactly what you should get
on the average for the quantum mechanics
Somebody who came to this computer and started playing with it
And doing this experiment, rotating this apparatus in different directions
Turing on magnetic fields on other directions
Waiting various amount of time
And then telling the computer measure this or that component
would reproduce exactly quantum mechanics
At least to the extent that random number generator are possible
They are not exactly possible
but you know you can make pretty good random numbers
Alright so that would be a quantum, that wouldn't be a quantum computer
That would be a classical computer simulating quantum behavior
Whereas somebody doing experiment on it can be fooled into thinking
that it's actually dealing with the single electron inside the computer
And doing a quantum experiment, you couldn't tell the difference
Now the question is could you do the same thing for two spins?
In particular I want to do the same thing for two spins
And I want to do in such a way that one of the spins
If all of it's data is located in one computer
And all of the data for the other spin is located in the other computer
Now I can bring the computers together
Have wires connecting them and so forth for a while
Do arbitrary things and then cut the wires and separate them
Can I simulate the quantum mechanics of the two particle system
In such a way that it would appear that one of the computer contains one particle
And the other computer contains the other particle
Now this is a classical computer, two classical computers
And the answer is the only way you could do it
would be to have wires connecting the computers at all times
You could not do it unless the computers
are capable of interacting directly out of distance
But that does not mean that the system is non-local
Non-local means the signal can propagate from one place to another
What it's telling you is you simply can't simulate quantum mechanics
in a local way by a classical computer
The logic of quantum mechanics is different
It's simply does not allow itself to be fake by a computer
unless that computer is connected
over large distances to everything in the world
Quantum mechanics managed to do the same thing
without having wires connecting things
However you could ask the question does that constitute what physicists call
non-locality, or what Einstein would have called non-locality
It does not, it does not constitute in any way the ability
to send a message from one place to another
But we are gonna come to that, we will deal with that
No it is fundamentally the inability to simulate quantum mechanics
by classical computers,
unless the classical computers are hook up in highly un-local ways
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu