Stanford University
Alright  we start to explore entanglement
I had actually started to think about doing Bell's theorem  this  tonight
But I decided not to do it yet
It's a complicate story  it  the Bell's theorem
It's very lovely
But more important thing that the theorem itself is what it says
So I wanted to get as much as possible tonight to what it says
And what entanglement has to tell us about the nature of systems
Sometimes people say the nature of reality
I don't like the word reality
I think it's misleading
Ok  um  if you look on the Internet
And the messages you guys send back and forth
They are very interesting
many of them have some very interesting points of them
There is terminology which I would discourage
at least you know what I mean with greater precession
And I see that's all over the place
People say entanglement a share
when two quantum system share the same sharing state
I never understood what that means to share a state
Um  quantum systems have states
If they are composite quantum systems  they have states
You can say that quantum systems
a pair of quantum systems
when they make giving quantum systems share a state if you like
But it just means a state of composite system
The important idea about entanglement
is not so much that systems share a state
That they always do
It's the important thing that they are not described by a product state
A product state being a state in which the wavefunction of the system
And we will talk about wave
Have we talked about wavefunctions very much?
I don't think we have
Let's begin by talking about wavefunctions
And then I want to move the concept of density matrix
This would make it much easier for us to think about entanglement
First of all  notion of wavefunction
A wavefunction may or may not have anything to do with waves
The concept grew historically out of the quantum mechanics of particles
and relation of probability description of them in terms of waves
but the  the logical concept of a wavefunction
is one that you can apply to any quantum system
and in general it doesn't have to do
with wave motion of any particular kind
The basic idea of a wavefunction is following
You have a quantum state
Let's call the quantum state  capital Psi
I'll use the letter capital Psi to denote a generic quantum state of the system
I think previously I've been using As Bs
But I am starting to use Psi
As a generic quantum state  pretty much any system
and also I have a basis system
The basis system is typically labeled
by a collection of eigenvalues of something
It might be labeled by one or more variables
If there are several commuting operators in the system
you can specify simultaneously the eigenvalues of more than one thing
and in many cases  you want to do that
In the basis vectors in those cases are labeled
by a collection of observables
or collection of eigenvalues of perhaps several quantities
I'll give you an example
If you're talking about the motion of a particle
then the X and Y and Z coordinates of a particle are commuting variables
The things that don't commute are the components of momentum
with the components of position
I know we haven't done this yet
But the other hand
the three components of positional commute with each other
That means they can be specified simultaneously
A useful basis for studying the quantum mechanics of a particle
is a basis which is labeled by the three coordinates of the particle
We've  I'll give a hand
Alright  so we have a basis
And the basis is labeled by a collection of eigenvalues
Let's labeled them
This don't have a decent pen
Alright  a b c  however many commuting variables
there are that need to be specified in order to specify a system
and the inner product of the basis vector
with the state of the system itself is called the wave function
In fact we can write that psi since these objects here form a basis
we can say that this is a sum
I still don't have a decent pen?
A little bit better
For sum over the basis vectors
which means a sum over this collection of eigenvalues a b¡­
of the inner product of the basis vectors with the state vector
times the basis vectors
I've rewritten this equation is kind of equation down before
What it says is that the expansion coefficients
that you use to expand a vector in basis vectors are
just the inner products of the vector with the basis vectors
this subject is called the wave function right here
and it's a function of the a's b's and c's
So let's give it a name
Let's call a little psi of abc and so forth
It's called the wave function
and defined in such a way that the state vector psi
is equal to the sum of a of all the indices
which takes the specified the basis
times psi of a b and c and so forth
Psi of a b and c of coordinates  of the coordinates
An example if we just talking about a single spin
Then  in a complete set of commuting variables necessary
to specify a vector
is for example just Sigma Z  Z component of a spin
and the psi would just be the probability amplitudes
for the spin to be up or the spin to be down
the function of one variable that variable take on the values up and down
if we had two spins then we would label a basis of vectors with ups
for once up and down for one spin ups and downs for the other spin
and we'll take two labels to label a state vector  not just one
The two labels would be the labels of the two spins
and that's all I we were talking about here
might take multiple labels to label a spin at the labels basis vector
and if so just display them here and then by definition
this pure definition the wave function of the system
You can think of it two ways
You can think of it as the set of coefficients
The set of coefficients that you use to expand an arbitrary vector
in terms of the basis vectors
Or you can think of them as the inner products
the inner products of the state vector with the basis vectors themselves
That is called the wave function
And Schrodinger's wave function is a special case of it
which we will not get to for the moment
but it is a special case of it
Question? Okay
So if you know the wave function of the system
you know its state vector and you can compute all sorts of things
You can compute expectation values and all sorts of things
Yeah?
>>This looks like a little like Fourier transform in some basis
>>Is Fourier transform?
Yeah  it is a Fourier transform for the case of position momentum  yes
>>So that can be going back and forth
The Fourier transform is going back and forth
between different basis sets  okay?
Here  have chosen a particular basis set
Supposing I want to use a different basis instead of Sigma Z Sigma X
Then I would have to transform these wave functions somehow
they look different in the X basis and that's
that's the analog of Fourier transform
okay
Now I want to introduce a concept called the density matrix
If we have just a single system
this is the way we think about the state of the system
Let's talk about expectation values
Supposing we have some observable  let's call it L
It's some observable and it has matrix elements
What does matrix elements mean
They mean  if this is a basis vector
I won't bother writing out multiple labels
Let's just put one label L summarizing all labels
and another label over here a prime
These are called the matrix elements of the observable
The matrix elements of the observable
observable acts on a basis vector
and then you project it onto one of the basis vector
and that's called L  I suppose a prime a
Just notation
Okay now supposing I want to calculate the expectation value of L
in a state whose wave function is psi
Let's see how we do that
We take a psi
I am going to as I said
I'm just going to restrict myself to a single  a single a here
but the same thing withhold the multiple a's
So what we do we take the state vector on the left  the ket vector
the ket vector  maybe we should write up a vector here
Sorry  the bra vector  bra vector  this is the ket vector
The bra vector is the sum over a and b
But you know I want to use different indices here
I want to call them a prime and b prime
They being summed over so it does matter what I call them
I just don't want to confuse with these
and then we are going to have our bra vectors a b c all
times  I am putting a psi here  psi star
So exactly the same kind of expression for the bra vector
except complex conjugate it coefficients
Good  now let's calculate psi L psi
That's the expectation value
or the average value of L in the quantum state psi
And we do it just by plugging in
The left bra vector here is the sum of single index
a prime  a prime  psi of a prime that constructs the bra vector
The ket vector I will have to write another sum
a sum over a  psi of a times a
Summing on a turns this into the ket vector psi  capital psi
Summing over a prime turns us into the bra vector
the corresponding bra vector
and in between we sandwich L
Now  hu  somebody please correct me what I write that wrong
Psi star
We take the psi's and the psi stars out of the expression
They're just numbers and so the whole thing is sum of a prime and a
Psi star of a prime  psi of a times the inner product
or the sandwich a prime L a
That's exactly the matrix element of L between a and a prime
So that's L which one is a prime a I think
And  this reduces every expectation value to a calculation
in terms of wave functions a psi  with a psi or with a psi star
times a matrix element of the observable that were interested in
So this is the basic formula for the expectation value of anything
that we might be interested in
Basically all of quantum mechanics is contained in there
the expectation value of everything in the world
That's  that's just about everything we ever may want to be interested in
And so let's put this equation over here and keep it over here
Now supposing we have a composite system
composed of two subsystems  let's call them Alice's and Bob's subsystems
Alright  Alice has control of one of them
Bob has control of the other
and maybe even there are times when
when they don't have control of them
but we just call them 2 subsystems  Alice's and Bob's
In fact let's use a now
to represent a complete set of observables for Alice's subsystem
Everything that Alice needs to know
in order to specify a basis for her subsystem
And b are the set of variables for Bob's subsystem
When we talk about spin I think
we called Alice's variable Tau and Bob's variable Sigma
if I remember correctly
but we just  these are a complete set of things
A complete set of variables for Alice
and this is a complete set of variables for Bob
Alice's states for her subsystem would look like this
Bob's would like that
we may use a different notation
so we don't wind up confusing to two vector spaces
But then this is a composite vector space
The composite vector space is the vector space
describing the composite system
and that has a basis which consists of an a and b
when a runs over all its values and B runs of all its values
We have a complete basis of the combined system
Okay so now let's talk about wave functions of the composite system
Again we have a state vector
The state vector psi is a state vector
in the composite in the tensor product space
The space made by tensor producting a's and b's together
It has  as its basis vectors
a basis vector from a and a basis vector from b
And now I want to define in the same way
the notion of a composite wave function
So what is it? It's just the inner product of psi with the basis vectors
And what's the function of?
Its now a function of two sets of variables  of two variables
psi of a and b  different b here
This  we are okay  here it is
It's a function of the variables of the two subsystems
It depends on two of them
Okay  that's the wave function
Now we have notion of a wave function of a composite system
And let's talk about observables of a composite system
The observables of a composite system
first of all among those variables are the ones
which would describe the separate subsystems by themselves
So let's suppose that L and M are two observables
One of them having to do with Alice's subsystem  Alice
and the other one having to do with Bob subsystem
I could call them L sub a and L sub b
But I want to go call them L and M
How do we represent observables acting on the composite space of states
The answer is simple
The operators associated with Alice's subsystem
act on Alice's piece of the state vector
and leave Bob's piece of the state vector unchanged
That's all we did when we did spins
we said Bob's Sigma matrices acted on his half of the wave function
or his half of the basis vectors
and were completely passive or Alice's pieces of the state vector
was completely passive just bypassed by these operators
So what that says  what that says is that Alice's observables are matrices
The matrices that can be written as L of a prime b prime  just like L here
has a prime variable and unprimed variable
But now the single index is replaced by two indices and a and b
What does this correspond to?
This corresponds to the sandwich a prime b prime L a b
Whatever a  whatever a stands for
But L only belongs to Alice's space of states
only belongs to Alice's system
So the question is what then do we say about this matrix here to say
to indicate that it has no effect on Bob's variables
Answer is simple
We make it proportional to the identity matrix in Bob's variables
The identity operator  identity operator in a space is the operator
whose matrix elements are the Kronecker Delta symbol
That's the identity operator
And the identity operator on a subsystem does nothing to that subsystem
The identity operator simply gives the same vector back
In other words if you apply the identity operator it does nothing
But now what we are doing is applying the identity operator
on Bob's half of the system
but the observable that supposed to be associated
with Alice's half of the subsystem
is represented by the same matrix that she would've used
as she have not even known about Bob
As she have not even known about Bob
she would've used the matrix a L a prime and a to describe her observable
how does she describe it in the bigger Hilbert space?
She says it does nothing to Bob's variables
and so it's just the identity matrix and Bob's half of the space
That's Alice's variables
We can say the same thing about Bob's
M of a prime and b prime and a and b
just equal to the Kronecker  Delta of Alice's variables
times the matrix that Bob would've used
to describe the subsystem having not known anything about Alice
Okay  let's prove some things about the about the setup here
First of all  let's calculate
expectation values of Alice's variables in a product state
A product state is one
in which the two systems are not entangled with each other
unless you  what we get
What would you expect to get if you have in un-entangled state
describing Alice's and Bob's subsystems
and you consider the expectation value of Alice's variable
We get exactly what you've gotten  had Bob not been there all together
So let's check that out
What do I mean first of all by a product state?
I explained the product state was
But now let me explain what a product state is
in the language of wave functions  is very simple
It  means that the wave function is a product of two wave functions
one from Alice and one from Bob
That's all it means
A product state is one whose wave function psi of a and b
Alice's and Bob's variables  is just a product
So let's see how shall we denote that
Let's call it  well let's just call it psi Alice of A and phi Bob of B
It factorizes
It's a product of two functions
It's a function of two variables
but it's a product of two functions each of one variable
it's pretty clear that if you factorizes like this
then Alice can think of this as the wave function for her subsystem
and Bob thinks of this as the wave function for his subsystem
Okay  let's calculate now Alice's expectation value of L
if this happens to be the wave function
So what do we do? We first takes psi
We are going to make a sandwich
We are making a sandwich
with the psi star on one side the psi on the other side
and L in between
So that's psi star  that's psi star of Alice of a prime
Phi star Bob of b prime
This is  where we write it? Here
That's the complex conjugate of the wave function
As a function of a prime b prime
What next?
Next we put in to the sandwich L of a prime b prime a and b
It's a matrix
One entry here  one entry here
But it's simple
It's just L of a prime and a times Delta b b prime
and then we close it up with the other half of the sandwich
which is this up here  psi A of a  phi B of b
Now we sum  as always we sum over everything in sight
a prime  a  b prime  b
That's the rule for calculating an expectation value
So what do we get?
First of all the Delta b b prime  that tells us to set b prime equal to b
So let's do that
First of all  let's do that
I'll just erase
So b prime equal to b
Alright  I'll let you write down your notes if you want
So b prime equal to b and remove the Kronecker Delta
Now b is equal to b prime
Then notice the only thing it depends on B is phi star B and phi B
What the sum over b prime was done when I said b equal to b prime
Then we sum over be of phi star phi
What does that give?
One
Under the assumption of course that Bob's wave functions is normalized
Under the assumption that Bob's half of the way functions is normalized
So that his total probability for his all his measurements
he could do is one
Then sum over b of phi star of B times phi of B is just one
And what does the whole thing reduce to?
The whole thing reduces to exactly what's up there
We can remove the phi's
Take them out  bring down here
That sum was just one  and the rest of it is just exactly
what's up on the top of the blackboard there
Another words in a product state the expectation value
of any of Alice's operators are exactly the same
as if Bob wasn't there
And it doesn't matter what Bob's wave function is
as long as it's a product
What about the one of Bob's expectation values
Or what happens if we stuck a  Bob operator in there?
Well  then instead of the Kronecker Delta of b-s
let's go back b and b prime
the b and b prime  b and b prime  b prime over here
And instead of L  in a prime  L we would have M of b and b prime
Delta a  a prime
and now we would set a prime equal to a
Sum  that would again give us one
and we will get the same
We'll get basically the same thing that I wrote up here
Bob  except it would be Bob's wave function phi star
Bob of b prime  M of b prime  b  times phi Bob of b
which is exactly what Bob would've done
had not known about Alice
So product states are really just that the states
in which one party just doesn't know about the other
is no correlation  is no information in one of them about the other
Ok. We can say a little bit more about correlation
Let's suppose now what that we are interested in
the product of an Alice variable and a Bob variable
we are interested in the expectation value of L times M
Let's see what we get
Expectation in a product state  strictly product state for the moment
We go back up to here
and now instead of writing M b   this should be b  b prime
This should be b prime
Instead of Delta of a and a prime  if we would take the product of L and M
Then what I put here?
L
If I'm interested in the operator
which represents the product of two variables
One for Alice and one for Bob
instead of putting the unit operator up here for Alice
I will simply put in Alice's operator  not M  L
Now this just factorizes
Let's look at all the a dependence
Here's a dependence
That factorizes let's completely separate from the b dependence
I could take everything with a b dependence
and put on one side
Everything with an a dependence put on the other side
and do the a and b summations independently
Can you see that? That  let's write that out
Sum of a prime  a  b prime  b  of psi Alice star of a prime L a a prime
psi Alice of a
all times phi Bob star of b prime  M of  b  b prime and phi of b
The sums can be done quite independently
We can put the sum over here
Same thing  I haven't changed it  with summing over everything
b's and a's
And we see all we get is just a product
We get the product of the expectation value of L
times the expectation value of M
Not surprising if we have a product state
and Alice does her measurement and Bob does his measurement
and we then come together and compare the measurements
and ask what was a product of the measurements
The expectation value will just be the product
The expectation value of the product operator
will be the product of expectation values
We can write this this way
Let's write it in a form for product states
for product  let's call product states
The expectation value of L and times M
Now remember L belongs to Alice  M belongs to Bob
and they operate in different halves of the system
The expectation value of L times M
is just the expectation value of L times the expectation value of M
Now  is this something that we expect always be true for every state?
That the expectation value in fact even in classical probability theory
if we have a probability distribution for two variables
in general is it true that the average of the product
is the product of the average?
>>The variables are already there
Which means what becomes of the probability distribution
>>Exactly what you've written there
It means that factorizes
It means the probability distribution
is the product of 2 probability distributions
Alright  well  what if it's not true?
What if the probability distribution does not factorize
Then this quantity here
The difference between the average of L times M
And the product of averages of L and M
is called the correlation between L and M
is called the correlation
and is a measure of how much these variables are correlated
We will see some examples
This is called correlation and whenever the correlation
whenever there is anything in the system
and Alice variable and a Bob variable
whose correlation is not zero
That's an indication of entanglement
If you can find any pair of variables
one of Alice's and one of Bob's
such that the average of the product is not the product of the averages
Then you're experiencing entanglement
I think we did an example last time
We took what I call the singlet state
which was up down minus down up over the square root of two
This is psi and this is not a product state
and in the state we took the expectation value of Bob's variable  Sigma Z
We took the expectation value of Alice's variable
which I think was Tau Z
You remember what these were?
What's the average value of Bob's variable?
Let's say the first entry here  the first entry stands for Bob
is Bob  Bob  this is Alice
Well what would you guess in the state the average of Sigma Z is?
Not the state  but the combined state
>>Zero
No.
Zero? Why is zero?
Because it has as much probability of being up as being down
Has probability one over
has probability one half to be up and one have to be down
So the average of Bob's variable is zero
I think we work that out last time
What about Alice's variable?
It's also up as much as it's down
It's also expectation values zero
What about?
So first step  both of these are zero in this case
What about the product?
What about the product of Sigma Z and Tau Z?
What its average value?
Well  we worked that out last time
We've gotten the answer
Anybody remember the answer?
>>Minus one
Minus one
But you can just look at this thing
and you can say in both vectors here  the spins are opposite
So in either case here  the product of the spins is minus one
It's pretty clear that this whole thing is an eigenvector of the product
because on either vector here  the product is minus one
Act with Sigma Z  you get  you know what would happen
So you'll just change sign
So yes this has the product of Sigma Z is equal to one
Minus one  excuse me
So they are entangled
In fact  in this case where we call maximally entangled
They are very entangled
If you can find any pair of variables
which are correlated in this form
the quantum state is entangled
Do you remember now here it's completely obvious
that the average of Sigma Z is zero
for just the reasons I said
For Sigma Z and Tau Z
Up appears as much is down for Bob
and down appears as much is up for Alice
and so it's clear the average is zero
What about the average of Sigma X? Do you remember?
Zero  but that's not obvious  is it?
That's not obvious
But we did it last time  go back to your notes
And you'll discover not only is the expectation value of Sigma Z zero
but Sigma X is also equal to zero  the average
On the other hand you also find
that the product of Bob Sigma X and Alice's Tau X
is again equal to minus one
So the Sigma Z's and the Tau Z's are correlated
Sigma X's and the Tau X's correlated
and what about Y? same thing
Same exact thing
You work that out
We know what these operators do
You can apply them to the states
and calculate what the expectation value is
So the state is a highly  a highly entangled  a highly correlated state
being correlated and being entangled are basically the same idea
>>Question?
Yeah?
>>In the general case  if you put the L in the end of M
>>say equal to each other
>> put the L in the M's  LM
>> minus bracket L bracket M equals ML minus the second  (mumble)
No
>> It just put the L in the end
Oh  yeah
>>That's equal  right?
You can show
>>Ok. So
Alright
It's a point there which I may not mention
All operators are associated with one system
commute with all operators associated with the other system
So it doesn't matter in which order you write them
That's independent of whether the system is entangled
It doesn't the matter which order you write them
>>Excuse me
Yeah?
>>I guess I am missing something
>>When you wrote that down
>>you show how the state if you have a product state that
>>when L is a state in Alice's M
Yeah  then this is equal to zero
>>And that's equal to zero
>>What does L M mean? Is that a product state?
This? No
>>What is it? In general
The state is  these are the states
These are the observables
>>Right?
Right
>>Isn't that LM a product state?
No. L's and M's are not states
>>Observables
Yeah  there are psi's in here
>>Ok
This is the statement about the state vectors
Right
Ok  one other point is what just noticing
When I say things are correlated  the spins are correlated
I mean it  what I mean is that you can learn something
about one variable by looking at the other
If you know this is a state  if you happen to know that this is the state
then if you know Bob's  if you measure Bob's variable
and you find out that it's up then in that component of the state
which is the only one left at the measure Bob
Alice is down
In a product state  you learn nothing about one system
by measuring anything about the other
In a highly entangled state you learn a great deal about one system
by measuring the other one
That's what entanglement means
In the other hand  it may also follow  it may also be true
that in a highly entangled state before hand
if you happen to know the state
you may know very little about each individual piece
For example in the singlet state here
there is  what is it the probability that Bob's variable is up
One half
What is the probability Bob's variable is down
So when the state knowing  knowing everything about the state
you still know nothing about whether Bob measures up or down
if he does the measurement
Curious  you know nothing at all
about whether Bob measures up or down
You know nothing at all about
what Alice measures up or down
But you know everything about the product of them
that if Bob does his measurement  Alice does her measurement
and you compare them afterwards every single time
If this is the state that you put the system into
the product will be minus
So this is an example of this odd thing quantum mechanics
You can know everything about a composite system
and know nothing about the pieces
That's what this is telling you
You know everything  when I say you know everything
I mean you know as much as quantum mechanics allows you to know
This is the state of the system
you are not gonna do any better than that
That's all there is to know about it
What you know about it is that Sigma times Tau
whether will it be Sigma X or Tau X
It is true for the XY or Z component separately
that the product of Alice's variable and Bob's variable is minus one
That's a lot to know
But it's not as much as you would know classically
Classically  if you know everything about a system
you would know everything about the constituents
as well as things that you could measure about that
you could combine together
In quantum mechanics you can't know
Either you can say you can't know everything
or to the extent that everything is everything you can know
In this case  you know everything about the combined system
and you know nothing about its constituents
That's the really odd thing about entanglement
That's extremely odd property of quantum mechanics
That allows such nonsense
>>With that speech you can't separate the components of the system
>>without information gotten from each other?
Yeah  yeah  it does mean that
>>When you write LM  I am gotten confused
>>Is that measure M and then measure L?
No  no  no
>>It's the product L and M?
Ok  let's be very clear
Let's be very clear
The operation  the operation mathematical operation
of multiplying a state vector by an operator
is not that anything to do with the actual physical act of measuring it
>>I know  but the syntax looks the same
The syntax is not the same
The syntax  I'm not sure what syntax means
I assume it means the words
>>It just means how interprete M and L on the board  that's all
>>The product of the operators
Yes  yes  it means you act first with M and then L
>>Ok
>>That's enough
Yeah  but it doesn't mean you've measured them
That means is just a mathematical thing  right?
The same is true in the classical mechanics
I can multiply the momentum of something by the position of something else
That doesn't mean I measure them
just because of I multiply the two things together
Physical act of measurement
It's not the operators which act on the states
It's the detectors or apparatuses which act on the system
So in words when you do a measurement
a detector or an apparatus acts on the system and gives result
In the space of states  a operator acts on a vector
not a detector acting on the system
Quite different concepts
Yeah?
>>If we make a measurement on electrons
>>unless we already know how it's been prepared
>>which is a special case
>>In that case we can describe the state
>>as linear combination of basis vectors
Yeah
>>But  before we make a measurement  we might know nothing about
>>We might know a little bit about it
>>No matter how much we know  we have to
>>expressed in terms of probabilities
>>Not in terms of the vectors?
Yes
>>And so in case there's a correlation between two electrons
>>Let's say it's not a pure correlation
>>It's a partial
>>It's not a product
>>It's not an truly intrinsic state in somewhere between
It's not a what?
>>A singlet state  for example
It's a somewhat entangled state
>>Exactly
>>So  if  then after we make the Sigma measurement
>>and we want to describe the Tau of electron
>>we still have to describe Tau in terms of probabilities
>>You wouldn't be able to specify in terms of a combination
Ok. I am not exactly sure what you are getting yet
But maybe this will help
If we have the quantum state of a single spin
Let's suppose somebody told us
what the state of the quantum state of the spin was
then for any quantum state there is always an observable
in particular some component of Sigma
which is definite  which is predictable
Every part  that's obvious for the states up and down
It's obvious for the states left and right
To the state up if you measure Sigma Z is definite
If you measure  if you know that the state is right
and you measure Sigma X  it's definite
This is more general
Given any quantum state whatever of the spin
there exists a direction that you can prove
that there exists direction for which the spin is definite  okay?
Curiously when you combine the system together into
an entangled state like this
There is no direction in which the spin is definite
In fact there is no direction Sigma X for one of the spins
Each one of the spins either Alice's or Bob's
has average value zero in every direction
No matter what direction you pick  X  Y  Z or anything in between
the average of the spin the Bob's spin in the state is zero
so  in his quantum state in which Bob can say nothing
what he cannot know what quantum state fully
and as I said has equal probability for up and down in every direction
I'm not sure if that's what you're addressing or not
>>My question in that show if you have a partial correlation
Partial  Ok
>>Somewhere between zero and one
So we put a big number here and a small number here
>>We measured one and
>>then the other quickly expressed as pure probability
>>as Sigma X and Sigma Y
Yes  we can calculate all the probabilities  calculate them  yeah
Okay
>>Did you remind us the physical
What is that?
>>the singlet state
Say it again?
>>What would be inventible physical experiment
>>corresponds to singlet state?
Good  that's an obviously important question
Another way to ask is how would you prepare a state
a system in the singlet state
Alright  I'll tell you have something about the singlet state
The singlet state has the property
that it's an eigenvector of a certain operator
It's eigenvector many operators
but in particular it's an eigenvector of Sigma X Tau X
You can prove it
It's actually an eigenvector of Sigma X Tau X
It's an eigenvector of Sigma Y Tau Y
And it's an eigenvector of Sigma Z Tau Z
What's the eigenvalue for each one of these?
Minus one  and the eigenvalues are the same for all of them
That means that it's an eigenvector of any linear
any combination of these with eigenvalue minus one
Any one of them acts on the singlet state
gets back minus the singlet state
Any combination of them will get back minus singlet state
So in particular if I take this object here
the singlet state is also an eigenvector of this
Now this is a funny thing
Alice and Bob can't easily measure this whole quantity here
Why? because Alice can't measure Tau X and Tau Y simultaneously
By separate measurements  this would be hard to measure
It can't be measured by separate measurements
Why? Because no separate measurement
can measure Tau X and Tau Y at the same time
or Tau Z at the same time
But this object is a perfectly good Hermitian operator
and there must exist a way of measuring it
But more to the point right now
there's a way of preparing a state
which is an eigenvector of this
Now  what's state?
The singlet state
The singlet state is an eigenvector of the object
with eigenvalue minus three
It's an eigenvalue of this one with minus one  this one with minus one
and this one with minus one
The whole thing has eigenvalue minus three
The point is the eigenvectors of this product  of a sum of products here
include the the singlet state is a particular one
You can also write this
It's just Sigma dot Tau
Sigma X Tau X  Sigma Y Tau Y   Sigma Z Tau Z
that uses ordinary classical vectors you are writing Sigma dot Tau
Now if you take two electrons  each one has a spin
In a very very far apart  they don't interact with each other
There is no energy associated with the interaction between them
But as you bring them together  there are all sorts of energies
One energy for example is just Coulomb energy between them
Product of the charges
There is also an energy associated with the spins
and one of the terms of the energy associated with the spin
is just the dot product of the spins
The spins are aligned  you get
If this is aligned  you get one value
If this is anti-aligned  you get the other value
Ang so Sigma dot tau is a piece of the Hamiltonian of the two spin system
In the singlet state  it's minimum
The three other states called the triplet states
in which it is maximum
So the energy is lowest in the singlet state
The spins are trying to get anti-aligned with each other
But in every direction  not just the z direction  every direction
and eventually compromise on the singlet state
So you have two energy levels associated with the spin of an electron
These two energy in hydrogen
Or in a Positronium   even better
In Positronium  you have the aligned and anti-aligned spins
and they have different energy levels  singlet  triplet
If you bring two electrons together
then any state can be written in terms of the singlet triplet states
Even a product state can be represented as a sum of singlet triplet states
What happens when you bring electrons together after a period
if they are in the triplet state with the high energy?
What happens the higher energy states after a while?
They emit a photon and go to the lower energy state
So if you take two spins which may be in a product state
And  you bring them together and wait a long time
a photon may or may not be admitted
If the system is in the singlet state  no emission
If it's in the triplet state it emits  gives off a photon
and winds up in the singlet state
So this would be a way of preparing the system
in the singlet state
We just take the two electrons and wait until they radiate a photon
Wait long enough  they do or don't radiate a photon
But if you wait long enough  you'll know that it's in the singlet state
So that's A experiment  that's an experiment
Another way  now this one so this one is very very far-fetched
extremely far-fetched
The energy in the singlet state is less than the energy
and the other three states
There are four possible states altogether
four possible basis states singlet and three triplet
The energy of the singlet is lowest
So you just take your composite system
and you put it on a scale and you measure its mass
Mass is energy
When you measured its mass
you measured whether it's energy is the energy of the singlet state
or the triplet state
and that constitute a measurement or constitutes a preparation device
are measurement of   basically its variable
but if you like the difference between singlet triplet
So  yeah  there are ways of preparing systems in the singlet or triplet
in singlet state
Always  in fact  if you bring the systems together and you wait a while
it's very difficult to have anything but the singlet state
Then once you've made that singlet state
if you grab the electrons without turning the spins
if you grab them somehow in a way
that doesn't put any torque on the spins and pull them apart
You now have two separate electrons for example  in the singlet state
So it's not a terribly hard thing to do
>> With the spin value  actual you can assign the energy to the entanglement
Yes  in this case  yes  in this case  yes
But  well you what you can say is the lower energy is certainly entangled
The lowest energy state  the one that seeks
the one to get to by
It doesn't have to be radiating a photon
Any mechanism by which the system can lower its energy
emitting a phonon   or doing interacting with the crystal lattice
anything to lower its energy will leave in the singlet state
So I think the right thing to say is
that the lower energy state is entangled
That's almost always the case
that the states of lowest energy are highly entangled between systems
Okay  so we  next question  is there a measure
a quantitative measure of the degree of entanglement
is there a way of taking a state and determining whether it's an entangled
and to measure how much entangled
That brings us to a concept called the density matrix
which I am probably gonna
It's getting later than I thought so I want to go over this little quickly
but I think we can we can do it
Let's define an object called Alice's density matrix
Alice's density matrix is a quantity
which even in an entangled state is as complete a description
of Alice's system for the purposes of Alice's measurements
as Alice can ever get
It's not a wave function if it was unentangled
the wave function would be the best description she could have
But for an entangled system you cannot extract out
a wave function for either piece of the entangled system
The best you could do is something called the of the density matrix
We actually had it up here
Let me go back to it
Let's talk about all of Alice's experiments
that she can do without measuring anything
about Bob's electron or Bob's system
Let's imagine they separated the systems
Bob has his Alice has her
and Alice can do all the experiments she likes
and measure any one of these L observables
L standing for Alice  Ok
How does she describe all the possible expectation values of everything
that she can ever measure
So we had a formula before
I am going to rewrite it
Expectation value of L is psi star of alpha prime  Beta prime
Or a prime  b prime
This is the combined system
We are going back to the combined system now
L a prime a psi a b
But we set b is equal to b prime
Or we like  we can leave the b prime here
And put a Kronecker Delta b and b prime
This is one of Alice's variables  and so as far as Bob goes
it's just a unit operator
It does nothing for Bob's piece of the wave function
and that just says  stick b equal to b prime
Okay look at this quantity right over here
Let's take L on the outside
Let's take L of a prime and a out there  isolated off
We have to sum this over b
We sum over everything
We sum this over b and here is a quantity right here
that depends on a prime a and a multiply something else
that depends on a and a prime
But it doesn't depend on b   we've summed over b
Once you summed over b  it doesn't depend on b anymore
So this object over here is a function
only of Alice's coordinates a and a prime
It of course to calculate it
you may have to know more about the wave function
But once you've calculated it
that's all that Alice ever needs to know
to calculate anything about her half of the system
So let's give it a name
It's the sum over b  psi star of a prime b  psi of a b
It doesn't depend on b degrees of freedom at all anymore
Bob's degrees of freedom
It's called the density matrix
That's a function  a thing which depends on a prime and a
It's a matrix  it's a matrix that has two entries
Any matrix can be thought of as a function of a row and a column
This is a density matrix
and if we know the density matrix
it doesn't matter where it came from
It doesn't matter what Bob state was if we know row in a row
Then we know that the expectation is right the formula
The expectation value of L is equal to
the sum of rho of a prime and a  L of a and a prime
I think I have one of them backwards
It doesn't matter
So Alice  if she knew this density matrix
could forget about Bob completely
and say I know everything there is to know about my subsystem
and here it is  Ok
What is rho of a and a prime if we start with a pure state
Supposing we started with a pure state
You are getting exhausted?
No? This is quantum mechanics for you  sorry  but this is it
>> (laugh)
I can't make it easier
This is the easiest I can make it
Alright  you are going to sit down with it  you'll go through it
and penetrate it
But I'll do my best  okay.
This is the notion of density matrix
What if psi is a pure state?
What can we say about this density matrix?
So let's go back and see exactly what it says
If psi is  I am sorry
What if psi is a product state
If psi is a product state it means the wave function factorizes
So let's go back  here we are
Here is the density matrix
The wave function factorizes into  this is a b prime
That's right  that's correct
>>The density matrix you summed over a prime and a is a double sum
Not in the density matrix
>>Why
In this one  yes  it's a double sum
It's a double sum but only involves rho
So let's erase this for a moment
and see what we learn about this creature called the density matrix
if psi is a product vector
It must have is a special form somehow
So let's say that psi is a product of Alice's wave function
times Bob's wave function
I forget which one is which now
Was psi Alice or psi Bob?
Psi with Bob?
Psi is Alice  Ok
It doesn't matter  we can change it now
So the complex conjugate here is Alice's wave function times
This is not the wave function of Alice's
This is the wave function of Alice's spin  incidentally
But I will call it as Alice's wave function
Alice's wave function times Bob's wave function  the complex conjugate
And then we multiply that by the non complex conjugate of thing
Let me put them in the opposite order
Phi of b  notice we identified b with b here
It's not b and b prime  and this is prime  Psi a
Each one of these factorizes
this factorizes into a function of 'a prime' and b
And this one into a function of b and a
And now we sum over b
What does this sum of b? Of Phi star phi? One right?
Okay so now we can take this out  throw it out
And here is what we find  we find that for a product state
Only for product state
that Rho is simply made up out of Alice's half of the wave function
Without any regard to Bob  she doesn't need to know anything about Bob
This is not too surprising that she didn't need to know anything about Bob
After all it's a product wave function
And the density matrix is just a product of the complex conjugate
of the wave function with the wave function itself
Two different a-s though  an a and a prime
Alright what can we say about a matrix like this
Let's call this matrix  let's call it
I think it's actually Rho of  let's call it Rho of a and a prime
Just call it Rho of a and switch the order  but that's just the definition
Let's take this Rho  it's a matrix and act with it on a column vector
How do you act if you know the components of a matrix
How do you act on a column vector? So let's suppose this is a matrix
Ya Rho 11  just a second  Rho 12 so forth  Rho 21
we made a matrix out of it
>> Do you wanna erase the transformation sign there on the far?
Ya I do  good point  excellent
Alright so we have Rho  it's made up out of Alice's wave function
And I maintain that this density matrix
All of these matrix has an eigenvector
I maintain all over that there is one and only one eigenvector
With non zero eigenvalue
And that the eigenvalue is plus one  somebody say right? Good
Okay  let's prove it  I will tell you exactly what that eigenvector is
It's Psi a  it's Psi itself  so let's check that out
Let's multiply this by Psi of a prime in fact
And sum it over a prime  this is matrix
this is the process of multiplying a column vector by a matrix
That's the way you do it  you write down the matrix
You write down the column vector and you sum over the element between them
Okay let's see if we can see what we get
Oh this is the action of Rho on Psi  okay
So let's do it  Rho is Rho
Now let's multiply it by Psi of a prime
And now let's sum over a prime  what do we get?
Psi star of a prime times Psi of a prime sum over a prime is? One  right?
So it all comes out to just be Psi
So this is Psi
What does that tell you about eigenvector
and eigenvalues of the density matrix?
It tells you that the original wave function is
an eigenvalue of the density matrix of eigenvalue plus one
Let me prove now that all vectors perpendicular
There are n minus one if the dimensionality of the space is n
Then this is the one eigenvector out of n  which is eigenvalue one
Let's take any vector now which is perpendicular
which is orthogonal to Psi
To Psi a  to Alice's wave function
Let's call it Psi a tilde
tilde now means it's orthogonal to the original Alice' vector
Now what is this inner product? Zero right?
So we find out that Rho on Psi tilde is zero
That means any vector perpendicular to Alice's vector
is an eigenvector with eigenvalue zero
The original state of Alice's spin is an eigenvalue with plus one
Conclusion? The density matrix for a pure state has one
and only one non zero eigenvalue and it's equal to one
What if it's not a product state?
If it's not a product state then you will find a collection of eigenvalues
In fact in general there will be all of the eigenvalues
in general with non-zero
Of the density matrix  you can try this out for the two spin system
Work out the density matrix of Alice's spin
the density matrix for Bob's spin
And you will find out that they are quite different
They don't have the single eigenvector which is non-zero
They have a pair of eigenvectors which are non-zero
So what we learn is that this information in the density matrix
and in particular in the eigenvalues of the density matrix
Which tell you whether it's a great deal of entanglement or not
The more eigenvectors which are non zero
The more entangled it is
If there is only one eigenvector which is non zero
It's not entangled at all
And Alice's half of the wave function is just that eigenvector
If they are entangled then one finds the more they are entangled
the more eigenvalues you'll find
And the maximum entanglement is when all the eigenvectors are equal
When all the eigenvectors are equal  all eigenvalues
when all the eigenvalues are equal  that's maximal entanglement
Take the singlet state  work out the density matrix of Alice's spin
And what you will find is that it has two eigenvalues
Each of which is a half  equal and equal to a half
So that's a test  that's the way to test
whether the system does or doesn't have entanglement
Calculate the density matrix and study it's eigenvalues
The maximum entanglement is when they are all equal
When they are equal  they are equal to one over n  you can prove that
When n is the dimensionality of the space  one over n
Okay that's entanglement quantified
can even be a little more quantitative
Even be a little more quantitative
No  let's not do that now
I will write a more quantitative condition of notes
Let's very quickly go through the connection
between measurement and entanglement
There is a deep connection between measurement and entanglement
Basically measurement is the process of entangling
of starting with a product state  a product state of what and what
A product state of a system and the apparatus
The apparatus is in a definite state to begin with
And the system is in definite state
What state is the apparatus in?
Well  the apparatus might be something which detect something or other
and if it's not detecting  you might put it into some neutral state
some neutral state which is the starting state  the undetected state
the neutral state of the apparatus
And now you bring the system you are interested in
Right up to the apparatus  it does something to the apparatus
Something happens to the system itself
And what's left over is an entangled state between the two of them
So I'll give you an example
I'm going to think of the apparatus as a very simple system
With only two states
Let's  let me find my notes here
Ya  my system is a spin and my apparatus also happens
to have only two states
You can think of it as another spin if you like
In fact they could be Alice's and Bob's
But you could also think of it as a more complex system
But for simplicity it only has two states
Here's the apparatus  it has only two states  let's say zero and one now
Zero is the state before the apparatus is switch on  when it's switch on
It has not detected anything  it always starts out in the state zero
And if it's not in the state zero give it a shove
and put it in the state zero
Otherwise it's not  otherwise  you know
you have to start your apparatus in a know state
Otherwise you are not going to be able to do a measurement
So it has zero and one  for it starts out zero
And we have our spin  here's a spin
and we are gonna do a measurement on it
Supposing the spin is in the up state
and the apparatus of course begins in the zero state
So we represent that by a combined ket vector
A combined ket vector is in a tensor product of the spin Hilbert space
and the detector Hilbert space
Up and zero  if the spin comes in  to begin with down
And then you start out in the state down zero
Why? Because you start out with a detector in the neutral state
Now I'm not going to tell you in detail what the interaction is
between the detector and the spin
That could involve magnetic fields and other kinds of things
causing an influence between the detector
But I am going to tell you  that if you bring a spin into the detector
And then take a spin out of the detector
I'll tell you what state is left over
So in particular  and I am making this up of course
I am making up a rule which would be a good detector
Which would be a good detector
Namely  if the spin  if the system starts
that the combined system starts in the state |u zero>
Then the detector feels the spin and it jumps to state one
It goes to state |u one>
Nothing happens to the spin  it just activates the detector
On the other hand  if the spin is down  it doesn't activate the detector
That's my rule  so this goes to |down one>  no |down zero>  |down zero>
And that's a very good detector of up-ness and down-ness
But now let's start with a superposition of up and down
Let's take alpha up times |up> plus alpha down times |down>
Somebody now brought us a spin and they superposition its state
A general quantum state  but of course the detector starts out zero
So that's the starting state  what happens after the detector acts?
Well if the state is |u zero>  it goes to |u one>
So that means it goes to alpha sub u times |u one>
Plus alpha sub down |down zero>
This all of a sudden has become an entangled state
It's an entangled state if it's up  if the spin is up  the detector is up
The detector is one
If the spin is down  the detector is zero
That is an entangled state  why is it an entangled state
It's an entangled state because by looking at the detector
You can tell what the spin is doing
In fact that is what a measurement is
A measurement is an interaction between a system and an apparatus
that leaves the apparatus in a state that depends on the
whatever it is measuring about the system
So from one point of view you can just say
Well look  this is exactly what I knew a measurement always was
It just  it leaves
It's just the process that leaves a record
on the apparatus of what the initial state was
Of the spin  but from another point of view
It's the physics of a combined system
that combined system being a spin and the apparatus
Which leaves them in a highly entangled state
So entangled that by looking at the detector you can tell what the spin is
So entanglement and measurement are really the same thing
And in fact to measure a spin  you really only need another spin
And this detector here could just be a spin
And one and zero could be up and down
So we had this kind of concoction here where exactly this happen
It would take only one spin to be a detector or an apparatus
Which could measure another spin
But in general this is the nature of measurement
that it entangles system together
that entangles in particular apparatus with the system
Is that clear? It should be very clear  and that's all
That's one way of thinking about measurement
And in this language in which
you think of the system and the apparatus together
You never speak about the collapse of a wave function
You speak about the development of entanglement
If you don't want to include the apparatus into your system
Then the only thing to say is that after the experiment is done
The system is either up or down
And you get  which one do you pick? You pick the one that you record
But the one that you record is the one that recorded by the apparatus
So thinking about just the system by itself
You will have to have this rule that the wave function collapses
Thinking about the system plus apparatus  the same physics is described
by the development of entanglement between the system and apparatus
>> So in that case would be a mixed state  a lot of states
>> what can you see in the meter of the apparatus  the one that is zero?
Okay  now you are another detector  this is the hierarchy of detection
Or the hierarchy of the measurement
Here is the spin  here is the apparatus
But we are not finished  we still have to look at the apparatus
We haven't gotten any where until we look at the apparatus right?
Alright  well what's gonna happen?
Again we are gonna have to say when we look at the apparatus
We wind up collapsing the wave function
to one of these two pieces of the entangled states
Or we can say  include the eyeball into the system
In that case  we should have included another system here
The eyeball  and the eyeball  I don't know  how do they start?
It started  um
It also has two states
the two states correspond to the two possible answers
that the brain up there  there is also a brain up here >> oh no
Two states of the brain  one state of the brain says
I saw the apparatus with a zero
The other state of the brain says I saw the apparatus with a one
If we want to include the observer as well as the apparatus
We have to include another factor here
And that factor has to depend on the state of the brain
Let's call it b not  it starts b not
which is the brain before you look at anything
And then it goes to b one over here or b not over here
It's now become a system which is entangled with the eye and brain
You can say wait a minute now
We now have this entangled state we describe it all
by the quantum mechanics of the entanglement
between spin and apparatus  and then latter on between apparatus spin
and eyeball  it's all been described by quantum mechanics
But you may not be satisfied
You may worry about if other fellows who comes in  in the room
Takes a look  and asks you what did you see
So somebody else comes in  and ask you okay Charlie what did you measure?
And in the process  collapses the wave function of the spin  apparatus
What is it's name? Give it a name
No  no no  this is Charlie  he comes in afterwards
Wigner  Wiggy  there was a Wigner that says Schrodinger right?
So Schrodinger  I don't know  which one of these has ears
This is the atom  this is the atom
The cat  he doesn't look at the atom
But he gets hit  something happens  something happens to them on the atom
So here's the detector  the cat is the detector
Here Schrodinger who looks into the box
here's Wigner who looks at Schrodinger
And there is a hierarchy here  the hierarchy
where you decide to break the hierarchy?
Where you decide to break the hierarchy
determines at what stage you will say the wave function collapse?
If you like  I suppose at some stage
you would say the wave function collapse
When the last person look at it
But you could always include that last person into the system
Then no collapse happens
but then in order to make sense out of the whole thing
Again you have to imagine some other person
So you always have to imagine a hierarchy of observation
And then with such a hierarchy of observation
the world is built like a onion  things inside
next thing out  next thing out
And each things get to observed   what's the inside of it?
>>Question  what is the process
>>when we are moving with the classical world
>>and one of those people actually see definite items because
Well I don't know  I don't think there is any sharp line
I don't think there is any sharp line
We tend to describe a big system as having little uncertainty
but I'm not sure that anything really different happens
When a electron looks at another electron
Or when a cat looks at a electron
I think the physics or the mathematical description
I think it's the same description or at least
if we want to say something special happens when the cat looks
Well it's not well described by quantum mechanics
We have to introduce some thing about cats
that doesn't contain within quantum mechanics
And personally I don't believe
there is anything about cats which is not contained
within quantum mechanics
So I'm happy with this description
I'm happy with this description  what makes me happy is that
it doesn't matter where you draw the line
You can draw the line in one place or the next place or the next place
And the result would be consistent
If the cat saw the spin up
Schrodinger would see the cat having seen the spin up
And Wigner would have seen Schrodinger
having the cat having seen the spin up
That's what the nature of the state is
So that define satisfyingly
that you don't ever have to say where you draw the line
And until you draw the line  you would put the line as far out as you like
Until you draw the line  everything is described
by the rules of a conventional quantum mechanics
>> So unless you puts the cat  you definitely draw the line
Well okay  I mean  look I think at some stage
you have to decide for yourself how you think about this
I'm not going to try to push my interpretation of quantum mechanics on you
Particularly since  I don't know what to say about it except this
That seems to disturb a lot of people
This whole business of systems for which
you could know as much as can be known
And know nothing about the parts of the system
That seems to disturb people
Is it disturbing? I
When Finding() was asked whether he thought
there is a problem with quantum mechanics
he's answer was that the problem was so big
that you could tell if there is a problem
He knew how to use it  he knew how to predict with it
He could predict anything he wanted to predict
Though that have an answer and he didn't expect
I'm not actually speaking about myself now
But in for him
he did not expect the quantum mechanics would ever go wrong
That the rules would always be satisfied
but is there a problem because of this sense of unreality
about where actual objectively  where objectively does something happen
Does this objective 'death of the cat' happen
when the cat looks at the atom
Or is it when Schrodinger looks at the cat
Or was it Wigner looks at Schrodinger
Where does the objective phenomena happen?
And maybe we are just playing with words there
Maybe we are playing with words
trying to use words in a context where they don't apply
You have to decide that yourself  my goal is to give you the tools
to be able to ask the question
I doubt seriously you are gonna answer the question even for yourself
You would probably come away feeling as uncomfortable about it
But you will know why you are uncomfortable
You know what is it with some precision
that's making you uncomfortable about it
At least I hope  at least that's my goal
Alright
>> In the equation you dealt there with the eye
>> forget about Schrodinger  just the eye
>> the equation that you wrote implies there is a correlation
>> of one commutative state of system the apparatus
>> could (inaudible)  and the state of the eye
Ya so the eye has become entangled with the rest of the system
>> So it was as though your vision weren't so good
(laughing) that's what you call a weak measurement
Ya  look  that can happen that could be partial
It can be partial entanglement for sure
I've given you a kind of idealized situation  alright
No it's a serious question  people talk about it
>> So I'm not quite sure with what the eye was saying?
No no  okay  there could be several reasons why your eye was not good
First of all you could be
that the interaction with the apparatus would be simply to weak
That there wasn't enough room for the interaction
It wasn't that your eyes were bad
it's just wasn't coupling between the two systems
And then you only get partial information
Or it could be that your eye is bare because you have Cataract let's say
Alright in that case  the eye did a measurement
it became entangled with the system completely
it's just the connection between the stuff in you eye
And your brain wasn't good enough to send the signal back to your brain
So the correlation happen but it was a bit messy
>> Was that detector efficiency problem?
That  sometimes it's the detector efficiency problem
Sometimes it's the problem  well detector efficiency could have to do
with the strength of interaction with the system
Or it could just be it's too hard to get the signal out
So I'm not sure what detector efficiency really means?
But I could think of several things
One is the signal is there and imprint itself into the system
And you personally have a hard time getting it out
the other is that the interaction was not strong enough
to really establish a full entanglement between the systems
both can happen
>> Would they bother be watching adult movie(?) ?
>> Would they know the detector
You can think of all sort of the variance on this
>> but let's say a bad detector and entanglement
>> and then I have a perfectly detector later on would it ...
I think  I guess the weakest link is where you
Alright let's talk about locality
Let's talk about locality and entanglement
which is really where people got hung up
And the villain  the arch villain here
who really tangle things badly was Einstein
Einstein not that he asked the question of course
he asked a wonderful question about the entangled systems
Really are understanding the entanglement
Then much of what we think about it and curious about it
goes back to Einstein's question 1933
who was very much puzzled by the idea that you can have a system
about which you know everything
and yet you know nothing about the components of it
and he wrote a paper  simply complaining about it
I don't know if he was the first one
to notice the phenomena of entanglement
I have a feeling not  he was the first one to get really exercised by it
and say something is very peculiar here
That I find quite okay  he then use the term
What was the term again? Spooky action out of distance
And that got everybody confused afterwards
Because Einstein knew exactly what action out of distance meant
And it didn't mean what he meant when he is using it in this context
Action out of distance literally means forces
between systems at a distance
The ability to affect the outcome of a experiment at one place
by doing something at another place
Action out of distance  the columb(?) force between electrons
Now of course in the real world it's not action out of distance
But in Newton's word  well Newton didn't know about electrons
Newton knew about gravity
In Newton's world
the gravitational interaction was action out of distance
And the meaning of that from our point of view is
Something came along and gave the sun a sudden shove
we would know it instantly for the simple reason that
the orbit of the earth would instantly react
to the change in the position of the sun
The force on the earth will instantly react
And so every measurement of everything you might want to measure
Would be to some extent to another modified by the sudden change
in the orbit of the sun
That's what action out of distance meant
The ability if you like  to send the signal
By shoving the sun you are sending the signal to earth
And you are sending it instantaneously
if there is an action out of distance
Einstein must have known  I am certain that he knew that
Entanglement did not entail action out of distance in that sense
What one can do  what one can work out is supposing you start
I will give you something you can try to play with
And see if you can work it out
Supposing you start with a system which is a two part system
It has as wave function Psi of a and b
And from that system you can construct a density...
It's Alice and Bob  you can construct a density matrix with Rho for Alice
That density matrix contains every possible
Oh statistical prediction that Alice can every make for her sub system a
Now let's imagine that Alice and Bob took their subsystems
Alice went to a distant planet  Bob stay in Palo Alto
And they are very far from one another
So far that would take light four years to get from one place to another
Bob does an experiment  that's means now
This is an  this could be an entangled state
This is not a non-entangled state
Bob does an experiment
and that has an effect on his half of the system here
But it has no effect whatever on Alice's density matrix
Perhaps I can prove that  I'm not gonna prove that tonight
It's not too hard to prove that any physically allowable change
in this wave function which only involves Bob's half of it
The process of interacting with some other system or whatever it is
Bob gives it an electron or not  whatever he does to it
He will not have any effect on Alice's density matrix
That's the way quantum mechanics really put together
And the implication is that anything that Bob does suddenly
at a fixed instance of time  will not have any effect on any prediction
or the success of any prediction
would have not effect on the statistical probabilities of Alice
measuring anything about a  it just will not
So in that sense  it was impossible
for Bob to send the message to Alice suddenly
Now of course he can do an experiment on his sub system
And after he has done the experiment
he can then send the telegraph to Alice far away
in a standard way that you send messages
and tell her what the result again
This is an entangled state  it could be |up down> minus |down up>
When Bob does an measurement on his spin
it has not effect on Alice's density matrix
He can then send Alice a message and then say look I saw it down
And Alice will say ah  ya  that's because I saw up
It will correlate it  I thought they will correlated
and you just confirm that
I measure it up  but a few months ago
and in fact I'm now getting you a telegram
And it tells me that you got down and that's consistent
everything was fine
Nobody sends any message faster than the speed of light
The mere fact that when  Bob measure his variable
He instantly know something about Alice
It's no source of anxiety for locality
This would happen for nickels and dimes for a perfectly classical system
The peculiarity is different than that
the peculiarity has to do with this idea that
you can know anything about a system and yet know nothing about it's parts
What is it then if this locality
the standard physicist definition of locality is not at risk
And you can't send signal faster... what is it that Einstein meant
And what did Bell meant
and what did all the other people who talk about these thing mean
when they said entanglement entails a degree of non-locality
So I will try to explain to you by imagining a game
>>Question? If Bob makes a measurement and Alice did not
>>Can Bob send Alice a message after his measurement?
>> Will that information along be enough to change Alice's density matrix
To be enough for what?
>>to change Alice's density matrix
Oh yeah  if Alice sends  if Bob sends a real message
and Alice hasn't look yet
Okay so let's say  Alice has not look  she doesn't know anything yet
And as far as she is concerns the density matrix is consistent to that
And basically tells her nothing
that's the density matrix which
doesn't got very much information in it about her spin
And then she gets a telegram from Bob  saying my spin was up
As far as Alice's concern  that collapses her density matrix and tells her
her spin is down  so there after
she still will use the density matrix which says her spin is down
So yes  once a message has time to go between them
Yes then she will know something she didn't know before
And she will therefore update her density matrix
But that would only take place after
there's been insufficient time to for the signal to propagate
>> If I understand correctly  the statement we are making here
>> is about the expected value of these experiments right?
>> When you realize it once
>> you are not actually getting the expected value  but you are gonna get
>> but this also holds for every value not just the expected values right?
No  expected or expectation value or whatever you want to call them
average values  if you know the average values of all variables
You don't need to know  let's okay
Supposing we have one variable that we are interested in
Let's call it L again  if we know the average value of L
The average value of L square  the average value of L cubed
Dot dot dot  we know the whole probability distribution of L
This is called knowing the moments
all of the moments of a probability distribution
If we know all the expectation values of L  L squared L cubed
Actually for a single spin  you only need the spin and the spin's square
Then you know the full probability distribution
Once you know the full probability distribution that's all you can know
So knowing all  knowing a full set of expectation values like this
is knowing everything I was to know about the system
>> but the actual realization of the experiment that happens towards it
Oh that's right  yeah  that's right
>> they are still guaranteed to be opposite right?
They are guaranteed to be opposite  yes
But Alice doesn't update her information about  until she gets
Before Alice get the information  as far as she knows it's half a half
But let's try to do a little bit better
Alice and Bob are now going to each have many spins  alright
So Charlie is gonna give each of them many entangled pairs
So Alice has spin number one  and Bob has his spin number one
And they are in the relationship of being entangled
Also Alice has spin number two which is not entangled with spin number one
But it happens to be entangled with Bob's spin number two
Charlie gave them a whole series of these
So they can do statistical experiment and collect statistics
When they've collected statistics they will discover that
every time Bob is up Alice is down
Every time Bob is down Alice up
But they can do a lot more than that
They can  let's see what's a good example for what can be done
Ya right  good  Bob does all of his experiments here
at some instance of time
And finds out every one of these
finds out exactly what everyone of them is doing
Does that convey any information at all to Alice about
which she knows that just about half of them are up
and half of them are down
Bob goes in mixed measurement
he does his measurement on every single one of them
Does Alice know anything afterward that she didn't know before? No
Does anything surprising happen when she measures these things?
Does the statistic of these thing over here in any way change
because Bob measure this things?
No  there will be no statistical difference
Bob can do his measurement
throw his measurement in the waste paper basket
But he's measured every single one of these
He has no influence at all on what Alice measures
But if Bob sends a message to Alice before she does her measurement
And says spin one came out plus  spin two came out minus bla bla bla
Then instantly Alice knows everything about these
In fact he could say sigma z equals plus one
But he decided over here not to measure sigma z
So I'm gonna measure sigma x over here  minus one
And over here he measure sigma y equals plus one
Having made these measurements without informing Alice in any way
Does nothing whatever to the statistic of her measurement
But if he now senses them  she can now decide
She can decide to measure anything she wants
But if she decides to measure sigma z
because she knew that Bob got plus one here and sigma x for this one
And sigma y for this one
we will find that in every case that they are opposite
>> Are you saying that Bob send the message  I'm not sure I understand
Yes it's a telegram
>> there is not he sending that is receiving at the (inaudible)
well of course yes
>> How can you be sure?
Well the important point is that it takes time to send the message
What? I missed  okay  well yes that was a problem
>> I don't know...it seems like the feeling of spooky action distances
>>comes not from ...
>> But it's also sticky about the inside the spectator (?)
>>there is two sepralities
Well  I will try to give you a precise definition
There is a theorem looking here  I don't know that the theorem has ever
been discussed in the computer science community
It's kind of a computer science theorem
whether anybody has actually discussed it
in a language I'm gonna tell you now I don't know
And I don't really quite know how to formulate it
as a theorem I've never tried
But I think I can capture the essence of what this theorem would say
If only the theorem could be made precise
We have ten minutes to try to do this
We go over it a little bit  we will do that
Here is a game I wanna play
I want  I'm gonna write a computer program  my computer
My computer has a screen  okay it has a screen
and all the usual thing that a computer have
Over here on the screen there is a little blackbox
And that little blackbox is called spin  you can't see inside it
But there is something in it
And in here is apparatus A  an apparatus A
you can see what it's doing and so forth
It's got a zero  I can measure zero or one
Now here's the game  the memory stores two things
The memory store information about the spin
This is a completely classical computer
The game we are gonna play is I'm gonna fool you into thinking
it's really a quantum mechanics system in here
How are we gonna do that?
We are gonna do it by I'm going to write a computer program
which completely simulates  the classical computer program
It completely simulates what happens when the apparatus look at a spin
Okay so here's the way it's gonna go
We are going to start just for convenience
We will start with the spin in a known state
So the apparatus or the computer program  it's not important
But the computer program let's say its starts out with a spin up
or whatever it's doing
The apparatus can either reads zero or one
There is a button over here in this
There is a button over here that you touch
And that button is M  means you measure  means measurement
So when you touch that button over here
The apparatus measures the spin
The computer records two things
It records the state vector of the spin  how does it do that?
By providing two complex numbers
stored into computers are two complex numbers alpha up and alpha down
Subject to the constraint that alpha star alpha plus alpha star alpha
is equal to one
So it stores in information
which is equivalent to the state vector of the spin
And the other thing it stores is the direction
that you point the apparatus
You can move the apparatus around by playing with the computer
Not moving it around but you can reorient it in any directions
that you like
You start with a spin up
now this spin might be interacting with a magnetic field
Or whatever it's happening to it
The computer solves the Schrodinger equation
In solving the Schrodinger equation for the spin
that means it updates the state of the spin
you start with a particular state  but it's now what it is
And after a time to it  it update the spin  it updates the state
So the computer now know what alpha is after a certain time is elapsed
Then you punch the measure button and the computer takes the state
turns it into a pair of probabilities
alpha star alpha up  alpha star alpha down
The computer now knows that the probability for up and down
And it also has a random number generator
Random number generator or a dime doesn't and they work very well
with the random number generator
it then take the probability alpha up and alpha down
And spit out the number plus or minus one
with probability alpha star alpha and alpha star alpha
So we just simulate the quantum mechanics
by having a random number generator
That either spits out plus one or minus one
but with a probability that's given by alpha star alpha
But then the computer then whatever the answer is
Whatever the answer that the apparatus spit out
The computer then updates once again the state of the spin
And says it is in the state that the apparatus measure
So if the apparatus spits out plus one along some axis
You get to turn the apparatus
but of course if you get to turn the apparatus
you have to do a slightly complicated calculation
to find out what this statistics are
but once you've done it  whatever the answer is
The computer goes back and update the state of the spin
to make it consistent with what the apparatus measure
You can do this  you can try to write a program
and it's a program that could be written
It's probably not even terribly complicated
And if you  only got to look at the measuring button  decide to measure
And look at the outcome  you would get everything exactly equivalent
to the extent of a random number generator
can be a good faithful random number generator
You will completely simulate the quantum mechanics of the system
What this is that quantum mechanics system
can be a special case of classical physics
So what's going on?
What the quantum mechanics system
can be a special case of classical mechanics
what is all this confusion about quantum mechanics spin?
Logically different  alright
Now we want to play the same game with a pair of spins
>>quantum mechanics is a special case of a classical mechanics
>> but in the former class  everything was deterministic
>> and then introducing probability
Okay but it's only  yay a
it's a classical computer and it's using a classical number generator
A classical random number generator alright?
So you don't have to add in another  but the difference between
quantum mechanics and classical mechanics isn't randomness
You can generate all sorts of random number generators
that would easily fool you into thinking if they are really random
Cause any real random number generator  the numbers come from somewhere
So they are not strictly random
But you can sure make a random number generator that would fool anybody
So ya  you can build
you can build a computer program to simulates the quantum mechanics
basically of any systems that you like by the same method  okay?
But now supposing you wanted to
simulate a system consisting of two electrons
There is two electrons two boxes here
And you wanted to do it with two computers
And in the process of taking the electron apart from each other
So as to ask this question about  you want to take the computers
You want to encode the information about Alice's spin in one computer
And Bob's spin in other computer  physically separated them
And ask can these computers simulates quantum mechanics?
So I will tell you want the answer is
As long as the spin are in a product state
As long as they start in a product state
and they don't interact with each other
And therefore stay in a product state
Then you can do it
then you can put all of the information about Bob's spin in here
Or all the information about Alice's spin in here
Likewise you can have Bob's apparatus over here
You can have Alice's apparatus over here  a little black box
And it's just basically two identical versions of what I said before
You can take the computer physically separate them
Do experiments on each one and they would completely agree with
the result of quantum mechanics  because if they are in a product state
One doesn't care about the other  but then you say
what if I wanted to put these two spins in a entangled state
Well first of all  to put them in a entangled state
you can not do it without bringing the computers together
Bringing the computers together so that they talk to each other
You can record in the combined computer system now they brought together
How many numbers does it take to specify the state of two spin system? Six
So you record six numbers in the computer here
Six numbers are recorded in the computer
And some numbers to reflect the orientations of various apparatuses
that you might conceive of
And then you try to split the computer in two
Keeping Alice's information in here and Bob's information in here
separate them and try to simulate
the quantum mechanics of the entangled system
Bell's theorem is what tell you that you can not do this
unless there are instantaneous action out of distance phenomena
taking place between the... wires between the computers so to speak
Hidden wires that have to be part of the system
connecting the computers together
you cannot simulate the quantum mechanics with a classical computer system
You can't simulates the quantum mechanics of an entangled system
Unless it's really just one computer  really one computer means
That signal can be transmitted back and forth basically instantly
That's what Bell's theorem really says
Now is this a form of non-locality?
Well you might think that if you really have to have these wires there
To simulate quantum mechanics
Then why can't you send the instantaneous message through these wires?
Of course you can,  but not if you only allow yourself
to do the thing which quantum mechanics permits
For example there are things that quantum mechanics doesn't permit
It doesn't allow you
to measure the x and y component of the spin simultaneously
All kinds of thing that does not permit you to do
Because they correspond to non-commutating operators
But if you restrict yourself to the measurement which quantum mechanics
allows you to do on either one of these  or any combination of them
Then it's a very magical and special fact
That you can not send information faster than speed of light
You can not send information instantaneously by this computer set up
>> What if you assign a probability but conditional probability
Doesn't matter  doesn't matter  if you want to simulate a quantum system
with a classical system of computers
And you want to study entangled systems
That computers have to be able to
communicate with each other instantaneously
That's the content of Bell's theorem
Now does that mean that there is any action  spooky action out of distance
Or does it just mean that you have gotten yourselves into trouble
by trying to simulate quantum mechanics with classical mechanics
And my view is that you've gotten yourselves into trouble
by trying to simulate something which just doesn't want to be
describe by a classical computer systems
And it's a deep and interesting fact about quantum mechanics
Einstein's view was that this is basically evidence
that the description is incomplete
And there are other variables for the system
And Bell's conclusion was those variables have to be hidden wires
that connect distant places
So you can take it for however you see it yourselves
>> If you have a quantum computer there
>> and let's say when you have the states
If you have a quantum computer you can do it
>> and you separated it right
>> now when you look at Bob's computer
>>you know something about Alice's right?
>> but can't really still send
It's the same problem  but look all the quantum computer
It's an electron in this computer
and electron (in that computer) that is all it is
It's just a quantum system right  it's just a true quantum system
Quantum system  and each one of these which has just been entangled
That's all what a quantum computer is
It's a quantum mechanical system
which can reflect the logical structure of quantum mechanics
And the way to make it
is by actually making a pair of entangled electrons in there
Something real has to be entangled between them
And it can't be simulated by a fake computer program
unless the computer has this property of
>> (inaudible)
Sure  alright
>> You could sort of hack this problem away using an analogy
>> supre random number generators all synchronized
>> so there are actually not they will be random
What you can't do is synchronize them in advance
and then not let them interact with each other
That wont' do it  the random number have to be
The random number generator have to be such that what this one measures
respond to what that one measure
>> Like for example  what I meant was
>> the random number generator are synchronized at the beginning
>> and whenever you measure  because they are synchronized
>> they will always generate up and down reversed
No  it's simply not enough  this is what the theorem says
It is not enough to synchronize them in advance and then take them apart
They've got to continue to interact with each other
That's what it says  that they must continue to interact with each other
and feed information back and forth
>> The problem was delay choice if you put a Bell
>>Then instantaneously Alice
>> four light years away  and that (?)
I told you everything I know about it
And what I know about it is that there is nothing Bob could do
which can influence the statistics of Alice's measurements
without sending her a measure
>> (inaudible)
Alright two more questions
>> you said we can classically simulate quantum mechanics?
Yes you can classically simulate quantum mechanics
But you basically have to do it with in a single computer
Where all parts of it speaks to every other parts
You can not physically take them apart
the way you would want to take the quantum systems apart
>>
No  no  In an entangled system Bob can do his measurement
Alice can do her measurements
But there are other things that can be measured
beside just the things that Alice would measure
on her system or the thing Bob would measure
For example  neither Bob nor Alice by themselves
can measure sigma x times tau x
It takes both of them to do it
It takes both detectors  it takes both apparatuses
to make a measurement of sigma x times tau x
This is something that you can not measure
Now you can measure with two apparatuses
The question is are there anything you could measure
That you couldn't measure even with those two apparatuses
And yes there are  sigma x tau x plus sigma y tau y plus sigma z tau z
is something that can not even be measured by using both apparatuses
It takes a new kind of apparatus which is not a combination
of Alice's and Bob's original apparatuses
Which each measures a Bob's thing and an Alice's thing
>> Can Bob measure the entanglement
Nobody can measure entanglement
No  Bob can discover that he's got  nobody can do anything with one event
But if you have a whole replication like I describe
where did I describe it?
Well we have many replica of the same thing
Many replica of the same thing
then Bob can discover the fact that his state is entangled with something
And the way he does it
is he says let me search around for a direction in space
For which the spins are definitely align in some direction
Here is what he knows
He knows that all the system were prepared in the same way
They are all identical  each pairs is identical...
each pair is identical to each other pair
And he's wondering could each one of these be in a product state?
Same product state for this one  same product state for that one
Same product state for that one
If there have inner product state then Bob can search around
He's got enough version of it  enough trials
that he can go on and on with experiments for ever
And he could search around for a direction where
when he measures the spin his spin
He always discover that it's up
Now the first time he maybe in the wrong direction
And he will find down
Next time he may find up and try again it would be down  wrong direction
It keeps searching around  if it's a product state
he would eventually find
the direction where the spin would continue to be up up up up
after he's found it
If it's in an entangled state  no matter what directions he measures
He will always find the spin are random okay
That's the character of it
>> And that's a seperate measurement right?
>> on separate discrete measurement right?
>> If not the measurement are the same thing
No you've got to have ensemble of identical system
to do anything like this
You just prepare each one the same way
You do a experiment
He doesn't care about Alice
he's just gonna measure his spin along some axis
Another one axis  another one axis
Until he find the one way  he keeps repeatedly getting the same answer
And then he said that's the direction that spin is polarized
And then he keeps doing it and finds consistency
He will never find that unless he  says a product state
So it's pretty interesting stuff  hard stuff
For more  please visit us at Stanford.edu