Stanford University
I was talking about what happens during or from beginning from before
A measurement to after a measurement
We are talking about what happens to the evolution
of an isolated black hole left to itself
between the time that it was prepared and the time it was measured
Okay, nevertheless I could answer a question
Is entanglement inevitably irreversible?
If two things which are not entangled come together
interact with each other
Do whatever they do and become entangled
Is it irreversible?
Not necessarily anything that can happen The opposite can happen
Now we're not talking about an external apparatus measuring the system
we are simply talking for example about two spins
two spins interact with each other come together
go off an they are entangled
what happens is it possible to disentangle them by,
for example, reflecting them, letting them come together and interact again
Can they become disentangle?
Yes, yes, there is no rule that says entanglement is irreversible
On the other hand, if an entanglement happens
and you take one of the electrons off and throw it away
then the other one is stuck there left being entangled with the thing that
just not gonna come back, not gonna come back
unless, of course, somebody out there reflect it back and
so yeah entanglement is re- is reversible
But as far as you're concerned,
the measurements that you do are irreversible
that's a very peculiar situation, you have to think about it
Understand what it means
we are gonna move off the question of these very simple systems
spins sometimes called qubits, tonight at some point,
but I want to just go over just very briefly,
I think I probably discussed this in class last time,
but nevertheless it's so important that I wanna hammer on it,
first of all there was a notion of the density matrix
if we have two systems Alice's system, and Bob system
and Alice's system or Bob system are far away from each other
so that Alice doesn't get to do any experiments on Bob system
Bob does not get to do experiments on Alice's system,
but they are entangled either they are or they are not entangled
they may be entangled
Is their description that Alice by herself uses to describe just her subsystem
the answer is yes, and the working description of her sub system is called the density matrix
so limited review that very very quickly and then go back over some concepts
if the wave function of the Alice Bob system
The combined system of Alice's subsystem and Bob's
the wave function is called Psi of a and b,
b for Bob a for Alice then Alice's, Alice's density matrix
Alice's density matrix is defined to be psi star,
the complex conjugate of the wave function,
I know,  let's say it rho it's rho, called the density matrix,
it's indicated by rho, it has subscript a and a prime because it's a matrix
but it doesn't have anything to do a Bob
so it's purely a matrix with respect to Alice's variables
let's indicate that by calling this Alice's density matrix
and its given by Psi star of a b a prime b, I was getting confused
a prime psi of ab, summed over Bob's variables
it doesn't depend on Bob's variables because they have been summed over
when you sum over something it no longer depends on that set of variables,
so this is only a function of Alice's variables
and it contains all possible all possible um, statistical information
that Alice can ever know about her half of the system
unless Bob comes in interact with her system of course
if Bob comes from wherever he is and give,
her system a shove of some sort that will change her density matrix,
but as long as Bob stays away from her system
Bob's in Palo Alto Alice's on Alpha Centauri
as long as Bob does not interact directly with her system
her density matrix doesn't change, no matter what Bob does
let me give a little proof of that
let's take Bob's subsystem to not be so narrow, just to be the little spin
that is carrying around and also Alice's
let's imagine that Alice's subsystem consists of everything in Alice's neighborhood
everything that she can have any contact with
everything in Bob system is everything in Bob's neighborhood,
Maybe even including Bob, and now Bob is going to do something
he's going to do something interact of course he can only interact directly,
Interact mean he may turn on a magnetic field,
he may do all sorts of things ought to change the evolution of his sub system
he's gonna make a subsystem evolve in some way
One of the ways which Bob can cause his sub system to evolve many many ways,
but whatever they are,
they are always governed by unitary matrices,
let's come over here and forget Alice for a minute and ask what Bob can do is subsystem
he has a wave function, let's leave out Alice and the picture altogether
just suppose that Bob has a wave function and he's gonna manipulate the system somehow
he's gonna manipulate the system somehow
and send it to a new wave function
rule is the new wave function of his sub system
must be related to the old wave function by a unitary operator
unitary operators of the things which govern time evolution go back
Remember the time evolution, unitary operators,
and that means it psi of b becomes replaced by sum over b
some unitary matrix
b b prime psi of b prime in terms of wave functions in matrices
This is the description of what happens to Bob's matrix
sorry Bob's column vector is basically called Bob's column vector
describing his half of the world
or his system and to find out what happens to it no matter what he does
even if he doesn't do anything but let's suppose he does something, he does something,
it generates a unitary evolution of his wave function
now how do we describe the same thing in the composite language
in the composite language of the wave function is psi of a and b
Alice's and Bob's variable
what happens to it when Bob manipulates his half of the world
exactly the same thing with Alice's variables be just spectators
just being passive spectators so psi of a and b just becomes psi of
oops, put in there b prime, sum of b prime,
this is a function of b and you sum over b prime,
okay that's again a sum over b prime of U of b and b prime
psi of a and b prime, a just passed through
Alice know nothing whatever about the about this whole process
her subsystem was not in any way influenced her index
her part of the wave function Her half of the dependence of the wave function
was uninfluenced by Bob's manipulation
so let's go back and take the manipulated wave function
This is the manipulated wave function
call it psi, the manipulated wave function of b and a, of a and b that's this,
It's been modified by the action of Bob's unitary operator,
Okay now let's recalculate let's recalculate Alice's density matrix
after all Alice's density matrix contains all information that you can ever know
about her half of the world, so let's see what happened to it
Well we first of all have to take the manipulated psi star
We have to sum over b, but now we take the manipulated psi star
Oh we hadn't written psi star,
Sorry about that we have to write psi star manipulated of
and we want to know about it with index a prime and b
a prime and b, and now we get just to complex conjugating it
this tells us how psi changes,
let's just work out the complex conjugate that's the complex conjugate of a prime
>> Where is a and b prime?
this is a prime b, just a prime and b
but here since b prime is a summation variable
we do not want to write b prime here,
b prime was the summation variable used over here,
Let's just invent another one called b double prime
we are gonna be, that's gonna be the summation variable in a moment
and U complex conjugate of b and b double prime
U complex conjugate of course is a sum over b double prime
and the only reason I called it b double prime instead of b
was so as not to confuse it with b prime
here's one sum and here is a separate sum
Now here is something what do we know about unitary operators
unitary operators are operators that if we interchange b
if we interchange the two indices and complex conjugate what happens?
That's called it's called the inverse operator or the Hermitian conjugate
for U, in general, it's called the Hermitian conjugate specifically for unitary,
it becomes the inverse operator,
Let's just call it the Hermitian conjugate
if I un complex conjugate and interchange these two,
sorry b double prime b double prime, b
and this becomes Hermitian conjugate
alright, so this is the usual story if operators operate to the right on ket vectors,
the corresponding action on bra vectors is given by the by the Hermitian conjugate
So now all I have to do is plug it
we plug this in for the, for the manipulated psi star of summation over b b double prime
psi star of a prime and b double prime times U dagger of b double prime and b
it's a nuisance too many indices for me to be comfortable and blackboard,
but I think this is worth doing
now what about psi, psi is the other half it comes into the density matrix,
and that's U, b b prime psi of what psi of a and b prime, complicated little mess
oh what do we summing over, we are summing over all the b-s basically
we are summing over this b over here,
let's put the b summation here,
we were summing over b double prime to get the manipulated wave
for this complex conjugate,
but we also have to sum over b prime here
sum over all the bs this side
each b is a summation variable by the time we finished
Alright but now look at what we have,
it looks complicated but what is this thing over here?
Well not quite yet , I will wonder, it's essentially correct,
but of course what you mean is the unit matrix
This is  the product matrix of U dagger
this is a unitary matrix so U dagger is used inversed
b double prime b b b prime,
this is just a Kronecker Delta b double prime b prime,
it just instructs you to set b double prime equal to b prime
when you do this sum, when you do one of the two sum
let's say the b double prime sum
so all of these then becomes sum over b prime,
well, let's see what have we got, we set b double prime
We've done b sum over b that's done, oh sum over b we just did it,
and now we set b double prime equal to b prime
psi star of a prime b prime, psi of a and b prime,
that's it doesn't matter whether we call b prime b prime or whether we call it b
because it's a summation variable so let's do that
Let's just call it b, and what do we have we have exactly I hope, I pray
the original density matrix so Bob, no matter what he does
as long as what he does is described by a unitary matrix
Bob will have absolutely no effect on Alice's density matrix
does not matter whether entangled or not
No way is that I specify that this was a product state
That is what physicists call locality
the inability of Bob to influence any statistical prediction of Alice's
by doing a manipulation on his own degrees of freedom
locality is not violated, this form of locality
This form of locality is not violated in any way by the phenomenon of entanglement
that's the technical argument, notice that it does depend on unitarity
so what do unitarity do, unitarity had to do with conservation of distinctions
what I called the minus first law,
at least in its quantum mechanical version
so funny and interesting interplay
funny, interesting interplay between the conservation of distinctions on the one hand
and locality
If Bob somehow had access to changes which were not described by unitary operators,
this would not have become the unit matrix over here
and the final density matrix, Alice's final density matrix indeed would have been modified
this is interesting the way the whole thing holds together
this is why it's so hard to change quantum mechanics
you wanna play a little game,
let's let Bob tha's Bob's evolution, not quite be unitary,
only approximately unitary,
well then immediately you start sending signals faster than speed of light
How? by instantly modifying Alice's density matrix
so things hold together tightly
and it's hard to change them
good so yes so
>>Is it correct to say that Bob's matrix is unitary?
He's not able to change Alice's, Alice's system
He's changed his own system by doing something
in the doing something was described by this unitary matrix
>> that's the part I confused, if you are doing something
>> Isn't he going to violate the unitarity?
For example, he might be turning a magnet,
He might be turning a magnet in such a way
that it has an influence on his spin
What is that influence? It will change the state of the spin
For example,  if you have a spin in a given direction and it's coupled to a magnetic field
Then you turn the magnetic field in some way
It will typically change the evolution of the spin
So Bob can do that, he can change a magnetic field,
it's acting on certain spin,
the result will be to change the way the spin evolves
that will change his own measurements of the spin of his spin
if he does act by rotating a magnetic field
which is mathematically described by some sort of evolution of matter what
some sort of evolution, it's described by unitary operator
then the that he does change the results of his own measurements
he rotates a magnetic field, but it doesn't rotated his apparatus
the result is he is gonna change the probability distributions of his own spin,
but he will not change any of the probabilities of Alice's spin
okay
>> So what you are saying is quantum mechanics always violates locality?
The locality defined by the inability of Bob to influence Alice's measurements
So what's the big deal? Is that what you are gonna ask?
I was guessing what you are gonna ask
>>single particle wave function, put a beam over
>>it goes off to two different direction
>>one of your detector is faster than the speed of light
>> then the wave function collapsed
What what what what, you do what?
>>You detect the photon at one detector
>>the function of the other detector collapse instantaneously
I tell you what happened, density matrix of the other system does not change, period
>>
I know I know I know people, look I'm doing my absolute best to tell it to you
as it really is and cut through the craps that's out there
cut through the crap that's out there
because there is a huge amount of there is a pile of mile high,
and we somehow want to cut through that
this is the mathematics of cutting through it
now, nevertheless there was some pretty damn smart people
who are uncomfortable about something
Something that they call non-locality
You know Einstein was no jerk, he was pretty smart
He ain't called Einstein for nothing
That's my favorite joke
John bell was pretty smart They didn't call him Einstein though
So there's something going on, something going on
I'm gonna get, I'm reviewing last week, so very quick
>>as you and that is the and idea of Locality means that
>> the state don't effect each other
>>the density, and the confusing part is,
>>it seems two different things get mixed up and now, Is that accurate or?
No it's positive, but it's true
I will try to tell you as I understand it,
what the concrete operational facts are
I was a little bit tired last time, and I'm not sure I was completely clear
So I want to go over it again because it's very very interesting
It really is at the heart of all of the confusions about confusions
Confusions I mean, I must say
including my own internal confusions about quantum mechanics
when I first learned about the Einstein Rosen Podolsky
I don't know who discovery, I think maybe Schrodinger
says something about entanglement,
but it was Einstein Rosen Podolsky,
who really called attention to peculiar was
basically what they said is we have a very funny situation here where
although we can know everything that can possibly be known about a composite system
we know nothing at all about its constituent
That's crazy violates my sense of reality that violates my sense
of what it means to know what a system is doing
violates all sorts of things, when I first heard about it
I was actually before John Bell some time in the 60s when a student
when I wasn't a student, or when I was a young assistant professor then
Think about it after about a lot
try to figure out what it means
I was sort of inclined to try to think about it in terms of simulating quantum mechanics,
and I still am
What are the limits if if if quantum mechanics is so very strange
and so very different than classical physics
does it mean that you can't fool somebody into thinking the system is quantum mechanical
if all you have your resources are entirely classical
and the answer is yes and no
so I know I talked about this last time,
but it really is at the center of thing
Let's go back over it quick, quick as I can
we get a build ourselves a quantum simulator
I think somebody built one on the site I came across about an hour ago, who's that?
Does it work?
>>It doesn't really simulate yet
Is that picture your picture?
There's a picture of Einstein, Heisenberg and Einstein I don't like this
Heisenberg's of
>>Einstein said,
I will like this you are you put it,
I think that captures it
let's talk about the nature of quantum simulators are
first of all I just want to simulate a single spin
I think I told you how to do it,
but let's write down the steps
we have a computer screen, here's a computer screen on the screen
We have a picture of the detector I will write down a detector apparatus
and the apparatus can be oriented in any direction in three-dimensional space
We need to do some of three-dimensional graphics here
and it has a window and the window shows one of three possible states
One is called blank, the that's the that's the detector of the apparatus
before its interacted with anything
so it can be b or plus or minus one, b is not important,
it's just there to say before the detector interact with anything
There is a button over here called m
and the operator of the system of the computer game,
basically all you get to do was press M and then look at the result of
M stands for measure performs a measurement
Now all I hear connected to the computer by wires of our cables,
Connected to the screen by cables is a computer
and the computer stores information in its memory,
and the basic information that it stores is two complex numbers
alpha up and alpha down
those are supposed to be the components of the wave function of the spin
I didn't say there is the spin here,
but that's sort of what we are talking about
alpha up and alpha down,
the computer only can generate alphas which satisfy alpha star alpha up
Plus Alpha star alpha down is equal to one
Whenever it generate them, and it can do something else
It can do two other things
it can update the alphas by solving the Schrodinger equation for them
There's some Hamiltonian For example,
It could be that the spins are in a, the spin is in an imaginary magnetic field
In which case the alphas would change with time,
the computer knows how to do that, it knows how to solve Schrodinger's equation
computers can solve Schrodinger's equation beautifully
and it updates these as a function of time
updates them according to the rules of quantum mechanics
One of the thing the cables are instantaneous
They convey information instantly and so will have one more element
The other element will be a random number generator
Let me just say some words about random number generators
random number generators sounds we are introducing quantum mechanics
No, we don't need quantum mechanics
you can simulate to a very very high degree of confidence
random sequence of random numbers of random number generator
Purely out of classical classical considerations you how to do it,
you take the digits of pi whatever and
you make something that looks would fool anybody,
including a sophisticated mathematician into believing
that you are generating a set of random numbers
There is a random number generator inside the computer
the operator starts by initializing of the system
and initializing the system simply means starting out some orientation for the detector
for the apparatus doesn't matter what,
and setting the alphas to some initial values
you can plug in what he wants he wants the initial values to be,
or the computer sets them according to whatever rule, it likes
then the system runs for a period of time an indetermined period of time
updating the alphas until the operator decides to press M
a certain amount of time is elapsed the operator decides how much time
and presses M at that point,
the random number generator generates a plus one or minus one,
but with probability alpha star alpha up that it's plus one,
sorry, alpha up alpha up star plus one,
or else alpha star alpha down that's minus one
remember the sum of these two alpha star alpha add up to one
so we went on to be a random number generator,
the computer sends a signal with a probability of the appropriate probability
to the detector and the detector detects or registers what the computer sent it
That's one measurement
Now as soon as that happens the computer reinitializes the alphas
how does it reinitialize the alphas, if the detector detected plus one,
then it sends back a message that it doesn't really need to send back a message after all,
this message got review here
so the computer over here knows whether it got plus one or minus one
if the detector saw a plus one
Then it sets alpha u back to one and sets alpha d to zero
Another words, it does what we call collapsing the wave function
according to the result, according to the outcome of the measurement
We reinitializes the alphas so what was measured
you start with probability one for the outcome a probability zero
what shall we call it the anti-outcome,
and then it runs again solve the Schrodinger equation
does it again the operator make  whatever decision he likes
what makes him decide to press the M ?
He's an experimental physicist what makes experimental physicists do what they do
I don't really know,
but but he does what experimental physicist
now and then he presses M and there's a whole operation over again
it oh sorry before he does,
he may decide to rotate the apparatus
now the computer in here knows what the orientation of the apparatuses
so when it calculates it not only calculates the updated alphas,
but it also calculates the probabilities for the rotated detector
to detect whatever it's going to detect
that's all algebra and a little bit of that's the purely algebra
The computer makes a kind of calculations that you did
or presumably did, makes a kind of calculations to calculate
what the probability would be
that if the detector was rotated in some arbitrary direction,
then the then what's the probability that it will get up or down
Now who was it that decides to rotate the computer?
Well it's the operator again the experimentalist
experimentalist not only can press M and but he can also
reorient the detector anytime he wants
This is about as much as an experimental physicist can do with that spin
rotate the apparatus measure, rotate the apparatus again measure
and what's the result of the outcome of this?
the outcome of this is indistinguishable from what the experimental physicist
examining the spin would see
so we simulated quantum mechanics
alright, now we want to know whether we can simulate quantum mechanics of two spins
one on Alice's side of the world over here and one on Bob side of the world's
>> I don't know what the purposes of M
>> When he decided to push it
Ya the computer has been updating all this time
>> Alright when we talk about our basic model of spin world, the Hamiltonian of it
we did talk about Hamiltonian we talk about Hamiltonian's
and how Hamiltonian's update the state of the system, you're right,
we didn't discuss how a, we didn't discuss much about Hamiltonians with spin
yes we did I believe I described the spin and the magnetic field
and how the average spin process
>> But we didn't have a magnetic field
>> Last time we talk about
right there is no real magnetic field,
It's just the imaginary magnetic field that the computer knows about
and where does it come into,
it comes into the solution of the nature of the exact Schrodinger equation,
okay now we do this over here and precisely the same thing over here,
except instead of alphas we have betas, beta stand for Bob
exactly the same set up replicated twice
Bob does his measurement hours of measurements
And he's perfectly happy with each one says I have a spin
quantum mechanical, they don't talk to each other,
and each one says my spin is in a state,
the language that we would describe this by quantum mechanically
is they have simulated a product state,
a product state in which Bob's sorry Alice's wave function is this
and Bob's wave function is this, and the combined system is in a product state
supposing now we want to simulate a any state,
a more complete description that includes entangled states
well we can do it this way,
let's start with a way sort guaranteed to work
we take the computer we put it in the middle of a single computer
we can think of a single computer as we like as a pair of computers connected by wires
but just the fact that they are communicating with each other interacting with each other
Really makes in a single computer and in that single computer we now store
four complex numbers, the four complex numbers that we store in there are alpha up up,
alpha up down, alpha down up alpha down down,
these complex numbers here are not necessarily products in fact,
let's assume the not products
another words at this is not a product state,
let's assume it's a highly entangled state,
even a highly entangled state is described by for complex numbers like this
that's what's in the computer, and what does the computer do with it?
It evolves the Schrodinger equation first of all,
we initialize same deal, we initialize we start with some alphas
the alphas are allowed to run according to whatever the Schrodinger equation describes them
and at the end, either Bob or Alice or both without knowing what the other one is doing
press, or as the case may be, don't press their measurement buttons
once the measurement button has been pressed and
instantaneous signal goes back to the computer
the computer grinds out random number generator
and whichever side was measured sends a signal to the detector
with appropriate probability either plus one or minus one
and then reinitializes itself, reinitialize itself in a way that doesn't touch for example
if Alice does the experiment then it doesn't touch Bob's end of things,
if Bob does the experiment the computer reinitializes his half of the wave function,
which is another way of saying throws away the piece that you didn't measure
throws away the pieces you didn't measure and re-normalizes the wave function
so that the total probability is one
exactly the same thing is, no no real difference with a single system,
you can simulated you can simulate a way
which would describe all the possible things that Alice and Bob can measure
into whether or not the system was, was entangled
where is where we get in trouble
we get in trouble if after initializing we tried to separate the computers and break the wires
For example, here's what we might do
Given these alphas we might put them into both computers
take the set of alphas that we generated, put this one into this computer
This one into this computer, computers are not gonna talk to each other
They have to have separate window number generators
and the random number generators will not talk to each other
Each one contains the full entangled state,
and then we go through the same operation
what's going to happen?
The computer is simply going to forget
For example, for a highly entangled state,
let's say the entangled state is the singlet state
then the right answer would be that if Bob and Alice both measure
they should get opposite values for any spin
if they measure the X component of the spin they should get opposite values,
if they measure Y components of spin, they should get opposite values,
but if when we separate them They have separate random number generators
the random number generators don't talk to each other
than guess what's gonna happen is gonna be no correlation of any kind
between what Bob measure than what Alice measures no,
Bob makes that measure plus and Alice may also measure plus
because the random number generators are not connected to each other
So even though both computers may know about the full state of the system
If the random number generators don't talk to each other
then the results of the experiments will not contain the correlation
the correlation that Bob and Alice could later come together and
report Bob would say my first experiments are plus
if things were working right,
then Alice's should save my first experiments are minus and so forth and so on
that correlation will not be there once you try to separate the computers
>> will the random number be correlated if you don't separate the computers?
you can have, you can have a single random number generator
that sends out signals to both computers
it sends out a signal plus one to this computer
and sends out a signal minus one for the computer
so all you need is a single random number generator,
but it has to be able to talk to both computers
so this got to be wires in the world, this is gotta be wires in the world,
connecting this side and this side
and if for no other reason than they can both
connect to the same random number generator
>>you will and will just and
Think about it,
that's, that's sort of right
Once you separated them, then what happens next after some measurements are made
doesn't preserve the relationship between them
they become disconnected from each other
So think about it a little bit
I mean even better try to simulated it, this is, I have never tried,
but I don't think it should be that hard if you tdo a little bit of computer programming
I've simulated much harder things, than that when my son was a little kid
We had this thing called BASIC anybody remember BASIC
and he and I designed a basketball game and have friction
well much harder than this,
so that was my last experience of programming anything
>> I think in that scenario
I think you will learn a lot by trying to simulate this
>> you have detector to pull itself off
>> and get a signal from Alice's
>> some thing could be a spin
>>let's suppose were
Would you speak concretely
we get a signal from Bob some random event what was that mean?
Could you please be exact, very exact
>> I'm getting two text messages, one from a one from b okay
>> and they can have a value one or zero,
>> okay and I get like a million of these things
>> I noticed in the distribution that the a signal is by 50% chance of being one or zero
>> the b signal, it could be from a spin
>> If the correlation turns out that whether it's a or b
>> the other one is the same, another one was correlated
>> correlation of one
That's in a real world, a tangled state
>> This could be, I don't know what it's coming from
>> just getting information so I get information a comes through
>> I don't look at it, b comes through, It's a 50-50 chance,
>> I don't look at it, but as soon as I get a
>> so the wave function of b completely changes
>> now the example I'm using is not a state,
>> just Bob and Alice are twins, one's a boy one's a girl
You got to hurry up because I have a get on particles
>> so there was nothing magical about that
>> there is nothing weird about that, they are correlated like that,
>> they are identical, so I'm addressing what is weird about that?
If you don't find it weird good,
What's weirder than you can't simulated classically without having a
central processor connected by wires, that's weird about it
>> So doesn't wires connecting those computers represent non-locality?
Okay now we ask a lot of wires there, for goodness sakes
Surely Bob can send the message through the wires to Alice that takes no time at all,
because they are instantaneous
True enough if this were a real computer set up,
but if Bob is restricted to only do the things which quantum mechanics allows him to do
if he is restricted by the rules of quantum mechanics,
then we find out, Amazingly,
that Bob can never send a message through the wires that violates locality
Why? because all Bob can do is manipulate his own system with unitary operators
and so that's what's curious, here
does that mean that the world is filled up with wires that we can't see
I don't think that's the message
I think the right message,
but of course you you can hear in which is room for debate
what the right message to all of this is
the message I take away from it is basically quantum mechanics
cannot be simulated by a classical system
The logic is two different, the structures of the two theories are too different
and I don't take away the message of the world is full of wires
that if only we could access them
We could send messages back and forth, other people do,
but I think at least if we know how to do quantum mechanics
will agree on the facts we may disagree on basically
whether there are or are not wires there
are there really wires there or are there really not wires there
Well, perhaps a octopus(?) is the word really
but this oh oh,  but there is one other element to it,
which is quite interesting, we made an assumption that
Bob and Alice get kind of randomly make decisions
about when to press the button about what orientations about what to decide to measure
Bob sits here and says okay Northwest and Southeast or whatever
makes these random decisions according to the principle of free will, so to speak,
that's fine as long as Alice and Bob are outside the system and not part of it
We don't need to ask the question of consciousness in the question of free will
we just admit that Alice and Bob can make random decisions
about when to were one to measure various things
It's obviously a pretty good approximation,
but once we take Alice and Bob and put them into the system
so that they are governed by the laws of physics
Then things get a little bit touchy
What do we mean by saying that Alice can decide to do this,
so Bob can decide to do that,
and that I think is where the possible loopholes in all of this can come from
that I don't want to get too deep into heavy philosophical discussions
of all sorts of psychological or questions of consciousness,
I don't know the answers That's it
I don't know the answers beyond what I've told you
I certain of two things about it
I am certain that there are a lot of people who think they do know the answer
and almost certain that they don't
>>Question? Actually not a question, if we google for random challenge
>> you will find the blog entries that has a set up for these
oh really? For the entangled case?
>> It doesn't ⋯ you can hear a program
>> Your challenge is fill in this right place
I see
>> They can give you a million dollar
>> he won't give you a million dollar, some one in Sweden will give you a million dollar
okay that's very interesting okay so I'm not the first one to
that I was the first one to think about it this way
but have been telling us to people 50 years
I don't I buy probably wasn't prior to the big thought about this
Who knows doesn't matter
Let's we could spend the rest of eternity talking about spin ,why,
because they really are interesting,
but you know, we want to get to something else
we want to get the particles we want to get the more complex systems
The most complex system we discussed is two spins fourr dimensional Hilbert space
We've gotten about to the point where in classical physics,
we got to the first lecture of the first lecture was about the simple, discrete systems,
and then we rather immediately moved onto continuous motion
of things like particles moving continuously with an infinitive,
and not just an infinite but a continuously infinite range of possibilities
That's where we have to go now though
Fortunately, we've set up so much of the apparatus of quantum mechanics,
and we can do it fairly quickly
There is a little bit of subtlety about replacing sums by integrals that's about it
That's about the nature of the subtlety
sums and integrals we've expressed our general principles of quantum mechanics,
and then exhibited it in,  a variety of simple spin system
My examples now we will plunge right in the quantum gravity
No we will plunge right in the problem of a single particle
moving on a one-dimensional axis
I will take the axis to be infinite
Although we if we that's mostly because I don't have time to be more careful
If you want to get anywhere as we gonna have to be of
slightly less mathematically rigorous so I have,
and in order to be rigorous,
you really have to contain the system in a finite volume and so forth
But we don't need to do that, so we have a line
a long and infinite line, one particle can exist
We won't do two particles yet
one particle can exist in one dimension,
and that line is labeled by a coordinate X
now write down the coordinate X
but also the state of the particle
The states of the particle are also labeled by the position of a particle
now here we are departing from classical logic in classical logic
The states of a particle are label by a position and the momentum
if we were talking about the states of the spin,
we would say the state of the spin is described by all of the
at least two of the components of spin,
but we can't do that in quantum mechanics,
we can't specify two component simultaneously, same in classical mechanics,
specifying I'm sure you know specifying the position
The momentum is too much
And we'll see how that works will see how that works
but for the moment let's take that as a postulate
that a complete description of the state of a particle
you can't get anymore out is for example to know that
it is located at a position x, and it's located in the position x
we will describe that by a ket vector
The ket vector X, that's the state of a particle when it was located at position x
now of course we can consider more complicated,
more complicated states, linear superposition of these
in quantum mechanics, We are always allowed to make linear superpositions
and so the space of states is bigger than just
the space of particles located definite positions
let's call the general state psi, this is the general state of a particle
doesn't mean anything now just an abstract symbol
and it's a vector in some vector space
The vector space now has a continuously infinite number of basis vectors,
Now strictly speaking, that's mathematically bad thing we gonna play that game
If you want to understand more deeply the mathematics of quantum mechanics
you go when you learn about Hilbert space, but we are not going to do that tonight
So the general state of particles called psi,
remember what the wave function of the system is
the wave function of the system in a particular basis
is the projection of the state on to the basis vectors and we call that, psi of a,
now we come to particle the basis of states are the position states
and what is the wave function?
the wave function is the inner product of the state vector with the eigenvectors of position,
and that's called psi of X that's the wave function that's the classical,
not classical, but that's the standard quantum mechanical wave function
of a particle, it plays the same role as in the simple systems we've discussed,
the inner product of the state vector with a
Now there is a little bit more in this context,
the probability that the system whatever it is,
The system exhibits property a, is given by this thing squared
In fact it's given by psi star of a, psi of a, that's the probability that the system,
That the outcome of an experiment to determine whether the system was at property a
that's a probability likewise
in exact parallel the probability to find a particle at x is equal to psi star of X
times psi of x, I really haven't done anything that we haven't done before
Now in quantum mechanics like in any other sensible statistical theory,
the sum of all probabilities should add up to one,
so the sum of psi star psi should add up to one:
but when probabilities refer to a continuous variable
we don't talk about the probability that the particles was located exactly at point X
It's too sharp, the probability the think located exactly at any given place is 0
we talk about the probability that's located within a range of X or better yet,
we talk about the density of probability we talk about the probability density,
and we integrate this over little range of X,
to find the probability that you in that range of X
we do something like that here,
if we want to know not whether the system is definitely specify as a
but we wanna know whether it's in range of a, we sum over them,
but here we sort of have to do it
total probability equal to one that's the condition
that the integral of psi star of X, psi of X, d X is equal to one
total probability of the system has to add up to one
and the only as I said the only new thing here
is that we have to replace sums by integrals
and it does make mathematical subtlety that we have to worry about,
but it, it sort of in mathematical details okay,
what about the inner product between two state vectors one of X and one of x prime
well here we go back for inspiration right back to
right back to this case
zero, if a is not equal to a prime and one of a is equal to a prime
We are not gonna able to quite get away with that here
We are not going to quite be able to get away with a statement that
XX prime is equal to zero or one
We are going to say that if x is not equal to X prime
that is zero:
But we are not gonna say that it's equal to X prime
That's one, that would not lead us anywhere
what we're going to say is that it's a function which vanishes
unless equals X equals X prime,
but has area 100, we will see how that works out
we will see what that does for us in a moment
What it really comes down to is a different normalization here,
but again the basic idea that states are orthogonal
if X is not equal to X prime that we will retain
but the numerical value of what we get when X is equal to X prime,
we are gonna take this to be slightly different
in fact were going to invent a function
Not we are, Dirac did, Dirac delta function, X minus X prime
the Dirac delta function is not a real mathematical function,
although by now the mathematicians of the find it to death,
so that there is a real mathematical entity,
but for our purposes we can think of it in a very simple way
it's a function which is zero , let's take delta of X
not delta of x, delta of x prime , it's basically built of X minus zero
the function delta of x, it's a function which is zero unless X is equal to zero
That's the same as saying this thing is zero unless X is equal to X prime
so this is X it's zero everywhere except X equals X prime
and X equals X prime, it's a very high, narrow spike
how high and narrow? high enough and narrow enough for the area under is one unit
that means if it's approximated by a narrow interval of size epsilon
that it has height one over epsilon,
and then you imagine a limit when you take epsilon smaller and smaller
one of the epsilon higher and higher,
always keeping the area under equal to one that's the Dirac delta function
Dirac Delta function zero everywhere except when X equals X prime
infinite in some sense when X is equal to X prime,
but in such a way that the area under it is equal to one
alright now let's use this to further elaborate on what the meaning of psi of x is
I'm gonna guess and then we are gonna check
I'm gonna guess that the meaning of psi of X is the following
that if I want to write a general state vector
Psi, that I can think of it as a sum over the basis vectors
but not a sum, a integral, of course it's a integral
because the basis vectors are continuous
d X of some coefficients, some coefficients well let's no,
let's write it this way,
Psi is equal to an integral d X of some set of coefficients
I'm gonna guess what they are, I'm gonna guess that this Psi of x
times the Eigen times the the state
The quantum state with a particle as it located at X
And then we are gonna add them up for different x-s
It's exactly the same thing that we did to ordinary quantum systems,
except this was replaced by a sum
Alright I'm giving you two distinct definitions of psi of X
One is that it's the inner product of the state vector with the eigenvector
acts upon the eigenvector of X, the other is the expansion coefficients
in writing psi as a sum over vectors
Now if you're a little bit uncomfortable with the idea of a continuous basis of vectors
that we integrate over
you are in good company
The mathematics of this is, um as I said
By now it is been made rigorous, but it's it's some,
it took pages and pages and pages and pages
in books and books and books on something called distribution theory
to make sense out of this with precision
But it's pretty intuitive, it's pretty intuitive, and we will stick with that
so let's calculate a prime there,
this is a sum and integral doesn't matter,
doesn't matter what you call the integration variable, let's call it X prime,
and now let's calculate the inner product of X with psi
as I said there were two different definitions of psi of X
let's check that they are the same, so there we have it
integrals of X prime, psi of X prime, inner product of X with X prime
what's the inner product of x and x prime?
I think I wrote it someplace where is it,
I think I erased it, it's equal to the integral of x', psi of x', delta of X minus X prime,
Okay, what is that? First of all Delta is a function
which is zero everywhere except X equals X prime,
so that means that in doing this integral here
you only get a contribution when X prime is equal to x
that means the answer is gonna come out to be proportional to psi of X
furthermore, the area under this delta function is exactly 1
and we imagine that this delta function is a pinched
narrower and narrower high spike so the area under is one
then this integral would tend to psi of X
the rule is if you have an integral over a delta function like this
It simply picks out the value of the integration variable
where the Delta function vanishes
sorry when the argument of that Delta function vanishes
when X minus X prime vanishes that's where the functions is not zero
and the integral of a function with the Delta function just gives you
the value of the function at the point X
That's a rule, we might as well write that down
Let's write that down on blackground as a rule
integral delta of X minus X prime, F of X prime is always equal to F of X
it picks out the value X prime equal to x
That's part of the definition of Delta function
okay so it's just equal to psi of X
and we find consistency that the thing that we call psi of X over here
is the same as the thing that we call psi of X over here
All of this has its exact parallel for the ordinary systems
>> So I'm looking in Psi of x prime times ket vectors
Superposing
>>I'm trying to figure out which of these is
>>Which are the basis vectors?
These are the basis vectors
let's let's compare that with, psi is equal to sum over a, a prime,
let's call it a prime, psi of a prime |a prime >
okay if we used the fact that a and a prime are orthogonal
and do exactly the same thing except replacing sums by integrals
we will also find that the that the Psi that appears here is the same as
the inner product of psi with the basis vectors
So we really done nothing that we haven't done before
and I appreciate it's a little possibly a little unfamiliar
but all it is, is same thing we've done before
>>So psi of x prime sort of plays the same rule as the alphas?
The x prime plays the same role as a prime here
the psi plays the same rule as psi,
the sum is replaced by the integral,
sum over a prime is replaced by integral d X prime,
and otherwise it's exactly the same
let's calculate the inner product,
>>One question,
>>on the right hand side we have direct form in the right hand corner
>>you got a vertical line between the x-es,
>>over here in the middle, there is no vertical line
Thank you, got you got you got you
No absolutely,
How about the inner product of two vectors?
Well, the inner product of some vectors is some inner product,
but one way of calculating the inner product,
let's go back to ordinary the ordinary quantum mechanics
Ordinary means for the discrete systems , we don't need this right now
how do we calculate the inner product?
let's take you what state inner product of psi with phi
We first write psi and phi as sums over the basis vectors,
so this is equal to sum over two sets of basis vectors a prime and a
psi star of a prime times a prime,that's bra vector we complex conjugate of course
we deal with bra vectors that's the psi half of it,
and then the phi half of it is the sum over a,  phi of a times a,
phi of a being the coefficients of the phi vector
psi star being the coefficients of the psi, bra vector
now phi of a is just a number, psi star of a is just a number
and the inner product of a prime with a is just a Kronecker Delta
so all of this adds up to sum of psi star of a prime
phi of a and then a Kronecker Delta of a and a prime which is exactly the instruction
to set a equal to a prime,
I think you seen that before
This is simply the rule about row vectors,
if psi star of a is represented by a row vectors psi star of a one,
Blablablablabla, and Phi is represented by a column vector
and this is just a rule to take this times this plus this times this plus this times this
so this is the common, garden-variety quantum mechanical in a product
I'm not gonna we don't need to go through the same exercise here
we can immediately write down what the result is going to be just by analogy,
it's almost not even an analogy,
it's just replacing wherever we see a, put x-es
and wherever we see sum, put integral
the inner product of two space vectors for a particle on the line
is integral d X psi star of X phi of X, this satisfies incidentally,
one of the basic rules of inner products
what happens to a inner product if you interchange the two vectors?
what's the relation between the inner product Psi-Phi and the inner product Phi-Psi?
complex conjugation, now what will happen in here if you interchange psi with phi
we wind up writing phi star here and psi here
that again would be the inner product of the complex conjugate
and for exactly the same reasons
So this is equal to this for both discrete systems and for these continuous systems
in a product the inner product of a vector with itself
is the norm of the vector just as in previous examples
you normalize a vector to one to express the fact that the probability adds up one,
so not much difference, just a difference of notation
and the what's I think what gets to be confusing about it
is you know both of these things,
you know about these simple row vectors and column vectors
and you know about functions,
but you are not used to thinking of functions as vectors
or maybe you are, if you are good,
but if you are not use to thinking of functions as vector,
as function of psi of x-es,
then you have to get used to it
but functions are vectors in a vector space, you can add them,
you can multiply them by complex constants
and you can add them, you can multiply by numbers,
and so they satisfy the axioms of a vector space
space of functions is a vector space
now sometimes you may want
>>In class of mathematics, would you put the limit of integration
>>minus and plus infinity?
Good, which incidentally said something
It says, we shouldn't be thinking about functions which would grow at infinity for example
we should be only thinking about functions which are square-integral-able
Now we are gonna have to, we gonna have to modify that
square integral means you square them
This is called squaring them that the integral exists
functions which grow at infinity won't do that
Those are crazy because it would say that,
if you have functions which grew with infinity where would the probability be?
a probability will be all located off at infinity
And that's not what we want
we want to be talking about probability distributions
which I have a total finite probability under them
so that means we should take perhaps with a grain of salt
The idea that we can write down any function,
but for the moment we are we are gonna be a little bit loose about that
okay, I think I will slow down here for a few minutes
# and digest it, and ask a few good questions
No, no no no no,
you know a you have a know I had that
I'm I meant about this, but okay
>> This is quick, it seems like everything must be entangled with something
>> almost all the time, is that?
Oh yeah, entangled with all sort of things in the environment,
and we haven't talked about the importance of a complex environment
it's not so important in the very foundations of the subject,
but it is important to why we see the world the way we are,
there were constantly being bombarded and getting getting entangled with things
>>Is there a .. For physicisits?
Oh boy, certainly
>> so okay, it's not just some, it didn't just the Dirac function all about it
oh you mean is that, I see what you mean,
You mean to do anything else besides clean up the .. I don't know
I think it's make rigorous as a set of concepts that physicists use over time
Has it really seems no no
The theory of distributions, ya I will tell you about that with physcists
It made them argue less with mathematicians
was one of the many examples were mathematicians
that drag screaming and kicking with physicists
of course the opposite also happens
but that was an example where mathematicians first looked at this thing
so what are you crazy that doesn't make any sense
It's not rigorous and in time they came to peace with it
through defining it, in a wrong way
No, I don't think the mathematical structure of it has influenced physics
as much as you might've expected
Unfortunately, because there are big problems of confusion
related to it in quantum field theory, and it hasn't resolve those problems okay,
okay, next place we want to go is observables
We want to talk about observables and give some examples of observables
observables are linear operators,
what are linear operators acting on the space of functions?
Their operations on the state on a function that gives another function
linear operator, let's call it M, for some reason
I saved L to stand for observables
and I've used previously M for general linear operator
So I continue to do, so whatever M is,
it's a machine and thought of as an abstract operator on it's space
it takes the state vector into another state vector,
psi prime psi, or a vector and a vector space,
but it also can be thought of as a thing which acts on wave functions
every state has a wave function that describes it
And the, the machine, or, that was why we call it M
Yes I remember now, you call it M for Machine,
the machine can also be thought of as acting on a wave function
to give another wave function,
so let's think of it that way,
let's think of it in concrete terms
as an action that we do on a wave function to produce another wave function
Now it's linear,
linear means that when it acts on the sum of two functions
It gives back the sum of the results,
it means that if it acts on a function which is a numerical product
a numerical multiple of some function it gives back the same numerical multiple
all have ideas of what a linear operator are, continued to be exactly the same
let's talk about some linear, oh, okay that's that's the notion of a linear operator
Now what about a Hermitian linear operator
I will tell you the definition of Hermitian we will,
We've talk about it before,
but I'm gonna give it to you in a condensed form
the condensed form is also true for all of the vector spaces we studied
and you may recognize it, if not, go back and prove that
it follows from the previous definitions
a Hermitian operator Hermitian for operators is, roughly speaking,
the analog of real, as opposed to complex okay,
here's what's true about Hermitian operators if you have a Hermitian operator,
which I will now call L
then it has a property that
if you take if you act on wave function psi or or state vector psi,
and take it's inner product with phi, that that is equal to psi L phi,
but not quite, I will have to do with it,
complex conjugate it, now if L not,
let's go back a step supposing L was not Hermitian
would this be right? not quite
What do we have to do? We have to put a dagger here
another words we have to roughly speaking,
complex conjugate L, if L is Hermitian in the rule for that
is that it's made with matrix elements it's it
It's so when sandwiched when sandwiched in opposite order
You don't have to complex conjugate L because it's already the analog of real
this is a condition that an operator is Hermitian
that's important because Hermitian operators are the class of observables,
so let's work out one or two Hermitian operators
or while we are at it, guess we may need this
so let's work out a couple,
First of all, one the simplest things that I can do to a wave function
I don't know there are many simple things that can do it,
but a very simple thing is to multiply it by x
and even simpler thing would be to multiply it by simple number,
but let's take slightly more complicated multiply it by X
multiplying by X give back a function
so this is it at minimum an operation on a function
is it linear? Sure it is, if x multiplies psi of x, let's say, or Phi of x
it gives x psi of x plus x phi of x
another words if it acts on the sum it gives a sum of the results
If it acts on a numerical multiple of the Psi,
it gives back the numerical multiple, so linear operator
question is it Hermitian? is it a Hermitian operator?
okay so let's check, here's what we have to take
we have to take psi inner product of x times phi, that's this one,
oh sorry, I think I want to do it the other way
Phi X psi, phi X psi,
and ask whether this is true or not
We will check in a minute
No X on them, X is a function x,
we multiply one function by another function that takes functions to functions
It's not a number, it's a variable, any given value of it is a number,
but it's a machine that takes a function psi of x and replaces it by X psi of X
alright, so let's calculate, the wave function of the ket vector
is x psi of x, the wave function of the bra vector is phi star of X
the inner product is, put brackets around it bracket
This is a ket vector inside the bracket, and this is a bra vector
and the rule for taking the inner product, oops, I think I interchanged it
But we will take the inner product is to integrate,
So let's get off the bracket here and just integrate dx
Oops, sorry,dx, that's in this order
What about this order? this order over here,
the inner product without the star without the star
the thing we are gonna compare with is the same thing
except with psi star x phi of x, well look at it
is this integral complex conjugate of this?
Yes, it is, the complex conjugate of phi star phi,
the complex conjugate of psi is psi star and what about X?
X is it's own complex conjugate so yes indeed
X is an operator which satisfies the basic rule of Hermitian operator
that if you interchange the psi and the phi, it complex conjugates
if, what observable does X correspond to?
position, it is the position, it's the Delta function
a eigenvector of position well maybe we will come to that next time
I think I want yesterday, but we will come back to that,
X is an observable, what does it correspond to?
it corresponds to position of the particle
we will prove that by showing that the eigenvectors X
that the vectors X are eigenvectors of that operator,
but not right now, we will do that the next time
It's easy, trivial
>>Question, so when you write x up there
>>It's implied that there really an x?
The X is a function of x,
X? X is an n alphabet, yes,
It's implied that x is a function of x
it has a whole bunch that's right,
it itself is a function which is multiplying another function
so it's an operation on a function which gives another function
that's exactly right,
Let's take another operation or operator
differentiation by differentiate a function they get a function
that the first test of whether it's an operator
If I differentiate the sum of two functions I get the sum of derivatives
by differentiate a numerical multiple of the function
I get numerical multiple of the derivative
it's a linear function, is it a Hermitian operator?
So, here we have to, here we have to get ourselves a fresh blackboard
and check once and for all whether it's well, check whether it's Hermitian
Okay, what happened, what is, let's call it derivative operation
let's call it capital D, D on psi gives us some psi prime,
what about wave function,
D when it acts on psi of x, by definition now,
this is the definition of how D acts,
it simply gives the d Psi by dx,
I may sometimes lapse and going to call this partial derivative with respect to X
it's fine doesn't matter, there is only one X
so it just differentiates , it creates a new function, it's a linear operator
is it Hermitian? okay so let's write down the two Psi of the Hermitian condition here
and see if they are the same, that's all, that's all there is to it
left side is integral phi star of X
times the operation D on psi which is just d psi by d X
what's the other way of doing it on the right hand side?
the other way of doing it is integral psi star, not not doing the same thing
doing something different, psi star of X, d phi by dx
and the question is whether this is the complex conjugate of this?
so let's write equals with a question mark
No no complex conjugate, so let's, let's do this integral over here
First of all a thing in the bra-ket here is just equal to integral
psi of X, d phi star by dX,
just complex conjugate, the complex conjugate of a product
is just a product of complex conjugate
The thing in the bra-ket psi of x d phi star by dx,
When we are asking whether this is equal to this, they look similar,
this has a psi, this has a psi
This have a phi star, this has a phi star,
but unfortunately this one has psi differentiated
and this one has psi, you know what I mean, psi and phi
How do you go from this to this?
integration by parts, and integrate like this,
Assuming, what do we assuming when we say we can integrate by parts
we are assuming that far away the integral, the functions go to zero,
That the end point contributions from integration by part don't give us anything
well of course the functions must go to zero far away
because the integral of the total thing must be one
so we can integrate by parts,
anybody know what integrating by parts is? If not find out fast,
It's simply a rule, I will tell you what the rule is
you can shift the derivative from one if you have a product
dx, that's dX here, if you have a product psi of X time derivative of phi star of X
then you can simply shift the derivative from one function to the other,
but it's at a cost, the cost, the minus sign right?
good, so this is equal to minus the integral phi star of x
d psi by dX, oops, we are in bad shape
This is integral phi star d phi dx,
this is minus the integral of d phi star d psi dx
they are not equal, in fact worse than that,
they are absolutely the opposite of each other
They are opposite in the sense of the negative of each other
can we fix it? Well no we can't fix this,
but we can redefine an operator which is Hermitian,
to redefine operator which is Hermitian, it's not derivative,
it is minus i, the minus sign it doesn't matter,
you can put i or minus I, d by dx,
so let's go through it again and check whether now it's Hermitian
This is the new thing that we gonna call
and we are gonna give it a different name
I'm not gonna call it d, because it's not derivative
it's minus i times derivative,
anybody have a good suggestion for what I call this?
p brilliant, p for, momentum Momentum
and if I really wanted to be momentum with units of momentum
what else would I put there? Where? right or left?
I will put on left but you better put it downstairs
Alright but we are not gonna worry about h bar
We are gonna use our usual convention of ignoring H bar for the moment
p is minus i, d by dx,
let's see what happens, over here we have to replace this by an i over here,
minus i thank you, minus i,
what about this one? with complex conjugate it and everything
we better change the signm because the complex conjugate of minus i is plus i,
so, let's put it this way, minus i, and we should get plus i here if it's Hermitian
Why? because in the process of taking the complex conjugate
every i gets converted to a minus i,
and every minus i gets converted to a plus i,
Is it true now?
Yeah, why, because this is equal to minus this
That's what we proved over here
okay so we stick an i here, because i changes sign on the complex conjugate
this little operation here tells us that minus i d by dx is a Hermitian operator
A little odd isn't it, that minus i, d by dx should somehow be a real thing
should represent the real thing, and d by dx should not
but, let's, let's check something out, let's check something out right now
let's just, we are gonna finish up in a moment
we haven't talked about expectation values yet tonight,
but I think you can guess how to think about them
expectation values in the state psi of an observable L
I just the sandwich composed of psi on both sides and L in the middle
so let's take the expectation value of momentum,
it's integral psi star of X, psi of X and then according to the rule here
p is minus i d by dx, is it real or imaginary?
you are wrong, it's real, so let's prove that it's real, I hope it's real
God hope it's real, okay
So let's integrate by parts
This is equal, first of all, let's take out the minus i,
minus i, integral psi star of X d Psi by dx, now let's integrate that by parts
This is equal to minus i, and then we can switch the derivative
we can switch the derivative to the star variable, integral
d psi star by dx times psi of X,
but then in doing the integration by parts, we have to change the sign
so, here we have a little thereom,
the integral of this thing here with a minus i
is the integral of this thing here with a plus i
What's the complex conjugate of this whole thing?
To complex conjugate it, you replace psi star by psi, or psi is over here,
you replace d psi by, d psi by d x by d psi star by dx
and you replace minus I by plus i
this over here is the complex conjugate of this
Can everybody see that, or should I explain it further?
let's put a minus i out here and write,
this is equal to d psi, this just gives us d psi by dx
minus i, d psi by dx,
this is clearly the complex, the integral are complex conjugate of each other
d psi by dx is this complex conjugate of this
that one is the complex conjugate of this
and i and minus i are complex conjugate of each other
so given that this is the complex conjugate of this and they are equal to each other
what you say about a thing which is equal to its own complex conjugate? It's real
so we prove rather startling fact,
that the integral of psi star of X minus i d psi by dx is real not yes,
I did, and again is because when you integrate by parts you pick up an extra minus sign
so instead of this thing being minus it's complex conjugate,
it's plus it's complex conjugate,
okay so what do we learn?
We learned that this is a Hermitian operator
it's a Hermitian operator and therefore an observable in quantum mechanics
The next time we will explore a little more
We will discuss what this has to do with Fourier transforms
We will discuss questions about what the probability
for finding the particle at different locations are,
but then we will also talk about
what the probability for having different momentum are
And then we move to the Schrodinger equation
We will move to the evolution of the, of the wave function
This, after all, now is really in the classic sense of the word wave function
and we will think about how it evolves with time
Oh one of the thing we,
we could do it tonight or think I think would probably
at the point of diminishing returns, Are you exhausted?
we could do one more thing let me do one more thing for you
Let's calculate an interesting quantity
and why it's an interesting quantity will come through in a moment
so let's take a quantity which seems very dull, but it's interesting and calculate it,
it's the commutator of x with p
take any wave function, whatever it is, psi of X anyone
And we are gonna do two things with it,
We are first gonna multiply it by X,
and then we are gonna multiply this by minus i d by or
operate would like minus i d by dx,
this can be called p x operating on psi
This is P this is X in the order first X then P
then we are gonna calculate it the other way
XP on psi, what was that?
the other half of the blackboard over here,
we are gonna write x times minus i d by dx psi of x
and see what we get, in fact what we are gonna do is
We are gonna do the commutator, which means we are gonna calculate this one
with a plus, I'm gonna calculate this one with a plus sign,
and this one with a minus sign
but before we subtract them ,let's just calculate them
Alright, this is just minus i
and now the derivative of a product
The derivative of the product
This derivative here now has to act on the whole result of x acting on psi of x
x acting on psi of x gives a new wave function,
and then P act on it
So what you get when you hit the product? You get two terms
The first term is the derivative of X times psi derivative of x is just one,
So the first term is just Psi of x
and the second term is plus X d psi by dx, everybody agree with that?
the derivative hit X in left psi, and then the derivative hit psi and left x,
This is the Psi over here, now what about the psi over here?
here, the d by dx doesn't act on x, it just act this way
it just acts on psi of X and gives us minus i d by dx psi of x
Sorry, X minus i X d psi by dx, now let's subtract them,
let's take this one with minus, and this one with plus
this corresponds to taking the commutator of X with P
acting on psi of X, commutator of X with P is another operator
and it acts on psi of X, what we get when we subtract?
let's see, this one now has to come with a plus sign
since we are subtracting ,some sort of subtracting we have to change sign here
and this term cancels,  this term cancels goes away,
and all were left with a psi of X,
that's all that's left with this term cancels, now we just left i psi of X i psi of X
alright so here's what we've found
for any psi of X whatever for any psi of X
the commutator of X with P acting on psi of X just gives
If it's a plus i, I think it's a plus i, psi of x
now if an operator acting on any wave function gives another operator,
but if the operator, XP acting on any wave function
is the same as i acting on that same wave function
for any wave function whatever
it follows that this operator is equal to this operator
Another way of saying it is if XP minus i
Put all in a big bracket, when hits any wave function at all give zero
then it means that this is zero,
there is only one operator which give zero when it acts on every state
On every vector, there is no vector which escapes when this thing hits it
The implication is that this thing is zero,
This is the only one operator which annihilates which kills every vector to zero
XP, minus, commutator XP is equal to i
that I put back the h bar, there would be an h bar here, i h bar
we've seen things like this before, you may have to go back to classical mechanics
we've seen things before, like this,
we've seen Poisson brackets which had similar relationships
Poisson bracket of X with P is equal to one
earlier in this course we discussed the potential relationship
we had reason to discuss why commutators have to do with the Schrodinger's equation
go back but we discussed the relationship,
it might be a relationship between commutators of Poisson brackets in particular,
the relation involved this i h bar
this is actually the way Dirac began his discussion of quantum mechanics
He said there must be something analogous to a Poisson bracket in quantum mechanics
and the only thing to think of which had the right algebraic structure
anti-symmetric, had a certain mathematical structure was the commutator
and he postulated that commutators and the Poisson brackets were related with each other
To an i h bar,
and then proceeded to go exactly backwards from the way that we went,
he said, if this is a if this is the Poisson bracket
then this must be the commutator, then there must be an operator P
was commutator x with i, and we went back through the operation
and discovered that P was minus i d by dx
so we went the opposite direction
We discovered P by just playing games,
let's say how about this operator d by dx have to do?
What we've found is that it was, it was not Hermitian
we have to multiply it by i to make it Hermitian
We explore it a little bit found out some interesting properties of it,
but the most interesting property is that it's commutator is equal to i h bar
which suggests that it's connected with the Poisson bracket
the classical Poisson bracket being one
of course the upshot of it, of course we need to do a lot more to convince ourselves
the operator minus i d by dx really behaves like quantum mechanical momentum
You can't just say it looks like a Poisson bracket
it must be the quantum mechanical momentum
we have to show that wave packets move with velocities
that the governed by the by the by this that thing must be conserved
that it has all the properties of momentum,
but we will
>> Is there some connection between these abstract operators
>> minus i derivatives and the body of mass
Well we would like to show that in some way that
it is mass time velocity, so what we will try, we will eventually show
that if you have a wave packet another words,
a psi of X which is a concentrated distribution like this,
and that wave packet moves along the x-axis
with a velocity which is given by the expectation value of this momentum operator
divided by the mass, that's what we would like to show
the velocity with which this wave packet propagates along the axis of velocity
just that we call the group velocity
Velocity that the group of waves move along times the mass of the particle
is equal to the expectation value of the momentum
once we do that, then I think we are, and I think that's conserved
that'll take us a long way of calling it momentum
at some point we have to say quantum mechanics is more fundamental in classical mechanics
and the definition of momentum should be true quantum mechanics,
and then we should show how it behaves in a certain way
when particles are heavy and so forth
for more, please visit us@Stanfordedu