Stanford University
I gather you people have a lot of fun with entanglement
It is a good subject  I mean it really is
absolutely the heart of quantum mechanics,
but of course yeah I mean, I would say up until now we have really studied
the foundations of quantum mechanics in very very simple systems
And the foundations have been laid out they've been exposed
you know what they are, and really the only thing left to do now
is to study some examples
>>Can I ask a question?
>> So in the classical mechanics you started with a very small number of
>>empirical observation by Newton more or less
More or less
>>So what's the equivalent in the case of the quantum mechanics?
>>What are those basic atomic empirical observations
You mean historically?
>>Well the minimal set that you need
well I would say the minimum set is what we describe
when we talk about an apparatus which you can rotate
a spin and the window and the apparatus that was zero and one
That would logically be the simplest thing you can do
is of course not the way quantum mechanics was discovered
But just analyzing the experimental data that you would get
by taking an electron or spin
orienting your, your detector, pressing the M button the measure button
and getting a one or minus one on the screen
doing this over and over and over again accumulating statistics
Ah...It's the simplest thing you can do
>>You have to do that for each physical properties like momentums
spin and so on
>>On the system we described about the singlet and triplet
>>and the photon going out,
You said you can capture the photon and reflect it back
>> Is that because you have a system with a Singlet and triplet?
>>Or can any other photons also cause this entanglement?~
No. But that's a good question
Well...En...You don't have a photon out there.
You have a photon or you don't photon
The radiation field itself is not in the state of positive..
Whether or not you have a photon out there could also be thought of
as zero or one.
The radiation state itself.  The radiation system itself
could be modeled by having another degree of freedom
and the other degree of freedom could also have the zero or one
The zero would mean no photon present one would be in the photon present
okay
so what happens?Let's suppose we start with
a singlet and the triplet superposed in this way
with no photons, alright so to express the fact that
there are no photons we have to put another degree of freedom in here
and we have to say this is a tensor product
with the state of the radiation field
which has no photons, that's the story, Keep in mind
this here represents the two electrons
either in the singlet state of the triplet state
and this represents the state of the, of the radiation field
now if you wait for a little while
and while the electrons are entangled here
they are not entangled with the radiation field
This is a simple product of a vacuum of photons
no photons and a particular state of the, of the electron pair
in fact I said this was entangled this is not entangled
this combination was just up down
Alright let it evolve for a while,
what happens is the singlet state is the singlet
and it does not emit a photon but the triplet
what happens to it?
it becomes the singlet and emits a photon
So what happens to the state ?
it is evolves into linear combination of singlet times
no photon and one photon . Another words,
the singlet electron,  it's a singlet state of the electron pair,
but a linear superposition, quantum linear superposition
of no photon and one photon
That seems a little bit strange,
but it's an important idea
that you can not only superposed states of a particle
you can superposed the number of particles
No particle and one particle could be quantum
And two states can be super-posed
so the state of a system of the vacuum empty space
That's a state of no photons, the state with one photon,
That's a state with one photon and you can add them
that's what's happening here,
You would eventually come to the state which is singlet
times no photon plus one photon
This state now is entangled between..
Are the electrons entangled with the radiation field?
No because it's pure product
But are the electrons entangled with each other?
Ya because it's singlet state, only the singlet state appears here
And the singlet state is entangled state,
So electrons are entangled with each other
But they are not entangled with the radiation field
On the other hand, the radiation field is left in a superposition of states
of having a photon of not having a photon
So what do we start with?
We started with a un-entangled state of the electrons
totally un-entangled with the radiation field
I say this is an un-entangled with the electrons
because that's what we started with |u d> |u d>and no photon
We started with un-entangled completely everything un-entangled
waited for a photon to be emitted
when the photon was emitted the triplet state became the singlet state,
but it emit a photon and the result was
an entangled state of the electrons
but un-entangled with the radiation field
okay pretty tricky set of ideas
>> You haven't talked anything external like a magnetic field
>>So what's causing?
No nononono, in order to, There is nothing external here
>> So what causes the triplet to emit the photon?
>>Is it with the interaction to the other electrons
Right, the interaction between the two electrons
roughly speaking each electrons in the magnetic field of another electron
but what they want to do was maximally anti-aligned or better yet
they want to minimize or make maximally negative
value of Sigma, that's tau
That's the, so they emit a photon to do that
Last time we start to move on to the problem of particle motion
Forget particle spin,
of course real particles may have both position and spin
but let's concentrate for today
on questions relating to the position of particles
The simplest example we can think of
is a particle moving on a one-dimensional axis X there it is
En...Before we study that I want to do a little mathematical interlude
It will take at most 10 minutes
Having to do with Fourier analysis, Fourier transforms
and its relationship to the Dirac Delta function
So let's stick blackboard and do some mathematics on it
the function e to the ipx, let's take p to be a number
p is a number now it's not a variable
e to the ipx, That's a combination of sine and cosine functions
and therefore has a wavelike character and we call it a plane wave
We call it a plane wave, are just the simple waves cosines and sines
combination of cosine p dot x i sine p dot x
And you could think of it as a wave
Of course it's not moving,
and just e to the ipx doesn't give you any time-dependent
So it doesn't move, so these are wavelike
Okay, a very wide class of functions and certainly all the functions
we will be interested in can be written as sums of plane waves
or integrals better yet, integrals of plane waves
and decomposing a function in this case a function of X
let's call it psi of X
decomposing it in the plane waves is called Fourier analysis
Now most of you know that in fact most of you
and some of you in any case know about Fourier analysis
where we gonna spell it out now
Every function that we will be interested in,
in fact it's probably true that that excludes almost all functions
but we also exclude almost all functions when we say
that there continuous when we say that there differentiable
when we say that we can express them in any meaningful sensible form
we exclude almost all functions
But we take all functions to be reasonably continuous reason
I will not try to be very very precise
Continuous and the, not to blow up at infinity
and falls to zero at minus infinity and plus infinity
Almost all functions L, all functions we will be interested in
can be expanded in waves,
you know expanded means they can be written as integrals over P
what is P? P tells you how fast the wave oscillates
this is some moderate value of p
if I increase P I create a wave of very short wavelength
decrease P I'm talking about wave with a very long wavelength
So this is just saying we can decompose function
into waves of different wavelengths
each wavelength has an amplitude
and an amount of that wave that's in there.
I will call that psi twiddle of p
timese to the ipx, psi twiddle of p
is just the amplitude that, that the wave of type P has strength psi of p
in the functions psi of X
Fourier's theorem is a theorem which tells you how to reconstruct
Psi twiddle, I'm gonna, just for definitions, really just for definition
I'm gonna put one over square root of two pi here
let's, that's the convention,
we could have absorb it into Psi twiddle of p
Psi twiddle is typically complex and so will psi of X be complex,
both of them might intend for the moment to the complex
now may happen that one of these is real and the other one is complex
It can happen but at the moment we just interested in
arbitrary complex functions
That's right, alright the question is
how do you reconstruct Psi twiddle of P from psi of X ?
and I'm going to leave it is something you can look up if you don't know it
It's the basic theorem of Fourier analysis
that Psi twiddle of P,
notice that, psi of X is an integral over P
Psi twiddle of P is going to be an integral over X
d X over square root of two pi
times psi of X, the natural thing would be to write here e to the ipx
but it's not particular minus ipx
Alright two pi, Thank you
That's the basic theorem of Fourier analysis
that psi of X is the Fourier transform of Psi twiddle of P,
defined in this way
And Psi twiddle of P is a Fourier transform of psi of X
very much the same pattern except for the e to the minus ipx there
We will need that theorem, so if you don't know that theorem
it's a very important theorem in quantum mechanics
and expresses a kind of reciprocal relationship between X and p
which, of course, ultimately are going to be position and momentum
Okay that's that's one little mathematical interlude
That maybe have to do with the Delta function
and then we are gonna combine them together
For mathematician the definition of,
we have a, we have a intuitive definition of the Delta function
it's a high, narrow function,
it's so narrow that it's width is essentially zero
and so high that the area under it is one
we can call that a representation of the Delta function
A definition of the Delta function,
because the Delta function is not a real function
it's infinite somewhere but you know,
that's the hey no attitude about the Delta function
It took years from physicist incidentally to convince mathematicians
the Delta function was okay
that mathematicians didn't like them, for very good reason
Their functions, they can't, you can't square them
They just, if you square them, they are still zero everywhere
Except at the same point but instead of having a height of
Big enough to make the area one
they have a height which is the square of that
So they themselves are not a, are worse objects
but they got over it, they got over it
And told now by some of the mathematician friends
that it's okay to write the Delta function
okay properties of the Delta function,
the first thing and the way a mathematician will think about it
is it's an operation that you can do on a function
In particular you can integrate any function of X
any reasonable function of X
with the Delta function Delta of X minus X prime
Oh no, let's go a step (back), let's see them go,
let's not even do that yet
Let's take Delta of X minus X prime times F of X
First property of the Delta function is that this is equal to F of X prime
times Delta of X minus X prime, why would that be true?
That certainly wouldn't be true for a general function Delta
The reason it's true is because Delta is only nonzero
when X is equal to X prime
So it's no big deal,
Delta of X minus X prime is only nonzero when X equals X prime,
and therefore it doesn't matter whether you put X or X prime
when multiplying it by a function
so that that's property number one
Now property number two that pretty much follows from that
No, not yet,property one,  property two
Integral of Delta of X minus X prime is always equal to one
that's just the statement that the area under this bump is equal to one
and it doesn't matter where you put it
Let's put it over here, we put it over here, we put it over here,
the area is always equal to one,
and so the integral of Delta of X minus X prime,
let's say from minus infinity to infinity is always equal to one
And the last property which follows from these two
is that the integral, the integral of Delta of X minus X prime,
F of X is equal to F of X prime, now you see it in two ways.
One is that you can say look
The Delta function is only nonzero when X is equal to X prime
and so it picks out the value X prime
or you can just say use property where is a property number one,
To rewrite this in the form F of X prime,
Integral Delta of X minus X prime, d X
Why am I allowed to bring the F of X prime on the outside?
Because it doesn't depend on X
>>X prime is a constant value
From the point of view of, ya, that's right
So I just bring it on the outside and then I say
the integral under the Delta function is one
and so I just get F of X prime,
Alright so that's the obvious properties of the Delta function
which you might use, the axiom applies, what a Delta function is
Okay now I'm going to prove a theorem
which provides a representation of the Delta function
An important representation of Delta function
Let's, I think I can erase this for the moment
I may have already said that but I probably didn't
Integral F of X Delta of X minus X prime
is equal to F of X prime
now this actually is a sufficient definition of the Delta function
this is the way mathematicians define it
As an operation that you do on a function
that gives value of the function at some point,
and this is enough to define the Delta function
If it's not enough to define the Delta function
there is only one function left,
if this is true for every function F
There is only one function only one Delta here that will fill at property
Okay so this can be taken as the defining function
if for all x, this is true, than this is the Delta function
What's that? Yes, d X, good d X
Okay now what I wannado is I want to take the two top equations
and put them together, here's what I'm gonna do,
I'm gonna write the psi of X is equal to this thing
but then you plug in for this thing,
the second equation,
and re-express psi of X back in terms of the function psi of X itself
Let's see what we get,
either we will get something completely trivially stupid
Or we will learn something, in fact we will learn something
So let's take psi of X and write it,
psi of X is equal, I'm just gonna write now
integral dP over the square root of two pi
e to the ipx, and now I'm going to shove in the second equation
the psi of psi twiddle of P, and that is
Let's put a bra-ket around it
d X integral, let's,
Hold on a second,
Let's call it psi of X prime and to make a psi of X prime,
all we have to do is put a prime here
Just change the name of variable on the left side
and to do so of course I have to change the
name of the variable on the right hand
I don't want to confuse X and X prime
Alright now the second equation for psi twiddle of P
that I can leave as it is,
and just write an integral d X over square root of two pi
psi of x, e to the minus ipx, so just plug been psi twiddle of p
now integrals
are generally insensitive to which order you do the integrals
is particularly if there integrations from minus infinity to infinity
as they are here both of them
If they are well-defined and converged and everything
that it doesn't matter which order you do the integrations
so let's start
let's isolate some things, let's put here integraldp over two pi
Oh over two pi, we now have a single factor of two pi
One coming from here one coming from here.
Let's isolate e to the ipx prime minus X from here
with e to the ipx prime,e to minus ipx
That's e to the ip(Xprime minus X)
And then we still haven't written down psi of X
So let's write down psi of X,
And now interchange the order of integration of X and P
and write this as an integral d X
Integral d x, that's equal to psi of X prime,
So look what we have,
we have a relationship between psi of X and psi of X prime
We have a way of writing psi of X prime in terms of psi of X
But what is it?but look what stands here,
Take this whole thing here, this is an integral over p, it's true
But all it is some function of X prime minus X right?
Let's give them a name, let's call it the capital Delta function
Let's call this the capital Delta function write this
Dx, capital Delta of X prime minus X,
It's whole messier, including the two pi and everything else
After integration over P times psi of X, equals psi of X prime
What does it tell you about this capital Delta function?
It is just a good old Delta function,
it is just good old Dirac Delta function
So we've prove an interesting relationship
and one that is at the heart of many many things in quantum mechanics
Here it is, the integral dP over two pi, e to the ip of X minus X prime
is equal the Delta of X minus X prime  Another words,
it's kind of screw all the way of writing the Delta function
by itself expressing it as a Fourier transform or a sum of plane waves
We can also write this, we can write, I'm writing the same thing
I'm writing a different thing, but just like interchanging X and P
By interchanging X and P I can write another equation
d X over two pi, e to the ix of P minus P prime
equals Delta of P minus P prime
this is, these two are identical, these two are identical
I just change the name of X to P and P to X
If this equation is true this equation is true
because there exactly the same equation
Except that I interchange the name X with P and P with X
That's , so this is a, this is an important as I said
Fact about Delta function
these and the basic mathematical facts that we need
This here is not important, we've got a blackboard over there
Oh if you don't like the way I get the second one from the first one
By just interchanging P and X,
You can go back to these equations
and instead of eliminating psi twiddle of P
Eliminate psi of X by stuff substituting in psi of X from here
and you get, you know, you just interchange P and X
good, alright, so now we have what we need
>> On the left hand side, you wrote X prime minus X
>> On the right board, you wrote X minus X prime
>> Does that imply a
I told you it doesn't matter, it's a good question
It doesn't matter and the reason is Delta of X minus X prime is unchanged
if you interchange X and X prime
It's a symmetric function of its argument
If you interchange Delta of X minus X prime is the same as
Delta of X prime minus X
So you can check that, so the answer is it doesn't matter
You are probably right, I probably did the derivation systematically
I might have got X prime minus x here
But then in the end it does not matter
So let's add this equation over here integral dP over two pi
E to the IP either X minus X prime or X prime minus X, it doesn't matter
is equal to Delta of X minus X prime
and integral dX over two pi, E to the i P minus P prime times X
X, is equal to Delta of P minus P prime
Alright, now let's come back to the world of physics
Theworld of quantum mechanics, a particle on the line
If we are doing classical physics,
we would describe the particle on the line
The state of the particle on a line by a point in a phase space
And phase space consists of a value of X and the value of P
one of each, for a one-dimensional particle just one, one X and one P
what about quantum mechanics?
How do we describe the state of a quantum mechanical particle?
Well you can try to make some guesses
Not have you to describe the state, but what can
how do we describe an orthonormal basis of states?
That's always is the question, give me, when you start in the new system
you ask what defines the space of states?
And one way of defining the space of states is to provide
an orthogonal normalized basis of states
and all states then are linear superpositions of that basis
Alright there are various possibilities
You might wonder, maybe
the states can be represented by the position of a particle X
You might think maybe they can be represented by the momentum of a particle
All you might wonder might the states be represented as a pair an X and a P
this is large, after all in classical physics,
it takes an X and a P to describethe position of, the state of a particle
What is it in quantum mechanics?
The answer of it in quantum mechanics is X and P are too much information
In the same way that for the spin knowing Sigma X and Sigma y
Or Sigma Z and Sigma Y or whatever is too much information
You can't know both of them simultaneously
The same of course is true in quantum mechanics
It's actually more familiar
for it's called the Heisenberg uncertainty principle
but you can't know both, So it's one or the other
Classical physics,a particle has an X and P
In some sense in quantum mechanics a particle has an X or P
Meaning to say you don't try to describe it by both
You described it by one or the other
We will see what the relationship is at a moment
So we suppose that there is an eigenvector of an observable position
For every value of the observable position
This vector represents a state in which the position of the particle
is definite and at position X,
That's an eigenvector,something which will think of as an observable X
We will understandable it more mathematically in a moment
And like any good basis,
the point of a basis is to write any wave function
psi or any state vector as a superposition,
a sum of the basis vectors,
this is the basis vectors form a continuous range of possibilities.
We write it as an integral dX replacing the sum
and then eigenvector X times something which depends on X
this is completely analogous to what we've done in the past
but we've retaken an arbitrary vector and
expanded in terms of eigenvectors of something
and these are the coefficients here
and we call these things the wave function
We call these things the wave function
In fact they are given by the inner product of the eigenvector psi
eigenvector X with the state psi, that is psi of X,
this is fully analogous to what we studied in simpler systems
wave function is the projection of the state
onto a state of definite X psi of X
And secondly psi star of X times psi of X is a probability
That the particle be found the position X
Now strictly speaking we talk about last time,
strictly speaking you have to think of it as  a particle
as a probability density,
a probability per unit X, or a probability per unit interval of X
but you know you have to take that into account
Alright, so that's this is the basic framework of quantum mechanics
just being repeated except for a continuous variable
The inner product between two vectors X and X prime
is zero, unless X equals X prime,
and if these were continuous if these with standard discrete variables
we would say zero unless X equals X prime
one if X equals X prime, we would write Kronecker Delta XX prime,
but X that's not helpful for continuous variables
for continuous variables we write the Delta function
Delta function Dirac Delta function,
it's a continuum analog of the Kronecker Delta
We have bra vectors and ket vectors
If a ket vector is described by a psi of X
a bra vector of course would be describe in a similar way
in terms of psi star of X
so kets psi of X, wave functions bras, psi star of X
usual thing nothing new here
Finally the inner product, not finally but the inner product
not between X and X prime,
but between two arbitrary states,
let's call them psi and phi,
each one of which can be expanded by use of a wave function
phi is described by a wave function phi of X, the bra vector psi,
Can you tell difference between my psi-s and my phi-s when I say it?
This is Greek phi this is Greek psi,
but I can never say p-si, I just say psi
I think the Greek sort of, anybody know?
>> So is this really just a bunch of Psi-phi (sci-fi)?
Write that down, keep that, good
And this one is described by psi star of X
and if you expand them both appropriately in eigenvectors of X
bra vectors and Vectors,  and then use the inner product rule here
for the eigenvectors of X
you would get of course that the inner product is the integral dx
It follows by simply expanding psi expanding phi
And they are using this inner product here
but it's also hardly surprising
the same kind of formula that we would have previously for the discrete systems
and last but
>>Question? So position and momentum is too much information
>>So we are certain really that just the position gives us the complete basis
>>and given anything else is just too much information
>>not just (position or momentum)
>>or redundant
Yeah, pretty much everything else
Now the only reason I'm hesitating is because
we imagine a particle moving in two dimensions
In that case is not clear
you whether you can know the x coordinates of the position
And the y-coordinate of momentum for example
And the answer is you can
So but if our system was just a particle in one dimension
that's it
X and,alright, so that's a good point
>>So does that mean that momentum and the subjugate
>>can be psi
Say that again?
>>So does that mean momentum can be treated as psi?
>>as it's expanded with an integral of x
Yes, the Fourier transform is for, right,
okay let's um, oh, one last thing
The probability density, the psi star psi, notpsi star phi
And if I integrate psi star psi with respect to X
that would be the inner product of psi with itself
and that should be equal to one on the basis that
the total probability should be one
another words nothing new again, physical state should be normalized
Normalized so that integral psi star psi is equal to one
Okay now next, last time we talk about some observables
The position and the momentum
so let's so reviewe a little bit about that, let's invent an operator,
now capital X here
maybe I should, how can I indicate that it's a capital X
let's put a line in it that makes it capital X and therefore an operator
as opposed to just a number or a eigenvalue
this is the operator or the observable
which whose eigenvalues or the positions of a particles the observables
the observable values, let's talk about the action of psi, of X
when it hits a vector, that's what a operators do
theyhit a vectors and they make new vectors
I'm going to tell you what the action is
by telling you how it behaves in terms of wave functions
Instead of telling you how psi acts on a abstract vector
I'm going to tell you what happens
when the operator X hits a wave function
Wave functions and state vectors can be thought of as a ,
one being a representation of the other
when X hit PSI of X, what it does is just multiply psi of X by X
another words it gives you another function
that's the nature of operators they act on functions
to give other functions
They act on vectors to give other vectors
If functions are representations
or constructions which represent those vectors
then whatever linear operators are
they should be such that the do something to the wave function
and this is what X does to the wave function
It simply multiplies it by X, it gives you new function which are
It's not the same functions, it's a different function,
but that's,that's the nature of it
now let's prove something
let's prove that the eigenvectors and the eigenvalues of this operator
or what we expect them to be
You of course do expect them to be something
You may not realize at this moment that you expect them to be something
But as soon as I show you what they are,
you will say, yes we expected that
Okay so what is likely to be the eigenvector of capital X?
Well it should be a state,
that should be a state with a particle is localized at position X
In particular let's so
let's talk about the particle being localized at point X not
What would we expect the eigenvector to be?
It should be a function which is zero everywhere except that X not right?
That's,that's what we would expected should be concentrated at X not
And so let's try the function Delta of X minus X not
X not is just a parameter here now, it's a function of X
But it's a function of X which represents the particle at position X not
And let's ask the question when you operate with the operator X
on this wave function what do you get?
Well the answer is, you just multiply it by little X
But now we go back to one of the properties of the Delta function,
Namely that when you multiply it by any function of X
You could replace it by function of X prime,
So or in this case X not,
this is also equal to X not times Delta of X minus X not
But what is this equation?
This is exactly the equation for an eigenvector of
an eigenvalue of the operator X, the operator X hits the wave function
and gives a number times the same wave function
the operator hits wave function gives number times wave function
It's clear that this is an eigenvector of the operator
with eigenvalue X not
So now we can make a list of the eigenvectors of various of
various of observables
We are starting out list, eigenvalues and eigenvectors
The eigenvector associated with a particle localized the point X not
that is equal to the Delta function of X minus X
Exactly as you expect it right? good okay, I'm sure you did
And that finish up x,
what about P what about momentum?
Again momentum being an observable
you can observe if it hits you in the side of the head you feel it
You recoil, that's what momentum is, it's,  momentum
means the same thing in quantum mechanics as in classical mechanics
it's conserve and so if you absorb something was a momentum
you recoil
Alright what was the momentum operator?
The momentum operator and we will make just ification for this
We will come over a little later
We did talk about it but I want to go back over
Momentum is called P
The operator momentum
And the operator momentum is equal to
there is no point beating around the bush
Let's say what it's equal to, it is equal to minus i,
And I am going to put in some units here
Later on we will set h bar equal to one
It's just the choice of units but for the moment let's keep h bar there
times the derivative operator D
The thing I called D last time or the operator D
The last time we studied whether capital D was Hermitian or not
And we found that it was not
but if we multiply that by i either with a ± it doesn't matter
If we multiply it by an i, then it becomes Hermitian
So we work that out last time if you remember that the little trick
with integration by parts,
We found that D was not Hermitian
but i times D is, so this is the definition of momentum operator
Or it's a bunch of symbol so far
But what is P do when it acts on a wave function?
It just gives minus ih bar times d psi by d x
So it's also an operator, it's also an operation
It's an operator it's a linear operator
and it is a Hermitian linear operator P
So that's what it takes to qualify as an observable in quantum mechanics
At this point since psi is only a function of one variable
it doesn't matter whether I use partial derivatives
or just ordinary derivatives
dlet's call them ordinary derivatives d psi by d X
next question what is the eigenvectors of a momentum?
the eigenvectors of the momentum satisfy P on psi or minus I h bar
d psi by d X equal some eigenvalue
Some observable value or some possible outcome of an experiment
let's call it P not time psi
This of course P not is a number, it's a eigenvalue
We can let's,let's just if we get rid of the minus i here,
It becomes plus I on this side now we can divide it by h bar
Right so this is just the equation for an exponential
Derivative being proportional to the same function
And the solution for psi,
it's unique apart from the multiplicative constant psi
This is the eigenvector as a function of X
and let's labeled by P not, let's just label it by the fact that
it's the eigenvector for momentum P not
It's a function of X and what is it?It's e to the i P not X
Question?Oh thank you, over h bar
Alright I just keep theh bar around for about ten more seconds,
I just want to point out that this is a wavelike thing
This is a wavelike thing, it has sines and cosines
and it has a wavelength,
the wavelength is the distance that you have to move
so that the thing in the exponent changes by two pi
Another words if we call the wavelength lambda
P not over h bar times lambda equals two pi
it's a definition of the wavelength how far you have to move
so that the sines and cosines returned to themselves
or that the wavelength is two pi h bar divided by P not
P not being the momentum of the particle
so, here we see the first example of the relationship
between momentum and wavelength
Larger the momentum smaller the wavelength
Of course we have not yet justified
the choice of the terminology momentum for this thing
but we can keep in mind later on we are gonna come back
and see that this P really does behave like momentum,
but so far it's just an abstract observable
we don't know what it means yet
Okay so here we are,lambda is equal to this
and now that I have demonstrated that let's get rid of h bar
becauseI will forget about it anyway
let's get rid of h bar, get rid of this formula here
and say this is the
now it's not clear that I have normalized this correctly
It's not clear yet that this is normalized to one
Let's take the inner product between two momentum states
This is, this here is a representation of the momentum state P not
Or let's just call it P, let's just call it P, get rid of the not
It's not serving any real purpose here, P
I think of P, just P
Let's take the inner product of two momentum states P prime and P
Where is our formula for inner products?
Here it is right over here
Alright, no, here it is over here
One psi star and one phi,
so that means the inner product is the integral
of e to the minus i P prime X
that's the wave function of P prime
or the complex conjugate of it
and then the wave function for E to the i PX dx
Or equivalently integral E to the i P minus P prime X d X
Now if we've done things right,
this P is supposed to be a observable a Hermitian operator
And the eigenvectors of Hermitian operators should be orthogonal
Then this should be zero if P is not equal to P prime,
It's pretty clear that it is zero,
P is not equal to P prime for the following reason
The real and imaginary parts of e to the i P minus P prime X
are cosines and sines,
If P is not equal to P prime,
these are cosines and sines of P minus P prime X
cosines and sines are as positive as they are negative
If you integrate them over a large interval you will get zero
As long as you pick up an integer number of wavelengths in the that's
That's important, so as long as P is not equal to P prime
This integral just oscillates itself to zero
Equally positive an equally negative for both the real and imaginary parts
so it is true
P prime is not equal to, sorry P the inner product is equal to zero
IfP is not equal to P prime
What about if P is equal to Pprime
this is integral from minus infinity to infinity
Without looking at the other blackboard then what can we say about this?
For P not, for P equal to P prime
This is gonna be infinite right?
The integral of one integrated over all space is infinite
So in fact it sort of looking and smelling like it is the Delta function
It's smelling like it is the Delta function
infinite when P is equal to P prime
And zero or otherwise it's a good thing
but we don't know what the actual numerical coefficient is
But yes we do, up here we have integral where is,
that's this one over here integral dx over two pi
It's delta of P minus P prime
The upshot of this is just that in order for this to be normalized
so it's inner product is a real Delta function
You will have to describe this divided by the square root of two
Ya, square root of two pi, big deal
square root of two pi
this is the wave function for a particle of momentum
A particle of momentum P
We now know what the wave functions of particles of momentum P are
>>Question?
>>When you are talking about two different version of P and P prime
You talked about taking the integral from minus infinity to infinity to sum
>>in an oscillating function and you said this is zero
And I just trying to think in my head that normally if you do an intergral
>>You, how do you justify that zero?
I can see there is sort of error in zero, but I'm not sure if it's justify
I knew somebody is gonna ask
The answer is that you really justify it
by starting with a theory on a finite integral
You are asking I think questions about convergence of the integral
Integral doesn't really converge
So you really have to go back to some earlier starting point
which have I start, if I were teaching quantum mechanics
in graduate class of something I would have started by
thinking of theory on a finite integral or even better
on a finite periodic integral, work it out and then
taking carefully the limit as you let things get go to infinity
and then everything could be justified with rigor
We don't have the time and so I don't do that,
but of course
>>Is about the Fourier transform itself right?
>>It's not really about quantum mechanics and physics
It's a fact about the Fourier transform but I did cheat
I did cheat at some point that I interchange
an X integration with the P integration
And one of those integrations didn't converge
I did basically the same cheat that I did here
But you know I wouldn't cheat you
if I didn't know that the steps can be filled in
and if I didn't know that
you will go find yourself a book on Fourier transforms
you won't be able to fill the stuff in yourself
so I haven't really cheated
what I've done was just a little bit of a short shortcut.
Right now we've talk about the wave functions of particles with momentum P
but now I want to talk about a different concepts
The wave function in the momentum basis
So far all of these wave functions have been thought of
as functions of X
P here is just a parameter it's the momentum of the particle.
But the wave functions a function of x
Oh, incidentally notice something important
Notice something important,
the wave functions of particles with definite momentum
oscillate endlessly forever and ever
and they are absolutely un-localized
They are as de-localized as they can be and in particular psi star psi of X
is uniformly spread out over the entire real axis
In no sense is the position well-defined
It is as uncertain as it could be
On the other hand, the momentum is very precise
This is an eigenvector and the momentum operator
If this were the wave function of a particle
and you measure it's momentum it would be P
If you measured it's position it would be random all over the axis
very much well much worse than
but very much like these Sigma X and Sigma Z representations
where one maybe definite at the cost of the other one being
as in-definite as possible, in that case it's just one or minus one
Here that's much worse,
So when a particle is localized in momentum
It's completely delocalized in position
We wanna be able to say we want to
I would like to do the reciprocal thing also,
I like to go in the other direction
for that what we want to do is construct the notion called
the momentum spacewave function.
The Momentum space wave function is related to the probability amplitude
for finding different momenta,
so let's see if we can construct that for that
I think we finished it over here, alright
We defined in general we define a wave function
by taking the state vector
and projecting it onto eigenvectors of various observables
and that gives us the wave function
in the basis associated with that observables
If I project it onto an Eigen state of X
that gives me the wave function psi of X
If instead I project it onto a state of definite momentum
thatgives me something I can call the wave function in the momentum basis
It's not a function of X so it doesn't look like a wave in space
Doesn't look like a wave in space,
but it's called the wave function, and it's a function of momentum
What is that? Let's give it a name let's call it psi twiddle of P
Just of this I use the twiddle notation just to
remind you that it's a different thing
a different animal from the, from the X wave function
How do we calculate this?
Let's suppose we know
the X representation of the of the state vector psi of X
How do we calculate this?
Well we take the inner product of the state vector psi
with the vector P but we know what that is
Just the integral dx,
I think I've lost it,
Only that the only the only equation what was the psi-phi
equals integral of psi star of X phi of X d X
Okay so I want the inner product between P
Well I know the wave function of P in the position basis
It's just what is it? It's e to the minus i PX
over the square root of two pi if I remember right
So that's what we wrote down for psi of p of x,
that's this guy over here, and then we have to multiply that by psi of X
and integrate, but that's exactly equal to psi twiddle of P
withthe same notation that I used for Fourier transforms
Another words, the momentum state wave function psi twiddle of P
is exactly the Fourier transform of the position space wave function
That's the upshot
Momentum and position are related in the same way that
ordinary variables positions and Fourier variables are related
Okay so here we have, let's just call it psi twiddle of P
If you know what this is, if you know the wave function
in the position basis
you know everything that's enough
In fact you can recover the wave function in the momentum basis
and also the probability to find the particle with different momenta
After all, I have abuse the notation, there shouldn't be a capital psi here
This should be a smallpsi, it's a wave function
And of course the probability to measure a given value of momentum
is just psi twiddle star of P times psi twiddle of P
So what do you do?
In some way or another you know what the wave function of a particle is
Psi of X, but you may not be interested in measuring X
You are interested in measuring P
How do you determine the various probabilities for measuring different P
you take that X wave function you subject that to the Fourier transform
You find the Fourier transform of it,
and it's square is the probability for different momentum
This is extremely similar to going
from the Sigma Z basis the Sigma X basis
Go through it and see if you can find the similarities between two
>>So if you wanted to take a position to a momentum space
>>it would be .. partialpartial P
The operator P was equal to minus i d by dx
And you apply this to a position space wave function
You apply it to the position space wave function
To find out how it acts
X ,not quite parallel, not minus id by dpbut plus d by dp,
The minus sign difference has a great deal to do with this minus sign here
And you can work it out
>>This is the first time I've seen an explanation for Heisenberg
>>position versus momemtum, I assume that the relation would ..
>>in other pairs like time and energy
The time and energy is a funny one
Time is not usually regarded as an operator in quantum mechanics
It's not usually regarded as, although you could,
You know, you do measure time, you look at your watch
The hand of your watch is an observable and so in that sense
Clock readings can be thought of as observables
Something a little bit funny about them
I don't wanna get into it for now,
But usually in quantum mechanics time is just consider the parameter
by which state evolve
butthis is true if you have a clock for example
And you are interested in making that in making
an extremely accurate observation of the clock
It will be at the cost of a lack of a precision in the energy of the clock
>>So how does Heisenberg works in field? ~
Electrician magnetic field, just the almost anything you can think of
will have a conjugate variable, electric and magnetic field
What's that?
>>temperature and pressure?
No temperature and pressure are statistical mechanical variable;
And it's not quantum mechanical variables
What's that?
>>angular momentum
Okay, the angular momentum in angle
The angular momentum of the axial symmetric, axially symmetric system,
the angular momentum and the angular orientation would be another one
Okay there are lots of others,
usually for example if you have some field
Typically the field and it's time derivative are a conjugate variables
So there is all kinds of a, another questions?
>>Yes, it seems like you work from a discrete state,
>>observables of discrete states that continuous is a kind of subtle change
>>inrepresentation, and in that case, the discrete states,
>>the operators operate on the ket
>>The wave function was just expansionary
Yeah, yeah, yeah, but we could also
Remember we also represent the operators as matrices
and thekets as columns, but a column is just a list of values
Of an amplitude as a function of where it's lying
How high, you know, there is a function of eigenvalue
So it really is the same thing
It is closely related to the representation of operators as matrices
Just the concrete, the concrete action in a particular basis
when you write column vectors you write them in particular basis
Alright last remark, last remarkabout uncertainty is
The uncertainty principle for this particular example here
I'm not going to derive the uncertainty principle not today,
if we make it to it,
but it really is a very simple thing,
it is simply the statement that, it's a statement about Fourier transforms
and it transcends quantum mechanics
It's in the quantum mechanics anytime you have a pair of quantities
which are related by Fourier transform in this way
It's generally the case that the narrower one Fourier pair,
Or half of the Fourier pair is, the broader the other one is
Another words the narrower range of P,
the broader psi of X will be and vice versa
So I don't want to go into the a mathematical statement about the
about the uncertainty principle here,
but whatever it is,
it really just does have to do with the character of Fourier pairs
X and P in this case, we will come back to it I think
What we want to get onto was the Hamiltonian's particles
Just the simplest possible Hamiltonian particles
And how they govern the quantum mechanical evolution
Remember what the Hamiltonian is?
The Hamiltonian is thing
which first of all enters into the Schrodinger equation,
and which also governs the time evolution of the state vector
Hamiltonian is to be identify with the classical idea of energy
Just as it is in classical mechanics,
If we go back, we I,I discussed this earlier
but let's,let's
starting point was the idea of the unitary evolution of state vectors
That's state vectors evolved by unitary transformation
And then we said well what happens if you make a tiny little
Tiny little change in time,
that should correspond to some sort of differential change
in the state vector
and we found out that the differential change
was governed by a Hermitian operator
called the Hamiltonian, sorry if you have forgotten the details
I will go back to it now, not not right now,
but but you remember the equation
Equation for the evolution of the state vector
asi let's put our h bar in for the moment
Take them out again in a little while
d psi by dt,
the way the state vector we can write this in terms of state vectors
state vector is generally a function of time
the state changes with time, you can take the difference between vectors
and you can differentiate vectors with respect to time
if a vector happens to be time-dependent you can differentiate it
id psi by dt is equal to the Hamiltonian operator acting on psi
That's the time dependent Schrodinger equation
Wework it, I think we work out an example
for a spin processing in a magnetic field
Where wejust used the Hamiltonian one of the components of the spin
Here is a general form of the Schrodinger equation
The time dependent Schrodinger equation
And let's try out some simple Hamiltonians
See what kind of thing you can learn from them
I think we just study one or two, and then we will go on afterwards
The very simplest Hamiltonian, that I can write down
which is quite illustrative, nobody ever writes it down
But I gonna write it down anyway
H now H is an operator it's not just an operator, it's a Hermitian operator
H doesn't stand forHermitianit stands for Hamiltonian, but never mind
I'm gonna try H is equal to a number, the constant,
C for constant, times the momentum
Perfectly good thing, let's see what it does,
Let's see what kind of thing we learn from it
Is this a reasonable Hamiltonian for a particle?
Ya actually it is,you will find out in a moment what kind of particle
But it's not the usual thing,
the usual thing we will usually write for nonrelativistic particle?
p squared over two m huh?
Momentum squared over twice the mass
We will come back to that, but this is simpler
This is simpler and worth exploring first
just to see how the apparatus works
Everything here should be capitalized everything,
'cause they are all operators
Okay, but how is this represented in terms of wave functions?
In terms of wave functions and with wave function psi of X
Wave functions in the X basis and the momentum basis
wave function in the X basis are just projections onto the X eigenvectors
We can do that inside these equations here
What this reads then, it's i h bar, d psi of X by dt
this is the way the wave function changes,
is equal, now H is C times P so let's put the C there
and P is minus i h bar D byd X, so there is a minus an i and h bar
and a d by dx, psi of X
Okay what have I done?
I rewritten this equation in terms of wave functions
That there was the concrete representation psi of X
d psi of X by dt, and I've used here the assumption that
the Hamiltonian is just equal to C times the momentum
and the momentum is i minus ih bar d by d X
But this is of course, psi is not only a function of X
What is the psi the function of?Time
It's a function of time
because in general a state vector changes with time that's all
okay we can now let's cancel out the i h bars
And I just get d psi by dt,
is equal to minus C times d psi by d X
or d psi by dt plus d psi by d X with a C is equal to zero
That's a pretty simple equation  In fact it's so simple that I know what
Not only what a was, a solution is,
I know all of the solutions of this equation
Anybody know what the solution of this equations are?
The general solutions?
A function of X minus C t
Any function, let's let's leave it this way
Any function which is a function of X minus Ct
Another words it doesn't depend on X and T separately
It only depends on the combination X minus Ct
We will solve this equation
If I differentiate it with respect to t
That will be minus C times the derivative with respect to X
and that's all this equation says
Any function of this form will solve the Schrodinger equation
So let's think about a function of this form
What does it do? What does it look like?
You can start at t equals zero cross out t here
with any function psi of X,
of course we don't want take any function
I want my functions to be such that the total probability is equal to one
So the integral of psi star psi should be finite equal to one
They shouldn't blow up or they should be fall to zero nicely
So we can integrate them ,but they could do all,
They can do whatever you like
Some sort of lump, it can oscillate, may or may not oscillate
And rather general, and now we let t run
We let time go forward, what happens to this solution?
What happens to the solution is,
it's stay in exactly the same solution shape
except every feature of it moves with a velocity C
The features of it moves to the right with uniform velocity C
That's what this function is, it's just a function which is moves rigidly
without changing its shapeand of course it's a complex function
Sort of has a real part and an imaginary part
But both of them maintain exactly the same shape
and they just slide down the axis uniformly with a velocity C
Now I chose C for a reason, it's because it's speed of light
Is this a photon? Well this is not really
the correct description of photons,
but it's pretty close to the right description of neutrinos
At least neutrinos which will the speed of light
Real neutrinos probably move a little bit slower than the speed of light
but there are un-measurably so
So this would be a damn good description of one-dimensional neutrinos
Except that we would have to and another possibility that they can all
Thisis pure right moving neutrinos
The pure right moving neutrinos
They don't have a funny thing that the energy can be
We are gonna come back to this,
not not this quarter I think
But the energy can be both positive and negative
P is a thing which can be positive or negative
So this particle has the property
that it can have Positive and negative energy,
but that's not important here
is a picture of the wave function
moving down the axis with uniform velocity?
The whole probability distribution rigidly moves down the axis
what happens to the expectation value of X?
It move the same way
to the expectation value of X moves with a velocity Ct
and that's the quantum mechanics of the simple system.
I would just point out that if we compare this with a classical mechanics
of exactly the same system, Hamiltonian is equal to CP
How do we compare the, how do we do the classical physics?
We use Hamilton's equations,
so, here was mainly for this reason right here
that we did all quarter over classical mechanics last quarter
So they are not just for this one, but for also things like this
Hamilton's equations let's look at Hamilton's equations
Hamilton's equations are, dH bydp equals x dot,
and d H by dx equals minus P dot
dH by dt is just equal to C right?
DH by d X that's equal to zero
So what this says classically is that the momentum is conserved
Now we will come back to the conservation of momentum in quantum mechanics
but it also says that the position of the particle moves with velocity C
In quantum mechanics the whole probability distribution in this case
This is a very very simple case,
So the engineers just have a simpler answer
The whole probability distribution moves with
but in particular the expectation value of X moves with velocity C
so the expectation value of the position behaves according to
a classical equations of motion
Now that's,that's this as I said this is a very easy example
which is a little bit too simple for it to be perfectly general,
but the, but it does illustrate the,
so this would be the Schrodinger equation
for this very very simple Hamiltonian
I think we are about to,
Alright let's go a little more, a little more
And what about, andthis of course would make this a relativistic particles
would not be a nonrelativistic particle is a guy move the speed of light
>>Without using the C just some other numbers
>>would this be the correct Hamiltonian
>>for any particles moving in three-space?
No any particle which is always constrained into move
with the same velocity
So right,right so for example,
You know just the photons are the quantum electromagnetic field
Soundwaves and crystals also have quantum
Sound waves of phonons and at least at low energies
Those phonons move with uniform velocity
the uniform velocity being the speed of sound
so if you have a one-dimensional phonons
You would describe them in a similar way
>>Can you just do that, throw in a electron in three space
>>and it would follow that?
No electrons don't usually move with the speed of light
>>
No nononono,
you see this this law of physics for this particular kind of particles
says no matter how you throw it, with a whatever momentum you throw it with
it's always gonna move with in same way
>>You say equation in C and
With what?
>>You said replacing C with velocity V
The velocity V mean momentum
>>But P V is the same as ..
Not quite, P square over m, but that's close, that's close
Alright I will do one more thing,
For relativistic particle of course v is not p over m,
but you are on the right track yeah,
>>I was just imagining that any particle has a
wave function for it's position right?
>>And if it's moving in space that wave function is just moving
No nonono, you see that's, that's not quite right
Only for this very very simple situation does the wave function move
with this rigid behavior and maintain a shape
Not true. More generally, if you take a nonrelativistic electron
We are gonna workout it's equation in 2 minutes
The shape of its wave function is not maintained
it sort of wobbles and does things
it's sort of gradually falls apart disburses
diffuses disburses, whatever you wanna call it
So, Right, as I picked this one just because it's easy to solve.
But it doesn't represent the most general kind of motion of a particle
Alright so let's,let's talk about, let's take a guess
Let's take a guess for nonrelativistic particle
I think I already earlier showed you that
the equations of motion for expectation values quantum mechanically
are very closely related to the corresponding equations of motion
classically
Hamilton's equations and Poisson,Poisson bracket form of them
So you can imagine that if you want to represent the quantum mechanics
of asystem which is a which was classical physics you know
You basically use the same Hamiltonian
Now we will come back to that, we will come back to justify it better
But the natural Hamiltonian to guess for a nonrelativistic particle
is just good old p square over two m
This is not a particle with a force on it
This is a particle of no force on it, a free particle
The energy the Kinetic energy T
is equal to one half mass times velocity squared
Momentum is M times v ,
now we can rewrite the kinetic energy if that's all there is
Let's call it H is P squared over 2M
So that's the Hamiltonian for a classical particle
Notice this Hamiltonian has a funny feature
Particles can only move to the right there were no
There were no left moving motion
They all only move to the right
And that's a funnything, the asymmetry between left and right
has to do with the fact that P goes to minus P
when you invert left and right
the Hamiltonian changes sign when this this Hamiltonian when you
that's a funny thing,
you would, the energy of a particle with negative momentum
is negative, energy of a particle positive, Momentum is positive
That's a little bit weird, okay?
Non-ordinary nonrelativistic particle
its energy is independent to which way it's moving
and that's insured by the fact that the energy is proportional to p squared
not P
so let's start with the energy being P squared over to M
and work out the Schrodinger equation
For now we will be working out the genuine Schrodinger
Well the original version of the Schrodinger equation for free particle
Alright I will just write H is equal to P squared over 2M
H is also id by dt, now let's put h bar it just to the
Schrodinger would've done it - on psi
that's the left hand side thought of as an operator operating on the
onthe, sorry, that's i h bar d by DT
On the right hand side, Right hand side of the equation
It's just H acting on psi,
but H is P squared over 2M
So let's write that as one over 2M
And then what is P?
Whatever P is we will have to square it
But let's write down what P is first
Minus h bar i, i h bar, derivative with respect to X
But we have to square it,
P squared, squaring it just means multiplying it by itself
so let's square this i h bar squared
And then the square of the first derivative is the second derivative
It means you just apply it twicetime psi or on psi of X
That's it, that's the Schrodinger equation
For a ordinary nonrelativistic particle moving on a one-dimensional line
Let's leave out the h bars, i h bar d psi by dt,
is equal to minus h bar squared minus comes from minus i squared over 2M
d second psi by d X squared
This is a kind of wave equation, incidentally,
this is also a wave equation,
this is a wave equation and psi is a wave function
this is a wave equation, psi is also a wave function
This is the Schrodinger equation for an ordinary nonrelativistic particle
It has the property that waves of different wavelengths
move with different velocities
I'm getting a little tired, so I wanna go over it quick so,
But the waves of different wavelengths move with different velocities
because of that the wave function does not maintain its shape
And in fact, it tends to fall apart and the, and spread
wave function spreads out with time.
Unlike is a very simple case over here
In this case, no matter what the wavelength
No matter what the momentum is they all move with same velocity
Not so here different momentum move with different velocities
And so a wave with a given shape different parts of it
will move with different velocity
different wavelength different wavelengths and it will move with velocities
and it will fall apart
We will study it a little bit more in detail
We will be studying the behavior, but I think I
For more, please visit us@Stanford.edu